<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>external eXist Information</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <p>
    	Below is the information for installing eXist externally.  Also advise see your <a href="../dbclients.jsp">DB Clients and WebDav</a> page (for connecting a GUI client or WebDav to the db.).
    </p>
    <section name="Installing customized eXist externally">
      <p>
      	 You will find a customized eXist at Astrogrid that has certain settings already set.
      	 Located <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/org.astrogrid/zips/external_eXist.zip">here</a><br />
      	 Here are the instructions on how to run and install eXist:
      	 <ul>
	      	 <li>Unzip it on a desired machine.</li>
	      	 <li>Typically good to set a environment variable EXIST_HOME to the location of the unzipped directory.</li>
	      	 <li>By default eXist will run on port 6080, if this is not desired you can change this in EXIST_HOME/tools/jetty/etc/jetty.xml change 6080 to desired port number.</li>
	      	 <li>Go to EXIST_HOME/bin and run startup.sh normally in the background so it is always going.</li>
	      	 <li>You may go to <a href="http://exist.sourceforge.net/quickstart.html">here</a> for info on installing as a service and other details about eXist.</li>
	      	 <li>When you come to configuration section of the Registry you will need to change a JNDI property "xmldb.uri" to xmldb:exist://{machinehost}:6080/exist/xmlrpc</li>
		</ul>	      	 
      </p>
      </section>
	  <section name="Installing eXist externally from eXist website">
		<p>
			You may for your own reasons want to install eXist straight from eXist website at http://exist.sourceforge.net.
			The download file is on the home page of eXist and see the <a href="http://exist.sourceforge.net/quickstart.html">quickstart guide</a> for 
			other info on installing such as on headless systems. <br />
		    Once installed here are some things to be customized for the astrogrid registry:
		    <ul>
		        <li>in the bin/functions.d/eXist-settings.sh set set_exist_options() to have a -Xmx400M for 400mb memory. Only neede for Full Registries
		        *For windows change the 128000k to 400M in the startup.bat. Memory is not much of an issue as much with its now streaming api service, but advised to increase.
		        </li>
		    	<li>Finally remember much like the above instructions to change your xmldb.uri JNDI property to your eXist and by default eXist runs on port 8080 this can be changed
		    	at EXIST_HOME/tools/jetty/etc/jetty.xml you can change the 8080 to 6080 for instance</li>
		   </ul>
<br />
		</p>
	</section>
  </body>
</document>