<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<Glossary>

<entry name="Cone Search">
<meaning>

<p>or "sky position neighbour location". The process of locating celestial
objects or observation pointings located within a certain distance from
a reference position. The search is performed in one or more catalogues
of objects or observations.</p>

<p>The reference location should be expressed in Right Ascention and
Declination in the J2000 reference frame.
</p>

<p>Typically you should specify the reference direction (or a file with
positions) and a distance to perform the search.</p>
</meaning>
</entry>

<entry name="Resource Locator">
<meaning>
<p> IVO provides you with the possibility of accessing different resources
around the world.

Locating these resources may be the difference between being able to
perform a task or not.</p>

<p>Locating Images, spectra, catalogues by different criteria is what we
offer. You can locate all catalogues related to quasars by searching for
QSO or quasar in the title, or locate catalogues which contain infrared
data by looking for a column UCD (which describes the type of quantity a
column holds) describing infrared quantities.
</p>

<p> You may be interested in finding images which have intersection with a
list of positions of your own, ie, you want images of the sky around those
positions in some wavelength regime.</p>
</meaning>
</entry>

<entry name="pending">
<meaning>
</meaning>
</entry>

<entry name="UCD">
<meaning>
</meaning>
</entry>

<entry name="Registry">
<meaning>
Is the service which stores and serves information about what's available
in IVO-land.
</meaning>
</entry>

<entry name="Glossary">
<meaning>
<span class="courier">[glo za ree]</span> The service which provides
(short) definitions relevant to all component of astrogrid.<break /><break />

Do not bother moving the mouse to this window only to close it. Click the
same active area you just used to close this window. This feature works the
same throughout the different pages of AstroGrid.
</meaning>
</entry>


</Glossary>
