<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
<properties>
   <author email="nw@jb.man.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
   <author email="mch@roe.ac.uk">Martin Hill</author>
   <title>Connecting to Databases</title>
</properties>
<!-- packrat requirments
1 INSTALL document per component, to include:
Where and how to download the installation kit
How to deploy and configure
How to administer (stop/start/restart)
How to trouble-shoot
-->
<body>
<section name="Introduction">

<subsection name="A JDBC Database, or other datastore"><p>
The Datacenter Server connects to a back-end system that contains the data collection to be published.
The commonest form of back-end system is a relational database - installation instructions for other kinds of back-end system
are included in the web-application bundle.
<p/>
The datacenter server can connect to any RDBMS that provides a
 <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jdbc/">JDBC</a> driver; it has been tested with the following
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> - the MM-MySQL JDBC Driver
</li><li><a href="http://hsqldb.sourceforge.net/">HSQL</a> - pure-Java RDBMS. For testing purposes or serving small databases based on textfiles.
</li><li>Microsoft SQL Server - <i>find driver &amp; details</i>
</li></ul>
<p />

Many RDBMS have a user account system, where different accounts may be provided with different acces privileges to the database.
 If this is the case with your target RDBMS, we recommend that a new user account be created for the datacenter service.
<p />
The datacenter account should only have read / query privileges granted. <b>Do not</b> grant permissions to write to
tables / create tables / delete tables, or to access other databases or tables than those that are to be published -
these abilities are not needed and present a security risk.
<p />
Refer to the documentation for the target RDBMS for details on account creation and access privileges.
<p />
You may also wish to consider making a duplicate of the original data collection database, or even running a separate
RDBMS server on a different machine specifically for access from web-services.
</p></subsection>
</section>
<section name="Install JDBC Driver">
<p>
Acquire the jar file containing the JDBC driver for your chosen database and copy it (along with any other jars it depends upon) into the
<tt>${CATALINA_HOME}/common/lib</tt> directory.
</p>
</section>



<section name="References"><ul>
<li><a href="http://www.astrogrid.org">Astrogrid Homepage</a>
</li><li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jdbc/">JDBC</a>
</li><li><a href="http://servlet.java.sun.com/products/jdbc/drivers">List of known JDBC drivers</a>
</li></ul></section>


</body>
</document>
