<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
<properties>
   <author email="nw@jb.man.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
   <author email="mch@roe.ac.uk">Martin Hill</author>
   <title>PAL Installation</title>
</properties>
<!-- packrat requirments
1 INSTALL document per component, to include:
Where and how to download the installation kit
How to deploy and configure
How to administer (stop/start/restart)
How to trouble-shoot
-->
<body>
<section name="Introduction">
<p>
This document describes how to publish a data collection using an Astrogrid Datacenter Server.
To do this, carry out the following steps:
<ul>
<li>Install the system pre-requisites
</li><li>Download PAL
</li><li>Deploy PAL
</li><li>Configure the database
</li><li>Configure the connection to the data collection
</li><li>Create a  description of the data collection
</li><li>Restart the servlet container
</li><li>Test the installation
</li><li>Add the data collection with the Astrogrid Registry
</li></ul>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Pre-requisites">
<p>
<a href="pre-requisites.html">This page</a> describes the software components that must be installed and configured before installing the Datacenter Server.
The Datacenter Server relies upon the following software components, which must be
installed and configured before installing the Datacenter Server.
</p>
</section>


<section name="Download PAL">
<p>
The publishers astrogrid library is distributed as a J2EE Web Application (.war) file named <tt>pal.war</tt>
To add a dependency on PAL to your own project, add the following to your <a href="http://maven.apache.org">maven</a> <tt>project.xml</tt>
<source>
   &lt;dependencies&gt;
   ...
   &lt;dependency&gt;
   &lt;groupId&gt;astrogrid-datacenter&lt;/groupId&gt;
   &lt;artifactId&gt;pal&lt;/artifactId&gt;
   &lt;version&gt;SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
   &lt;type&gt;war&lt;/type&gt;
   &lt;/dependency&gt;
   ...
   &lt;dependencies&gt;
</source>
Alternately, the latest snapshot of PAL can be downloaded directly from<br />
 <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/astrogrid-datacenter/wars/pal-SNAPSHOT.war"
 >http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/astrogrid-datacenter/wars/pal-SNAPSHOT.war</a>
</p>
<p>
Or the latest stable release (It4.1) from<br/>
 <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/astrogrid-datacenter/wars/pal-Itn04_1.war"
 >http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/astrogrid-datacenter/wars/pal-Itn04_1.war</a>
 </p>
</section>

<section name="Deploy PAL">

You can use the Tomcat manager to install PAL (see the Tomcat manager instructions)
or you can do it by hand:
<source>
$ cp pal.war ${CATALINA_HOME}/webapps
</source>
<p>
Copy <tt>pal.war</tt> to the <tt>webapps</tt> directory of your tomcat installation and
restart your server:
</p>
<source>
$ ${CATALINA_HOME}/bin/shutdown.sh
$ ${CATALINA_HOME}/bin/startup.sh
</source>
<p>
Once tomcat has been restarted, the pal web application will be unpackaged into the directory <tt>webapps/pal</tt>. If installed on your
machine in the default location, the web application root will be <a href="http://localhost:8080/pal">http://localhost:8080/pal</a>.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Configure PAL">
<p>

<a href="configuration.html">This page</a> describes in detail how to configure
your datacenter. However once PAL has been installed, it should be possible to
run the <a href="self-test">installation tests</a> and some cone <a href="query-form">queries</a>
 on it, as it contains a simple SQL database by default.
<p/>
Read the <a href="configuration.html">configuration page</a> before going on, as you
will need to make a new configuration file to connect to your data.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Connect to your data">

<a href="connectdata.html">This page</a> describes how to configure and connect to your data.

</section>


<section name="Describe your data">
<p>You need to write a description of the data collection provided by your installation. This document should conform to <b>(what schema?)</b>
The location of this file can be set in the configuration file. The default location is <tt>metadata.xml</tt> on the classpath.
</p>
Finally your newly-published dataset must be added to an Astrogrid Registry. Somehow.
</section>

<section name="Verify the installation">
<p>
Pal comes packaged with a series of self-test scripts. To run these, visit the web application root,
and navigate to the <i>self-test</i> page. Inspect the result from each script - no
errors should appear on the output.
</p>


<subsection name="Logging">
<p>
The datacenter uses 'commons-logging' to log messages; on a Tomcat server this is
routed to the server's <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/log4j/docs/">Log4J</a> logger.
A default log4j properties file is included in the distribution, and can be found at
<tt>/WEB-INF/classes/log4j.properties</tt> in the web application.
<p/>
By default, the properties file causes INFO and higher messages to go to std.out (these
can be found in the catalina.out file when using Tomcat), INFO and higher messages are
stored in pal.log, and DEBUG and higher messages are stored in a rolling file (it is
size limited) called pal-debug.log.  These latter two are found in ${CATALINA_HOME}/logs/ when
running under Tomcat.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Running test queries">
<p>
The datacenter web application contains a simple web form that submits a query to the datacenter service.

<p />
In addition, the client delegate jar contains simple command-line tool that will fire a adql query at the server and display the VOTABLE response. You need
to write an adql query that conforms to the adql schema (downloadable from the web application) and save it to a file.

<source>
$ java org.astrogrid.datacenter.ui.DatacenterCommander adql <i>&lt;url-endpoint&gt;</i> <i>&lt;query-xml-file&gt;</i>
</source>

</p>
</subsection>
</section>


<section name="References"><ul>
<li><a href="http://www.astrogrid.org">Astrogrid Homepage</a>
</li><li><a href="http://java.sun.com">Java Homepage</a>
</li><li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Jakarta Tomcat Homepage</a>
</li><li><a href="http://ws.apache.org/axis/">Apache Axis Homepage</a>
</li></ul></section>


</body>
</document>
