<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
<properties>
	<author email="nw@jb.man.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
	<title>PAL for Other back ends.</title>
</properties>

<body>
<section name="Introduction">
<p>
The datacenter server is designed so that different back-end implementations can be plugged into the system.
The back end implementation to use is specified in the system configuration file. You may provide your own implementation
and plug into the datacenter server.
</p>
<subsection name="Requirements">
<p>
A back-end implementation must extend the abstract class <tt>org.astrogrid.datacenter.queriers.DatabaseQuerier</tt>. The compiled
class, and all other libraries it depends upon must be available on the web-application's classpath.
<p/>
<b>Having to extend an abstract class is a bad idea for the follwing reasons. We plan to add a SPI interface to code against instead</b>
<ol>
<li>Prevents implementation classes extending any other class</li>
<li>The service interface is not clearly defined - the abstract class contains details
that should not be manipulated by the back-emd implementation</li>
</ol>

</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Development">
<p>
The classes of interest are in the packages:
<dl>
<dt><tt>org.astrogrid.datacenter.queriers</tt></dt>
<dd>DatabaseQuerier is the abstract base class for back-end implementations, currently. QueryTranslator is an
abstract base class for translating ADQL queries into the format required by the back end</dd>
<dt><tt>org.astrogrid.datacenter.queriers.sql</tt></dt>
<dd>SqlQuerier is a vanilla implementation of a JDBC-driven back end. It uses SqlQueryTranslator to convert ADQL queries
into simple SQL statements</dd>
<dt><tt>org.astrogrid.datacdenter.queriers.[mysql|hsql|sybase|..]</tt></dt>
<dd>Specializations of the vanilla SQLQuerier for specific database flavours. Possibly some use as examples</dd>
</dl>
<p />
<a href="server-dist/astrogrid-datacenter-server-HEAD-src.zip">Source</a> and
 <a  href="server-dist/astrogrid-datacenter-server-HEAD.zip">Binary</a>
 distributions of the datacenter server code can be downloaded from this web application.
 The distributions contain documentation and javadoc, which is also <a href="server/index.html">available in this web application</a>
<p/>
<b>Do something about dependent libraries</b>
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Possibilities">
<subsection name="Writing a querier for another JDBC database"><p>
The standard JDBC database querier <tt>org.astrogrid.datacenter.queriers.sql.SqlQuerier</tt> should be suitable for most database flavours,
given an appropriate JDBC driver. Situations where it is not applicable split into:
<dl>
<dt>The generated SQL is not compatible with my database</dt>
<dd>Extend the <tt>org.astrogrid.datacenter.queriers.sql.SqlQueryTranslator</tt> to provide new translation rules for the offending
ADQL clauses. The query translator to use can be specified in the system configuration file.</dd>
<dt>My database requires some special initialization</dt>
<dd>Subclass the standard SqlQuerier to perform the initialization.</dd>
</dl>
</p></subsection>

<subsection name="Adapter Servers"><p>
Another possible form of back end is one that does not retrieve data from a local store, but instead acts as an adapter for an existing
datacenter - possibly another web service. An adapter server can integrate a legacy web service into Astrogrid without requiring changes to
the existing code. Its task is to translate the ADQL queries it receives into a form understood by the legacy service, perform the call to the service
and then massage any results into the format expected by astrogrid.

<p />
See the cds-delegate example back-end for an example of an adapter server.

</p></subsection>

<subsection name="XMLDatabases" ><p>
Shouldn't be too hard. Would need to transform the ADQL into whatever query language the XMLDB uses - maybe XQuery, and then transform
results of query again into a VOTABLE for output.
</p></subsection>

<subsection name="Something else??">
<p>
We'd be interested to hear of your experiences integrating other back-end systems into PAL. We'd also appreciate code donations, to
build up a larger library of back-end implementations.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

</body>
</document>
