<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Context entries</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Context entries">
            <p>
                The AstroGrid Community WebService uses JNDI entries to lookup the following resources.
                <ul>
                    <li>The service identifier</li>
                    <li>The database configuration</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <subsection name="Community identifier">
                <p>
                    The Community WebService needs to know the IVO identifier for the Community service.
                    This identifier forms the base for the IVO identifiers used to access objects within this Community service.
                </p>
                <p>
                    For example, if the CommunityIdentifier is set to
                    <ul>
                        <li><code>org.astrogrid.test.xyz</code></li>
                    </ul>
                    then the IVO identifier for the service would be
                    <ul>
                        <li><code>ivo://org.astrogrid.test.xyz</code></li>
                    </ul>
                    and the IVO identifier for an Account <i>abc</i> in the Community service would be
                    <ul>
                        <li><code>ivo://org.astrogrid.test.xyz/abc</code></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    In order to make it available to the WebService, the Community identifier needs to be
                    configured in a JNDI <code>Environment</code> property in the server configuration or
                    WebApp context.
<source><![CDATA[
<Environment
    name="org.astrogrid.community.ident"
    type="java.lang.String"
    value="org.astrogrid.test.xyz"/>
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    When the WebService is installed, the install toolkit reads the Community identifier from the
                    <code>install.properties</code> file and automatically configures the JNDI <code>Environment</code>
                    property in the Tomcat configuration.
<source><![CDATA[
# Local community name.
# Change this property to set the service identifier.
org.astrogrid.community.ident=org.astrogrid.test.xyz
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The install toolkit contains test data files for the following communities :
                    <ul>
                        <li>Cambridge <code>(ivo://<b>org.astrogrid.test.cam</b>)</code></li>
                        <li>Leicester <code>(ivo://<b>org.astrogrid.test.le</b>)</code></li>
                        <li>Edinburgh <code>(ivo://<b>org.astrogrid.test.roe</b>)</code></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Database resource">
                <p>
                    The Community WebService needs access to a local database to store the Community data.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In order to make it available to the WebService, the database needs to be configured in
                    a JNDI <code>Resource</code> entry in the server configuration or WebApp context.
<source><![CDATA[
<Resource
    name="jdbc/org.astrogrid.community.database"
    type="javax.sql.DataSource"
    auth="Container"/>
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    When the WebService is installed, the install toolkit automatically configures the JNDI
                    <code>Resource</code> property in the Tomcat configuration.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Database properties">
                <p>
                    In addition to the database <code>Resource</code> entry, the database properties need to be
                    configured in a <code>ResourceParams</code> entry in the server configuration or WebApp context.
<source><![CDATA[
<ResourceParams
    name="jdbc/org.astrogrid.community.database">
    <parameter>
        <name>url</name>
        <value>jdbc:hsqldb:/var/astrogrid/org.astrogrid.community</value>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
        <name>driverName</name>
        <value>jdbc:hsqldb:/var/astrogrid/org.astrogrid.community</value>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
        <name>driverClassName</name>
        <value>org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver</value>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
        <name>username</name>
        <value>sa</value>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
        <name>password</name>
        <value/>
    </parameter>
</ResourceParams>
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    When the WebService is installed, the install toolkit reads the database location from the
                    <code>install.properties</code> file and automatically configures the <code>ResourceParams</code>
                    entries in the Tomcat configuration.
<source><![CDATA[
# Database files location.
# Change this property if you want to relocate the database files.
database.home=/var/astrogrid/community
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p style="font-size:x-small;font-style:italic;margin:20px">
                    <img style="float:left;margin-right:5px" src="images/note.gif"/>
                    The WebService needs to have read/write access to the database files.
                    Make sure that the system account that Tomcat runs as can read and write files in this directory.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
