<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community quick install</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Service install">
            <p>
                The install toolkit contains all of the components required to install and configure the AstroGrid Community WebService.
            </p>
            <p>
                The toolkit includes the following components :
                <ul>
                    <li>Ant script</li>
                    <li>Ant properties</li>
                    <li>WebService war file</li>
                    <li>3rd party libraries</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <subsection name="Required components">
                <p>
                    The install toolkit requires the following pre-requisites installed on the target system(s).
                    <ul>
                        <li>Apache Ant <i>(recomended version 1.5.4)</i></li>
                        <li>Apache Tomcat <i>(recomended version 4.1.24)</i></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Service properties">
                <p>
                    The install toolkit uses the following properties, configured in the <code>install.properties</code> file supplied with the toolkit.
                    <ul>
                        <li>org.astrogrid.community.ident <i> - the ivo name of your Community.</i></li>
                        <li>database.home <i> - the location of the Community database files.</i></li>
                    </ul>
<source><![CDATA[
# Your community name.
# Change this property to set the service identifier.
org.astrogrid.community.ident=org.astrogrid.localhost

# Database files location.
# The default is to put the database files in '/var/astrogrid'.
# Change this property if you want to relocate the database files.
database.home=/var/astrogrid/community
]]></source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Local install">
                <p>
                    The install toolkit can install the WebService directly into a Tomcat instance on the local system.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Assuming that the pre-requisites are already installed, and the service properties have been configured, executing the <code>install</code> Ant task will automatically install and configure the WebService.
<source><![CDATA[
ant -f install.xml install
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    This will install the basic WebService into Tomcat container.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To install and configure the database, refer to the <a href="database-install.html">Database install</a> page.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Remote deploy">
                <p style="font-size:x-small;font-style:italic;margin:20px">
                    <img style="float:left;margin-right:5px" src="images/note.gif"/>
                    Remote deployment is not implemented in the current release.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The install toolkit can also deploy the WebService into a Tomcat server running on a remote system.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Deploying the WebService on a remote system requires Tomcat installed and running on the target system, and Ant installed on the local system.
                    Assuming that the pre-requisites are already installed, executing the <code>deploy</code> Ant task will automatically deploy the WebService on the target machine.
<source><![CDATA[
ant -f install.xml deploy \
    -Dtomcat.host=host.astrogrid.org \
    -Dtomcat.manager.name=xyz \
    -Dtomcat.manager.pass=xyz
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Alternatively, the Tomcat properties can be set by providing a local properties file, <code>tomcat.properties</code>.
<source><![CDATA[
#
# Target deployment hostname.
# Used by the remote deployment task.
# Change this property to specify a remote system.
tomcat.host=localhost

#
# Tomcat manager name and password
# Change these properties to match the settings on the target system.
tomcat.manager.name=QWERTY
tomcat.manager.pass=qwerty
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    In which case, the Ant command can be simplified to the following.
<source><![CDATA[
ant -f install.xml deploy
]]></source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
