<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="jl99@star.le.ac.uk">Jeff Lusted</author>
        <title>Portal User Guide - Resource Browser</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Resource Browser Contents">
<p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="#Catalog_Search">Catalog Search</a></li>
<li><a href="#Task_Search">Task Search</a></li>
<li><a href="#Browse_Filestores">Browse Filestores</a></li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">
<p>
The Resource Browser is a facility for searching the Astrogrid Registry. The registry is THE critical repository of information in
Astrogrid, containing information on astronomical datasources, on tools that can be used to process those datasources or data derived
from those datasources in a workflow, and on the location of MySpace servers (Jeff: yet to be implemented). The main page Resource 
Browser (reachable by using the portal's navigation bar) is indeed a tool for exploring the Registry. You can examine the results of 
the searches, but the searches are read only. You cannnot update the registry using this facility. Moreover, the results cannot be 
immediately used. It is more of an exploratory medium to get to grips with the registry. 
<br/><br/>
The emphasis with the microbrowsers is somewhat different. These provide the same facilities as depicted here and in the same format
(in fact if you're not careful you can mistake a microbrowser for the main browser they look so similar), 
but at the service of another Astrogrid component. In these situations, the search is being done in a specific context, like 
finding a suitable astronomical datasource for building a query, or finding a suitable task for processing votable in a workflow. In 
contradistinction, the main browser (the Resource Browser) is really for your intellectual curiosity in what is possible to find
in the registry.
<br/><br/>
On initial entry the <a href="../example-pages/resources.html" target="_top">main page</a> gives a choice of the three search dialogues available.
</p>
<a href="#Resource_Browser_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Catalog Search">
<p>The <a href="../example-pages/catalog-search.html" target="_top">catalog search box</a> is divided into two main areas, one labelled 
General Constraints and the other area divided into specific searches based on Wavelength, Mission and Keyword.  
There is also a control area at the bottom.
</p>
<subsection name="General Constraints">
<p>Every resource in the registry has a name, publisher, title and description. You can enter text for all or 
any of these fields to search upon. The idea to grasp is that searching using these particular fields is 
always on a "contains" basis and is always case insensitive. So, for instance, if you enter "mssl" in the name
field, the search will find all resources which have the string "mssl" (or "MSSL") somewhere in their name.
There is a control field at the bottom which enables the constraints to be switched from logical AND 
to logical OR. So the alternatives are:
<ul>
<li>[Resource name] AND [Resource publisher] AND [Resource title] AND [Description]</li>
<li>[Resource name] OR [Resource publisher] OR [Resource title] OR [Description]</li>
</ul>
Just to emphasize once more, each of these constraints is always on a contains basis.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Wavelength Mission Keyword">
<p>
The right hand area contains three list boxes labeled Wavelength, Mission and Keyword:
<ul>
<li>Wavelength. Each datasource in the registry can have one or more entries against waveband, indicating
that the source contains data for those wavebands.</li>
<li>Mission. Each datasource can be tagged by the observatory or facility used to collect the data.</li>
<li>Keyword. Each datasource can have a number of relevant keywords entered against it in the registry. The keywords are
drawn from the <a href="http://msowww.anu.edu.au/library/thesaurus/" target="_top">IAU Astronomy Thesaurus</a></li>
</ul>
In each list box more than one choice can be selected by using the Ctrl key with the left mouse button.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Using The Search Facility">
<p>
The default search technique is 
<ul>
<li>For each area to logically AND its individual search arguments together. For instance, it is possible to choose 
datasources covering Radio and Xray by making sure both are selected in the Wavelength list box. </li>
<li>For all four areas to logically AND together. For instance, you can choose a catalog with
resource name containing "mssl" with wavelength "radio" and ignore mission and keyword. Areas where nothing is selected
are not used.</li>
</ul>
The defaults can be changed selectively by the control fields at the bottom of each area and between each area from 
logical ANDs to logical ORs. The bottom box of the dialogue provides for a blanket change of search action between
the areas, again switching between AND and OR. And if you need to, you can reset the whole form by choosing the reset button. 
Reasonably sophisticated searches can be built up using combinations of AND-ing and OR-ing criteria together. However,
there is a balance to be struck and if you are too restrictive the search is likely to find no appropriate entries.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Examining The Results">
<p>You can see the basic display of a search that returned one item 
<a href="../example-pages/catalog-search-results.html" target="_top">here</a>. For each item returned there is some high level
information and at least two buttons: one for curation details and one giving the actual XML entry held in the registry.
The latter can be rather verbose and will only be of interest to those wanting to delve into the lower levels of the
registry. If the catalogue entry contains table information, there will also be third 
<a href="../example-pages/catalog-search-results-column.html" target="_top">column button</a> present, which when 
pressed will show a line of details for each column. The details shown are, for each column:
<ul>
<li>Name</li>
<li>Description if present</li>
<li>Type</li>
<li>Units if present</li>
<li>UCD if present</li>
</ul>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Catalog Search in the Microbrowser"><p>
The catalog search facility is invocable from the Query Editor, when it is then known as a microbrowser. 
At that point it is possible to select a table from the search results to be included in the current query being edited.
The above example, but in the microbrowser version, is shown 
<a href="../example-pages/mb-catalog-search-results-column.html" target="_top">here</a>. The Select button is the trigger for the
metadata to be pasted into the query.
</p>
</subsection>
<a href="#Resource_Browser_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Task Search">
<p>The task search is a much simpler search than the catalog search. It will retrieve instances of software programs
that can be run as tasks within a workflow. As a program (e.g. SExtractor) can have many instances registered as available across 
the Astrogrid network, it is possible to retrieve a number of items for even a very basic search, where the same task has
been deployed on more than one site. </p>
<subsection name="General Constraints">
<p>
The <a href="../example-pages/task-search.html" target="_top">task search box</a> only has
General Constraints with a control at the bottom to switch between logical AND and logical OR.
The example shows its use after a search using the string "extractor" in the Task Name field.
As with the catalog search General Constraints, the search is undertaken on a "contains" basis,
so all tasks whose name contains the string "extractor" have been retrieved. The application definition
given in this example has been expanded <a href="../example-pages/task-search-appdefinition.html" target="_top">here</a>.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Task Search in the Microbrowser"><p>
The task search facility is invocable from the Workflow Editor, when it is then known as a microbrowser. 
At that point it is possible to select a task from the search results to be included in the current workflow step 
being edited. The above example, but in the microbrowser version, is shown 
<a href="../example-pages/mb-task-search.html" target="_top">here</a>. The Select button is the trigger for the task to be inserted 
into the workflow step.
</p>
</subsection>
<a href="#Resource_Browser_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Browse Filestores">
<p>This facility is still to be developed</p>
<a href="#Resource_Browser_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

</body>
</document>
