<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community resolver toolkit</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Login task">
            <p>
                The resolver toolkit contains an Ant task to login to an AstroGrid Community service.
                Validating an Account identifier and password and returning a SecurityToken.
            </p>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;font-style:italic;margin:20px">
                <img style="float:left;margin-right:5px" src="images/note.gif"/>
                Before using the login tasks, check that the Account identifier has been set to point to a valid Community and Account.
                <br/>
                See <a href="resolver-toolkit.html#Resolver properties">Resolver properties</a>
            </p>
            <p>
                    The following Ant script fragment installs the password resolver task.
<source><![CDATA[
<taskdef name="login.task" classname="org.astrogrid.community.resolver.ant.CommunityPasswordResolverTask">
    <classpath refid="resolver.classpath"/>
</taskdef>
]]></source>
            </p>
            <subsection name="Live registry">
                <p>
                    The <code>login.live</code> Ant task uses a live Registry service to resolve the endpoint of a Community
                    service, and then calls the Community service to validate the Account identifier and password.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The following command will run the login task, using a live Registry service to resolve the Community service.
<source><![CDATA[
ant -f resolver.xml login.live
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The following Ant script fragment calls the password resolver task, using a live Registry service to resolve the Community service.
<source><![CDATA[
<login.task
    registry="${org.astrogrid.registry.url}"
    account="${org.astrogrid.community.account}"
    password="qwerty"
    />
]]></source>
                    In this mode, the task requires the following parameters :
                    <ul>
                        <li>registry <i> - The endpoint URL for an AstroGrid Registry service</i></li>
                        <li>account <i> - The IVO identifier for the Account</i></li>
                        <li>password <i> - The Account password</i></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    If the login succeeds, then the task will print out a new security token value, returned from the Community service.
                    The task will also store the token value in an Ant property called <code>org.astrogrid.community.token</code>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Local registry">
                <p style="font-size:x-small;font-style:italic;margin:20px">
                    <img style="float:left;margin-right:5px" src="images/note.gif"/>
                    There are reported problems when using the local registry files on a Windows system.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <code>login.local</code> Ant task uses local Registry files to resolve the endpoint of a Community
                    service, and then calls the Community service to validate the Account identifier and password.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The following command will run the login task, using local Registry files to resolve the Community service.
<source><![CDATA[
ant -f resolver.xml login.local
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The following Ant script fragment calls the password resolver task, using local Registry properties to resolve the Community service.
<source><![CDATA[
<login.task
    properties="${basedir}/config/registry.properties"
    account="${org.astrogrid.community.account}"
    password="qwerty"
    />
]]></source>
                    In this mode, the task requires the following parameters :
                    <ul>
                        <li>properties <i> - The location of the local Registry properties file</i></li>
                        <li>account <i> - The IVO identifier for the Account</i></li>
                        <li>password <i> - The Account password</i></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    If the login succeeds, then the task will print out a new security token value, returned from the Community service.
                    The task will also store the token value in an Ant property called <code>org.astrogrid.community.token</code>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
