<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
  <author email="nw@jb.man.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
        <title>Configuration</title>
</properties>

<body>



<section name="Configuration"><p>
The component may be manually configued using the standard astrogrid config system - i.e. setting properties as environment variables, or in a configuration file (<tt>astrogrid.properties</tt>), or within the JNDI service in Tomcat. See the general <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/common/apidocs/org/astrogrid/config/FailbackConfig.html">config documentation</a> for details.</p>
</section>

<section name="Configuration Properties">
<p>
The configuration properties that JES understands are as follows
</p>
<subsection name="Working Directory"><p>
JES requires a directory in which to store workflow transcripts, and other bookeeping information. Jes will create a series of directories under the direcory given in the <tt>jes.jobfactory.file.basedir</tt> property. This base directory must be writable by Tomcat (and JES given permission under any security manager you may be running).
</p></subsection>

<subsection name="Registry Endpoint"><p>
The property <tt>astrogrid.registry.endpoint</tt> should contain the URL endpoint of the Registry webservice this JES is to use.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Callback Endpoints"><p>
When JES dispatches a step to a CEA server, it needs to tell the server where to send notification of the step execution. The properties <tt>jes.monitor.endpoint.url</tt> and <tt>jes.results.endpoint.url</tt> contain the absolute URL endpoints of the callback webservices for this JES server. These always follow the same pattern</p>
<source>
jes.monitor.endpoint.url=http://<i>server.name</i>:<i>port</i>/<i>jes-context</i>/services/JobMonitorService
jes.results.endpoint.url=http://<i>server.name</i>:<i>port</i>/<i>jes-context</i>/services/ResultListener
</source>
<p>
Where <i>server.name</i> is the DNS resolvable name (<b>not 'localhost'</b>) of the machine the Tomcat is running on, <i>port</i> is the port that Tomcat is listening on, and <i>jes-context</i> is the context in Tomcat that the jes service is installed at.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

<section name="Required Properties">
<p>
JES also requires the following keys to be set. Don't alter the values - these keys just need to be as follows for a deployed JES Server.</p>
<source>
jes.locator=registry
jes.store=file
#org.astrogrid.registry.result.version=0.9
</source>
</section>
<section name="Example Configuration File">
<source>
# file: astrogrid.properties - sample configuration file for a JES Server
# Working directory for jes
jes.jobfactory.file.basedir=/home/tomcat/jes

#Registry Endpoint
org.astrogrid.registry.query.endpoint=http://capc49.ast.cam.ac.uk/galahad-registry/services/RegistryQuery

#Callback Endpoints
jes.monitor.endpoint.url=http://my.server.name:8080/astrogrid-jes/services/JobMonitorService
jes.results.endpoint.url=http://my.server.name:8080/astrogrid-jes/services/ResultListener


#Required Properties.
org.astrogrid.registry.result.version=0.9
jes.locator=registry
jes.store=file
</source>

</section>
</body>
</document>
