<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
  <author email="nw@jb.man.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
        <title>Configuration</title>
</properties>

<body>



<section name="Configuration">
<p>
You should set the configuration by editing the component's properties, using the
editor pages built into the component. This is accessible via the 'administration controls' menu
on the left-hand side-bar of the web pages included in the component itself (so you won't see it
if you're reading this on the AstroGrid web site).
The editor pages include specific instructions for applying the new configuration to a 
JES running in a Tomcat container.
The meaning of the properties is discussed below.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Configuration Properties">
<p>
The configuration properties that JES understands are as follows
</p>
<subsection name="Working Directory"><p>
JES requires a directory in which to store workflow transcripts, and other bookeeping information. Jes will create a series of directories under the direcory given in the <tt>jes.jobfactory.file.basedir</tt> property. This base directory must be writable by Tomcat (and JES given permission under any security manager you may be running).
</p></subsection>

<subsection name="Registry Endpoint"><p>
The property <i>org.astrogrid.registry.endpoint</i> should contain the URL endpoint of the Registry webservice this JES is to use.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Callback Endpoints"><p>
When JES dispatches a step to a CEA service, it needs to tell that service where to send notification of the step execution. 
The properties <tt>jes.monitor.endpoint.url</tt> and <tt>jes.results.endpoint.url</tt> contain the absolute URL endpoints 
of the callback webservices for this JES server. These always follow the same pattern:</p>
<source>
jes.monitor.endpoint.url=http://<i>server.name</i>:<i>port</i>/<i>jes-context</i>/services/JobMonitorService
jes.results.endpoint.url=http://<i>server.name</i>:<i>port</i>/<i>jes-context</i>/services/ResultListener
</source>
<p>
where <i>server.name</i> is the DNS-resolvable name of the machine the Tomcat is running on, 
<i>port</i> is the port that Tomcat is listening on, and <i>jes-context</i> is the context in Tomcat at which 
the JES component is installed. The default settings, when the component is first deployed, include <i>localhost</i>
as the address. This is <em>not</em> sufficient for normal operation, as an endpoint based on <i>localhost</i> is not
meaningful on other computers.
</p>
<p>
After changing these endpoints it is best to re-run the installation tests: see the menu in the left-hand side-bar.
The installation tests check that the endpoints are accessible.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

<section name="Required Properties">
<p>
JES also uses the following properties. The defaults are correct by definition, so don't
try to change them.
</p>
<source>
jes.locator=registry
jes.store=file
</source>
</section>
	
<section name="Example Configuration File">
<p>
This is how a complete set of JES properties might look if written out in a properties file.
You may wish to list your properties in this format (the configuration-editor pages allow
this) for comparison.
</p>
<source>
# file: astrogrid.properties - sample configuration file for a JES Server
# Working directory for jes
jes.jobfactory.file.basedir=/home/tomcat/jes/jobs

#Registry Endpoint - AstroGrid central registry
org.astrogrid.registry.query.endpoint=http://galahad.ast.cam.ac.uk:8080/galahad-registry/services/RegistryQuery

#Callback Endpoints
jes.monitor.endpoint.url=http://my.server.name:8080/astrogrid-jes/services/JobMonitorService
jes.results.endpoint.url=http://my.server.name:8080/astrogrid-jes/services/ResultListener

#Required Properties.
jes.locator=registry
jes.store=file
</source>

</section>
</body>
</document>
