<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
<title>Astrogrid Portal - Overview</title>
<author email="jl99@star.le.ac.uk">Jeff Lusted</author>
</properties>

<body>
<section name="Overview"><p>The portal is Astrogrid's web-based user interface, a browser being used to interact with services 
provided by the underlying Astrogrid infrastructure. The purpose being to enable a user to
exploit the services and do some astronomy.  To a user, the portal is
the Virtual Observatory.</p>
<p>The portal itself provides a level of organization that adds value
to the raw services. The basic organization centres around seven main
pages:</p><ul>
	<li>Logon. A user must log on before being able to use the VO.
	There is an email facility to request a userid or the reset of a
	password if it has been forgotten.</li>
	<li>Home Page. This is the page displayed after login. It shows
	the latest jobs submitted by the user, as well as providing access
	to the client-side desktop applications which are the focus of
	Astrogrid version 2.</li>
	<li>MySpace Explorer. Manages the user's virtual file space
	within the VO.</li>
	<li>Resource Explorer. Browse the VO registry of available
	resources.</li>
	<li>Query Editor. Construct ADQL queries for later submission
	against some registered data collection.</li>
	<li>Workflow Editor. Construct and submit for execution workflows
	which can combine queries and registered astronomical tools in any
	degree of complexity. A submitted workflow is known as a job.</li>
	<li>Job Monitor. Review and manage the execution of jobs.</li>
</ul>
<p>A word is required of the basic ideas behind Astrogrid that have
driven organization of the portal.</p>
<p> Astrogrid has been described as a data mining application. 
There are many collections of astronomical data and the volume of
information is expanding at an increasing rate.
Unfortunately there is little uniformity here: the collections are
both heterogenous and distributed, and large enough to defeat the
most ardent researcher. Behind the portal stands the registry, where
details of resources are registered in standardized formats suitable
for automatic searching by computerised techniques. Astrogrid uses
the registry to hold information on both data collections and its own
internal resources.</p>
<p>The registry can be explored directly using the Resource Explorer
page, but is also of critical importance to the Query Editor and the
Worfkflow Editor. The place of query and of workflow in Astrogrid
require some explanation...</p>
<p>The aim of the Query Editor is to provide a means of taking
information about a data collection from the registry and formating
an astronomical query that can be submitted against that data
collection.  Being able to query against one data collection is an
important but in itself limited facility. The results of a query may
require further processing or the results of a number of separate
queries may need processing and amalgamating in interesting ways.
This aspect is fullfilled by workflow, which adds an 
amount of muscle to the astronomer's toolkit, but also a degree of
complexity. The Workflow Editor enables workflows to be designed that
can combine queries with the processing of other astronomical tools
in a multi-stepped manner. There are no limits other than available
processing power and the patience of the astronomer in designing a workflow.
Multiple queries can be run, the results analysed, federated and
processed by standard tools whose presence has been recorded in the
registry. The steps can be processed at different locations. The
results of one workflow can be used subsequently as the input of
another workflow. Queries, workflows and results can be shared, and
thus in important respects become intellectual capital.</p>

<p>It is useful to think of workflows as existing in two contexts.
One is design time: workflows must be designed and the designs
persist like the blueprint of a building. The other context is
execution time. Workflows must be executed to produce results (much
like a building must be built using the blueprint). When a user in
the Workflow Editor submits a workflow for execution, the workflow
becomes known as a job and can be tracked by the Job Monitor page.</p>

<p>A quick reading of the above will show the need for a
virtual file system. Query designs, workflow designs and any files
used or produced by workflows are held within MySpace, which is the
VO's virtual file system. The MySpace Explorer page gives the user
access to the user's home space, where all a user's files reside.
The physical location of the files is automatically handled by the
system, although a certain amount of intervention is allowed if the
user so chooses.</p>
<p>Until a full suite of desktop applications becomes available the
portal is the user interface into the VO. It is very easy to install
with very few prerequisites, although the trick is to get all other
components to the state where the portal can begin orchestrating
them.
</p></section></body></document>