<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="jl99@star.le.ac.uk">Jeff Lusted</author>
        <author email="jdt@roe.ac.uk">John Taylor</author>
        <title>Installation</title>
</properties>

<body>
There are in fact few software prerequisites for installing the portal.
However, as the portal is the web-based user-interface to Astrogrid services, 
related Astrogrid components need to be installed and configuration undertaken before the portal becomes usable.
Also, a user requires a userid within an existing community and an allocation of file space within the MySpace 
virtual file system before an effective logon can be achieved.

<section name="Prerequisites">
<p>

<ul> 
<li>JDK1.4 or above</li> 
<li>A suitable web container. Astrogrid was developed using <a ref="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/">Tomcat. </a>
A Tomcat version 5.0+ is the recommendation.</li> 
</ul>

</p>
</section>

<section name="Related components"><p>
A fully functioning portal depends on all components within Astrogrid being deployed. 
These components do not have to be colocated with the portal. It is indeed likely 
that over time there will be multiple deployments of each component.  

<ul> 
<li>Registry</li> 
<li>Community</li> 
<li>JES - the Job Execution System, which manages workflows at execution time.</li> 
<li>CEA - the Common Execution Architecture, which mediates between Astrogrid and astronomical applications,
including data collections.</li>
<li>PAL - the Publishers Astrogrid Library. Coloqually an instance of PAL could be thought of as a datacenter.</li>
<li>The MySpace virtual file system. Two components are involved here: File Manager and File Store.</li>   
</ul>

The portal will function provided it is configured to point to its local community, a registry against which
it can make queries, and a JES against which it can submit workflows for execution. Any further details that are
required regarding applications, data collections and MySpace are gained from having access to the registry.

</p></section>

<section name="Installation">            
            <subsection name="The Portal Installer"> 
                <p> <img src="../img/astrogridIntro.jpg" align="LEFT" border="30"/>
                    If you are using Tomcat 5.0+ as your web container, then AstroGrid supplies an installer 
                    application. This is a self-extracting jar file that will manage required downloads, prompt the user for any required configuration
                    settings It also gives you the option 
                    to save settings for reuse should you wish to reinstall the portal. Further information can be found on the <a 
                    href="http://software.astrogrid.org/userdocs/install.html">software site</a>. Having downloaded
                    the installer, execute it by running from the directory that contains the installer:<br/>
                    java -jar [installer's jar file name]<br/>
                 If you are not using Tomcat, or you are using it, but are the sort of person who likes the challenge of working in the dark, on your 
                    knees, with a hand-tied behind your back, please follow the instructions below.
                    <br clear="all"/>
                    </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Deploying the whole portal the hard way">
                <p> This <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/org.astrogrid/wars/?P=*portal-*.war">link</a> gives access to the latest war files. Take 
                    the astrogrid-portal-*.war and deploy it to Tomcat by your favourite method.</p>
                <p> *NOTE* As of today (16/9/04) the portal <em>must</em> be deployed to a webapp named "astrogrid-portal". It is anticipated that this 
                    restriction will be removed soon. You may need to rename the war to "astrogrid-portal.war" to achieve this, depending on the deployment
                    method you use.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Deploying selected portal pages the hard way">
                <p> If you wish you can deploy only a subset of the portal pages. 
                    <ul> 
                        <li>Deploy the astrogrid-portal-base.war to Tomcat in the usual 
                    way.</li> 
                        <li>Stop tomcat</li> 
                            <li>Then take each subcomponent astrogrid-portal-*.war in turn and unzip it over the top of the webapp's 
                    folder in Tomcat. </li> 
                        <li>Restart Tomcat</li> 
                        </ul> 
                        </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Configuration">
                <p> If you deploy the portal by hand, you will need to configure it by hand too.</p>
                <p> The login page configuration is handled using the org.astrogrid.config package. There are a number of different ways that the application 
                    can be configured (see the Config javadoc), but the simplest way to configure it is to enter the JNDI properties below into Tomcat's 
                    server.xml file using the Tomcat administrator tool. <ul> <li>org.astrogrid.registry.query.endpoint=end point of the registry query 
                    webservice</li> <li>org.astrogrid.community.ident=Local community identifier (e.g. org.astrogrid.localhost)</li> 
                    <li>emailserver.address=address of your smtp server [127.0.0.1]</li> <li>emailserver.user=user whose account is used for sending reminder 
                    emails [astrogrid]</li> <li>emailserver.password=user's password (if necessary) []</li> <li>emailserver.from=return address for reminder 
                    emails [astrogrid@star.le.ac.uk]</li> <li>astrogrid.portal.admin.email=email address of the administrator who should receive reminder and 
                    registration emails from users[jdt@roe.ac.uk]</li> <li>workflow.jes.endpoint=end point of the Job Entry System's JobControllerService</li> 
                    <li>workflow.applist=registry (Instructs the portal to get the list of applications from the registry)</li> </ul> If values are not given 
                    for these properties, the defaults in square brackets are used instead. </p>
            </subsection>
</section>
<section name = "Building the Portal">
            <subsection name="Prequisites">
                <p> <ul> <li>JDK1.4 or above</li> <li><a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a></li> <li>The Maven javaapp plugin</li> </ul> To install the 
                    javaapp plugin type:<br/> <tt>maven -Dmaven.repo.remote=http://www.ibiblio.org/maven,http://maven-plugins.sf.net/maven 
                    -DartifactId=maven-javaapp-plugin -DgroupId=maven-plugins -Dversion=1.3 plugin:download </tt> </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name = "Building">
                <p>
                    After checking out all the files, cd to the root portal directory and execute
                    <verbatim>
                        maven astrogrid-install-artifact
                    </verbatim>
                    to generate the war files.
                    To generate the documentation execute
                                        <verbatim>
                        maven astrogrid-build-site
                    </verbatim>
                </p>
            </subsection>
</section>

</body>
</document>
