<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="nw@jb.man.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
        <title>Introduction</title>
</properties>
<body>
	<section name="Astro Runtime : An API for the VO"><p>
The Astro Runtime (AR) simplifies access to Virtual Observatory 
(VO) services.  It implements the client side of many VO services,
 and provides an API that is higher-level, simple, consistent and 
 self-contained. It provides functionality for implementing data 
 analysis applications which use remote VO resources.  
 It is intended both for use in actual applications and science scripting.  
 Identical functionality is made available in multiple languages and 
 application environments.
</p>
<p>

In general, scientific analysis applications want a higher level
interface and want to be isolated from the details of, and changes to,
the more fundamental VO protocols and related technology comprising
the core VO infrastructure.  Astro Runtime hides most of the details of
the VO infrastructure, provides a straightfoward way to deal with
protocol versioning, and allows for more transparent infrastructure
evolution.
</p>

<p>
			Some current or potential uses of the AR are
			<!--  check for concrete examples of these. -->
			<ul>
				<li>as  infrastructure for new VO clients and services.</li>
				<li>to VO-integrate existing desktop applications</li>
				<li>to provide VO functionality to existing packages (PyRaf, Parceltongue/AIPS) </li>
				<li> simplify science scripting: e.g. programmatic access to VO
					services from Python, Perl,  IDL
				</li>
				<li>to provide a commandline interface to the VO</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
</section>
	<section name="Motivation">
		<p>
			Virtual Observatory technology is becoming complex -
			partly through necessity, and partly because of growing
			pains. This complexity is challenging and time-consuming to
			learn and may be a barrier to entry for some. Amongst the
			causes of the complexity are:
			<ul>
				<li>growing number of standards</li>
				<li>interaction between standards</li>
				<li>variation between standard versions</li>
				<li>non-compliance of service implementations</li>
				<li>
					use of existing computer-science technologies -
					WS-*, SOAP, XML Schema
				</li>
				<li>
					variation between implementations of these
					technologies
				</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		<p>
			We hope that the Astro Runtime (AR) hides enough of this complexity
			so that the VO becomes accessible to more developers - from professional
			programmers to casual shell scripters.
			</p>
		
	</section>
</body>
</document>