<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "xdoc.dtd" >

<document>
     
   <properties>
     <title>Data Server API</title>
     <author email="dave@ast.cam.ac.uk">Dave Morris</author>
      <author email="mch@roe.ac.uk">Martin Hill</author>
   </properties>
<body>
   <section name="Overview">
      <p>
      AstroGrid PAL data servers implement a number of web interfaces, including [some of]
      the International Virtual Observatory standard interfaces.
      </p>
      <p>These include SOAP and http post accessors, and a number of pages for direct human
      access.</p>
      <p>No client code is provided as most programming languages provide direct SOAP and http post libraries
      anyway. </p>
   </section>
   <section name="Stable versions">
A deliberate effort is made to persist data server interfaces even as the standards are changed. This
      means that if you write a client to access a data server, that client will work even after
      the data server has been upgraded to provide new interfaces.
      <p>This is done by including a version number with the interface name.  So, for example,
         the first 'native' AstroGrid SOAP interface is at http://.../services/AxisDataService06.  The
         next AstroGrid SOAP interface might be at http://.../services/AxisDataService07 .
      </p>
      <p>However some interfaces may be deprecated and eventually removed if they are unused.</p>
   </section>
   <section name="Cone Search">
      <p>Http-post NVO-style Cone searches are provided via a servlet, at http://.../SubmitCone.
      Pass in RA, DEC and SIZE, SR or RADIUS parameters, eg.  <code>http://.../SubmitCone?RA=12&amp;DEC=23&amp;SR=2</code>
      Additionally, as with all the AstroGrid PAL http post interfaces, specify a <code>Format</code> parameter
      as HTML, VOTABLE, CSV or TSV, and a <code>Target</code> parameter as a URL indicating where
      the results should be sent (which may include homespace identifiers).  By default the format is VOTABLE and the results are returned
      to the browser.  Note that case is important for the parameters, ie <code>FORMAT</code> will not
      be interpreted.</p>
      <p>The RAs and DECs that will be searched are configured by the data publisher</p>
   </section>
   <section name="Common Execution Architecture">
      AstroGrid PAL dataservers provide a standard Common Execution Component interface to the
      Common Execution Architecture. Each dataset is
      registered as a 'query tool' with one service providing access to that tool.
   </section>
   <section name="SkyNode">
      Unfortunately the SkyNode interface is still incomplete; it should provide an IVOA-compatible
       SOAP access to the database.
   </section>
   <section name="Other">
      <p>For those who prefer "light 'n' easy" access to web services, the web service methods are also available
         via 'direct' http post.  These include AskCount (returns an integer number), AskQuery (synchrnous/blocking
      query), SubmitQuery (asynchronous query, returns an ID to the query), GetMetadata (returns the metadoc)
      AttemptAbort (for attempting to abort asynchronous queries). For arguments these take <code>AdqlUri</code>, <code>AdqlSql</code> or <code>AdqlXml</code>
      for the query, and <code>Format</code> and <code>Target</code> as above</p>
      <p>
      There is a 'native' SOAP interface to the dataset via <code>http://.../services/AxisDataService06</code>. This
      provides SOAP access to the full range of query methods, some of which are not available
      through the IVOA interfaces (such as asynchronous querying).
      </p>
      <p>There are also IVOA-standard SIAP and SSAP interfaces (where appropriate, ie where images are
      or spectra are served)  </p>
   </section>
</body>
</document>
