<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="jl99@star.le.ac.uk">Jeff Lusted</author>
        <title>Portal User Guide - Job Monitor</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Job Monitor Contents">
<p>
<ul><a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></ul>
<ul><a href="#Job_List">Job List</a></ul>
<ul><a href="#Workflow_Details">Workflow Details</a></ul>
<ul><a href="#Workflow_Transcript">Workflow Transcript</a></ul>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">
<p>
The Job Monitor allows a user to interrogate his/her jobs. 
A job is a workflow that has been submitted for execution. As a workflow can be submitted many times, each 
submission will result in a new job that can be tracked using the Job Monitor. The initial monitor page shows a
list of jobs. Subsequent pages allow a user to drill down into more detail for a selected job. 
</p>
<br/><a href="#Job_Monitor_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>
   
<section name="Job List">
<p>
The initial Job Monitor page displays the user's <a href="../example-pages/job-monitor.html" target="_top">list of jobs</a>. The list is refreshed every 20 seconds so that the most uptodate details are displayed. The information for each job covers the name and description
of the originating workflow, the date and time the workflow was submitted, the job status and the job id. Against each job there is also a button to allow deletion of the job details. Deletion of the job details whilst a job is in execution will result in the job itself being cancelled. The underlying Astrogrid component that manages job entry and execution is known by its acronym: JES, which variously can be
ascribed as the Job Execution System, or sometime the Job Entry System. Status and Job ID are two important details furnished by JES:
<ul type="square">
  <li>Status. A job has four possible statuses:
     <ul>
        <li>Initializing</li>
        <li>Running</li>
        <li>Completed (without error)</li>
        <li>Error</li>
     </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Job ID. The job ID is a long and unique string allocated by JES. In the display it forms a link to the details of an individual job. </li>
</ul>
</p>
<br/><a href="#Job_Monitor_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Workflow Details">  
<p>
The <a href="../example-pages/job-monitor-workflow.html" target="_top">Workflow Details</a> displays the complete workflow structure of the job. Each step can be highlighted and its status and details revealed. The job step status is similar to job status. A step can be
     <ul>
        <li>Initializing</li>
        <li>Running</li>
        <li>Completed (without error)</li>
        <li>Error</li>
     </ul>
The workflow details also contain a button whereby a user can request a workflow transcript ...
</p> 
<br/><a href="#Job_Monitor_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Workflow Transcript">  
<p>
The workflow transcript is a detailed log of the job's execution as managed by JES. It will return relatively detailed messages from
each of the execution environments. The details can be useful in error situations.
</p> 
<br/><a href="#Job_Monitor_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

</body>
</document>
