<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="jl99@star.le.ac.uk">Jeff Lusted</author>
        <title>Portal User Guide - Logon</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Contents">
<p><ul>
<li><a href="#Logging_On">Logging On"</a></li>
<li><a href="#Getting_a_Userid">Getting a Userid</a></li>
<li><a href="#Forgotten_Password">Forgotten Password</a></li>
<li><a href="#When_Things_Go_Wrong">When Things Go Wrong</a></li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Logging On">
<p>
There are three entry fields on the login screen. Enter your username, password and the community you belong to as a member. 
Then press the login button. If all goes well, you are logged in to the portal and will have your home page displayed. Otherwise, 
a message will be shown in a red box below the login fields asking you to check your details and try again.  
</p>
<br/><a href="#Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Getting a Userid">
<p>
 You will need an AstroGrid 1.1 username-password-community set to be able to log into the Portal. (Please remember that your user-account 
 is for your own use only). If you are a research astronomer, please email astrogrid_signup@star.le.ac.uk to request a username. In your 
 registration email please include your name and academic department. (NB: this information will remain confidential to the AstroGrid project) 
</p>
<br/><a href="#Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Forgotten Password">
<p>
If you forget your password, click on the password link below the login box and a Password Reminder page will be shown. Type in your
name and email address and the system administrator will give you a fresh password and email you your details.
</p>
<br/><a href="#Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="When Things Go Wrong">
<p>
A number of things can go wrong.
<ul>
<li>If for some reason the portal of your choosing is unavailable, a substitute page is displayed rather than the login page. 
It will show links to alternative Astrogrid portals. If you are an existing member, follow one of these links, as you should be able to 
login to any portal and proceed with your work. There may be a slight diminution in performance. 
However, if you are requesting registration, it would be best to wait for your chosen portal to become available again before 
proceeding.</li>
<li>If your details are correct but nevertheless get rejected with the standard message, then you must contact your system 
administrator to follow up the situation. Pass the administrator the portal address, your details and the time of your attempted login. 
The administrator will need to examing log records to diagnose and correct the situation.
</li>
<li>If at all possible a suitable message will be displayed provided we do not compromise system security by so doing. However, unless
the situation is relatively trivial, almost all will entail contacting the system administrator.
</li>
</ul>
</p>
<br/><a href="#Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

</body>
</document>
