<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="jl99@star.le.ac.uk">Jeff Lusted</author>
        <title>Portal User Guide - MySpace Explorer</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="MySpace Explorer Contents">
<p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="#Main_Browser_Layout">Main Browser Layout</a></li>
<li><a href="#Using_the_Tree_View">Using the Tree View</a></li>
<li><a href="#Using_the_Folder_View">Using the Folder View</a></li>
<li><a href="#Microbrowser">Microbrowser</a></li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">
<p>
MySpace Explorer is the user interface for MySpace, Astrogrid's file system. In MySpace, files are stored across the Astrogrid network.
Each user is given a "home space" where his/her files are logically situated, although the actual physical location of each file can
be different. Physical location is taken care of by MySpace. Although users can have some control over this aspect, the idea is that
they should be able largely to ignore where files are held. Why is there a need for such a system? First and foremost a user needs
somewhere to keep files. These cover workflows, queries, configuration files for tasks, results and intermediate results of investigations,
and indeed anything users find useful in their work. As the underlying paradigm for Astrogrid is one of workflows which can be 
conducted across the network and over a considerable period of time, a distributed and available file system is a necessity. 
MySpace Explorer tries hard to present a usable file management interface somewhat similar to Explorer in Windows and Nautilus in
Linux. There are inevitable differences, some to do with the fact that it is browser based, some to do with the fact that the system
is not localized to the desktop.
<br/><br/>
MySpace Explorer comes in two guises. Firstly, a user needs a main interface where the focus of attention is exploraing and 
maintaining their personal file space. This main interface is what we normally term the 
<a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer.html" target="_top">MySpace Explorer</a>. Secondly, a dialogue
is required that is similar but simpler than the main interface, and which is placed in the service of other Astrogrid components:
for example, when a user wishes to save a query in the Query Editor. The latter form of the Explorer is normally termed a microbrowser,
or the <a href="../example-pages/mb-myspace-explorer.html" target="_top">MySpace Microbrowser</a>.
<br/><br/>
Throughout MySpace Explorer, we use the metaphors of file and folder, familiar to desktop users. Visually, there is a high degree
of consistency in the use of these terms. Colloqually, and in Astrogrid documentation, you will also find the term directory.
Directory and folder should be treated as synonymous terms.
</p>
<a href="#MySpace_Explorer_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Main Browser Layout">
<p>
MySpace Explorer uses two views, a <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-tree.html" target="_top">tree view</a> 
and a <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-folder.html" target="_top">folder view</a>. 
You should treat the latter as your main working interface.
The tree view is purely there as an aid to help visualize your file structure, and is a good aid to navigation around that 
structure. However, the folder view contains a control area where you can manipulate file and folder structures. You can also
navigate using the folder view, albeit somewhat more sedately than using the tree view. Please note that the border between 
the two views can be dragged for resizing.
</p>
<br/><a href="#MySpace_Explorer_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Using the Tree View">
<p>
The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-tree.html" target="_top">tree view</a> only displays folders, not files. 
When users first enter the Explorer and see the tree view, they are presented with 
their "home space" displayed and any folders one level below the home folder.  For a new user, only the home folder will be displayed, 
until folders are subsequently created by the user within the home folder. When a user clicks on a folder icon, the Explorer will open 
the folder and display any subfolders one level below. Hence by clicking on folders a user can open their whole tree of folders,
if that is desired. 
<br/><br/>
As the Explorer is only an interface into MySpace, it may be that when a folder is clicked for opening, that the contained information
may need to be loaded from MySpace. If this is the case, a "loading..." message will be displayed immediately below the folder icon
until the information has been loaded. If the folder is a bottom leaf, the Explorer tries to give some indication of its contents,
again with a small message below the folder icon: "empty" if indeed the folder is completely empty, and "empty of folders" if it 
contains some files but no sub-folders. It is possible to open your whole tree in this way. You can manipulate the display by also
closing a branch by clicking on the appropriate open folder; thus you can maintain a tree display of the relevant part of your
system rather than having the whole tree open in the view. The tree view is scrollable both vertically and horizontally.
<br/><br/>
You see no files within the tree view. But by clicking or highlighting the name of a folder, you direct the Explorer to open that 
folder within the folder view, and there you can see files...
</p>
<a href="#MySpace_Explorer_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Using the Folder View">
<p>
The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-folder.html" target="_top">folder view</a> is the main working view of the Explorer.
It is composed of two areas: a folder area and a control area. 
</p>
<subsection name="Folder Area"><p>
The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-folder-area.html" target="_top">folder area</a> fulfills a similar function as the 
tree view. It displays structural information about what a particular folder contains, but in this case both (sub-)folders and files,
and enables the opening of contained folders, and the highlighting of files and of folders for further manipulation. 
Clicking on a sub-folder's icon will open that sub-folder in the Folder View replacing the current (i.e. parent folder) in the view.
Thus you can drill down further through the tree, from folder to sub-folder to sub-sub-folder, and so on, until you reach a bottom 
leaf. This is an important alternative way of navigation to the Tree View. A file or folder can be highlighted by clicking on its name:
in doing so you copy the path of the item into the Selected field contained within the Control Area.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Control Area"><p>
The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-control-area.html" target="_top">control area</a> is the focus for manipulating
MySpace files and folders. The control area is formatted into 4 tabs:
<ol type="1">
<li>The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-control-area.html" target="_top">Navigation</a> tab shows you your current location. This is the path (within the user's home space) to the folder displayed in the Folder View. A typical value might be the path home/queries where queries is a folder that might contain adql queries. Whichever way you navigate about MySpace, the current location should always show you where you are. Below the Current Location field are four buttons:
   <ul type="square">
     <li>Up. This will navigate up a folder to the current location's parent folder.</li>
     <li>Home. This will navigate back to your home space folder.</li>
     <li>New Folder. This will produce a dialogue enabling you to create a new folder within the current folder.</li>
     <li>Refresh. This will force the Explorer to go back to MySpace and refresh the contents of the current folder.
         Sometimes this is necessary as things can be happening to MySpace at the same time a user is browsing his/her 
         home space. At present only the file contents are refreshed.</li>
   </ul>
</li>
<li>The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-edit-tab.html" target="_top">Edit</a> tab enables manipulation of files within the Folder View.
   <ul type="square">
     <li>The Selected Field. The name of any selected folder or file is displayed here. If nothing has been selected by the user
     then the string "*** none ***" is displayed. You must have an item selected (by clicking on its name within the folder area), 
     before you can manipulate by using other edit controls.</li>
     <li>The Clipboard Field. If an item has been placed in the clipboard by using the Copy or Cut buttons, 
     then its path is shown here. The Clipboard field is used when the Paste button is pressed. If no item has
     been placed in the clipboard, the string "*** empty ***" is displayed.</li>
     <li>Copy button. Pressing the copy button will place the path of the selected item into the Clipboard Field.
     This enables a user to paste a copy of the file into a folder.</li>
     <li>Cut button. Pressing the cut button will place the path of the selected item into the Clipboard Field.
     This enables a user to paste a copy of the file into a folder whilst removing it from the current folder.
     Equivalent to moving the file from one folder to another.</li>
     <li>Paste button. The paste button will utilize the path of any file in the clipboard. If the file was placed there
     by using the Copy button, then a copy of the file is placed in the current location. If the file was placed in the clipboard
     by using the Cut button, then the file is removed from its folder and moved to the current location. Note that the current
     location is changed by navigating, so in order to copy or to move a file from one folder to another, you must navigate between
     the folders. You can tell which "mode" the clipboard is in by hovering the mouse over the clipboard field: a tool tip will 
     then display either "Source for copy" or "Source for move". Pasting always gives you the opportunity to rename a file by
     presenting a suitable dialogue.</li>
     <li>Delete button. Will delete any selected file. A prompt dialogue is presented so you have the opportunity to change your mind.</li>
     <li>Properties button. The properties button displays a simple 
     <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-properties.html" target="_top">properties dialogue</a> for any file selected. 
     If you wish to download a file from MySpace to your desktop, this dialogue is required. The dialogue shows:
       <ul>
          <li>Name</li>
          <li>Path. This is a link to the file. Left click mouse-button will display the contents of the file. Right click and choose
          "Save Link Target As..." to  download to the desktop.</li>
          <li>Date/Time Created</li>
          <li>Date/Time Modified</li>
          <li>Owner</li>
          <li>Size</li>
          <li>Mime-type</li>
          <li>File store location. You can change the physical location of the file by using the associated Relocation dialogue displayed in the bottom part of the properties page.</li>
       </ul>
     </li>
   </ul>
</li>
<li>The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-desktop-upload-tab.html" target="_top">Desktop Upload</a> tab enables files local to the user's desktop system to be uploaded into MySpace. The browse button displayed enables a user to browse their own local file sytem to choose a suitable file. Once a file has been chosen, the Go button will trigger an upload to the current location. The upload is undertaken synchronously, so you will wait for the action to complete. The uploaded file will appear in the current folder.
</li>
<li>The <a href="../example-pages/myspace-explorer-web-upload-tab.html" target="_top">Web Upload</a> tab enables uploading of files from the web. Note you must paste or type the URL of the object to be uploaded.
</li>
</ol>
</p>
</subsection>
<a href="#MySpace_Explorer_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

<section name="Microbrowser">
   <p>
       The <a href="../example-pages/mb-myspace-explorer.html" target="_top">microbrowser</a> version of the MySpace Explorer 
       is always invoked in the service of another portal component. At present, the contexts are:
       <ul>
         <li>Loading or saving workflows in the Workflow Editor</li>
         <li>Loading or saving queries in the Query Editor</li>
         <li>Selecting files as inputs or outputs in a workflow. Again in the Workflow Editor.</li>
       </ul>
       The microbrowser is a restricted version of the Folder View. There are slight variations in presentation and behaviour
       according to the context. Most have sub-dialogues to guide a user.
   </p>
<br/><br/><a href="#MySpace_Explorer_Contents">Go to Contents</a>
</section>

</body>
</document>
