<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Page Title</title>
    <author email="paul.harrison@manchester.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
  </properties>
 <body>
 <section>
 	<p>
		The Client area's main purpose is to give the users a delegate to go by
		and to interact with a Registry server or cache.  The Client section
		will read in a config file and determine to use a Registry server which
		will be the most common or use a a local cache through it's config file.
		It determines rather to use a server or local config file by simply determining
		if the endpoints are in the config file.  It should be noted current 
		implementation only queries based on identifiers when using the local config
		cache.  The current client is now associated with the ivoa standard now of
    	querying via ADQL and is OAI conformed on the web service interface.
	</p>
	</section>
	<section name="Builds">
		<p>
			The registry allows you to build at the top level or at it's sub-project level.  
			Here are the maven goals for building the registry.
			<ul>
				<li>astrogrid-clean - cleans out and removes all previous builds.</li>
				<li>astrogrid-install-snapshot - Builds all the necessry jar and war files.</li>
				<li>astrogrid-deploy-snapshot - Builds and deploys the snapshot onto the repository.</li>
				<li>astrogrid-deploy-site - Generates reports and documents to be deployed on the site repository.</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
	</section>
	<section name="Deployment/Installation">
		<p>
			It is expected that this jar will be bunded with an appropriate
			war file for use with other components.  There is no seperate 
			installation just for the client itself.  After a build a jar
			file is produced in the "target" directory.  When ever it is 
			bundled with another component, it is expected to have in the
			System properties or JNDI a key value of "org.astrogrid.config.url"
			pointing to a config file.  An example config file is given in
			cvs under the config directory for this client area.
			Current config properties needed to use a server:			
			<ul>
				<li>org.astrogrid.registry.admin.endpoint - administration endpoint for updates.</li>
				<li>org.astrogrid.registry.query.endpoint - query endpoint.</li>
			</ul>
			<i>just define no properties and define an identifier pointing
			   to a xml file of the Resource for that identifier when using the local
			   config cache.
			</i>
		</p>
	</section>
	<section name="How to Use for Other Components">
		<p>
		Once the configuration is complete and ready for another component
		to use.  It may use the various delegates with the delegate factory.
		<br /><strong>The Query:</strong><br />
		Instantiate with: 
		org.astrogrid.registry.client.query.RegistryService rs = org.astrogrid.registry.client.RegistryDelegateFactory.createQuery()
		<br />From there you have access to all the delegate methods 
		mentioned below for the Query section.  It is of course advisable to
		use import statements at the top of your code to make things easier.
		<strong>Still need to put some examples of the query schema/string here</strong>
		</p>	
	</section>
	<section name="Delegate - Helper methods to the Interface">
		<p>
			This section is a quick description of what delegate methods can be used for
			other components to take advantage of. This is not necessarily the actual web
			service interface methods on the server side registry.
			<br />
			<strong>First the Query:</strong>
			<ul>
				<li>submitQuery - 
				  Queries the Registry. Examples of the queries can be found in config/junitcache,
				  but will add a section here soon.
				  There are various submitQueries that can be used.
				</li>
				<li>getResourceByIdentifier - returns a Document DOM object of this one resource entry.</li>
				<li>getEndPointByIdentifier - returns a string which is a endpoint of a Service entry by looking at the WSDL if it is a Web service.</li>
				<li>getBasicWSDLInformation - returns a WSDLBasicInformation object containting a targetNamespace and endpoints found in a WSDL.</li>
				<li>loadRegistry - returns a Document DOM object of just the registry resource entry.</li>
    			<li>search - A query based on ADQL.</li>
    			<li>listRecords - OAI list records.</li>
    			<li>getRecord - OAI getRecord.</li>
    			<li>listmetadataprefix - OAI listmetadataprefix.</li>
    			<li>listidentifiers - OAI listidentifiers.</li>
    			<li>identify - OAI  identify.</li>
			</ul>
			<strong>The Update:</strong>
			<ul>
				<li>update(Document) - updates a resource entries in the registry given a one or more Resources from a Document DOM object.</li>
				<li>updateFromUrl(URL url) - Not yet implemented.</li>
				<li>updateFromFile(File fi) - Not Yet imnplemented.</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
	</section>
	<section name="More on Queries">
    	<p>
    		The queries should be done in ADQL now, but current components still use an old style xml, look below on more 
    		information about that.
    	</p>
		<p>
			Currently the queries conform to an old style xml schema and syntax and will be changed shortly in itn06 to 
			conform to the IVOA schema.  The schema can be found: <a href="..">Registry ~Query Schema</a>, but look at the
			examples below to see basic syntax of the queries, it is very SQL like and easy to understand.
			In the current iteration the parsing looks for all namespaces "*", and the current sectionOp values are "AND|OR".
			The section items can be set to any text node or attribute, and finally for itemOp is much like the Xquery syntax see the itemOp list.
			<br />
			<i>ItemOp List:</i>
			<ul>
				<li>CONTAINS - constains or substring</li>
				<li>EQ - equals</li>
				<li>NE - not equals</li>
				<li>GE - greater-than-or-equals</li>
				<li>LE - less-than-or-equals</li>
				<li>GT - greater-than</li>
				<li>LT - less-than</li>
			</ul>			
			<br />
			<i>Examples:</i><br />
			<i>			
				<query>
					<selectionSequence>
					    <selection item='searchElements' itemOp='EQ' value='Resource'/>
        		        <selectionOp op='$and$'/> <!-- this is a dummy ob for the searchElements item hoped to be removed soon, but neeed now -->
						<selection item='AuthorityID' itemOp='EQ' value='" + authorityID + "'/>
        		        <selectionOp op='AND'/>
		                <selection item='@type' itemOp='EQ' value='RegistryType'/>
        	        </selectionSequence>
        	    </query>
			</i>
		</p>
	</section>
 
 
 </body>
</document>