<document>
   <properties>
      <author email="pah@jb.man.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
      <title>Advanced Configuration</title>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="Introduction">
         <p>The CEC has been designed as a collection of pluggable
            components that can be "glued together" to create a working
            server. This approach allows considerable scope for fine
            grained control and extension of the behaviour of the CEC.
            This page discusses some of the more coarse grained
            customisations (i.e. choosing different versions of
            particular components) that are possible. For more
            specialized needs, such as writing a new version of a
            component then the reader is advised to consult the
            documentation that comes with the CEA Common Library.</p>
         <subsection name="Spring">
            <p>
               The CEC is constructed the
               <a = href="http://www.springframework.org/">Spring Framework</a>
               as the architectural "glue", and consequently advanced
               configuration does require some knowledge about the
               spring framework - in particular the configuration files
               themselves are standard Spring configuration files.
            </p>
            <p>Because of this access to such low level of
               configurability it is possible to significantly alter and
               customize the CEC, including adding new behaviour that
               you yourself write. With this level of control comes
               danger - it is easy to mis-configure in such a way that
               the CEC will not function, so in all cases back up the
               original files before making alterations.</p>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section name="Customizing existing components">
         <subsection name="Configuration Files">
         </subsection>
         <subsection name="Adding new Applications">
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section name="Writing new components">
         <subsection name="Inversion of control">
            <p>
               The CEC has been written with the design aim that each of
               the components obtains its dependencies at construction
               time - a pattern that is known as "inversion of control".
               In the specific case of spring this translates to
               <code>autowire="constructor"</code>
            </p>
         </subsection>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>