<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
   <properties>
      <author email="pah@jb.man.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
      <title>Configuration</title>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="Configuration">
         <p> You must configure the CEC so that it works with your
            chosen applications and in the environment of your site.
            Please follow this sequence:</p>
         <ol>
            <li>Edit the CEC's "environment" to tell it where to
               find things.</li>
            <li>Edit the "registration-template" document.</li>
            <li>Preview the registration document.</li>
            <li>Restart the web application to pick up the
               changed configuration.</li>
         </ol>
         <p> Instructions for each step are gven below.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="Edit the CEC's environment">
         <p> The CEC needs to be told where to find things in its
            operating environment. You do this by editing the
            "environment entries" (i.e. named properties) for your
            application server.</p>
          <p>The method by which these environment entries are edited will depend on the application server that you are using.
          </p>
          <p>The environment entries are described in <a href="env-entry-reference.html">more detail here</a>.
          </p>
         
         <p> When you have saved the changes in the configuration. This
            makes a safe copy of the environment but doesn't apply the
            changes. The editor then applies the environment by copying
            it into Tomcat's configuration directory. At this point,
            Tomcat should detect the change and restart the web
            application with the new environment.</p>
         <subsection
            name="The CEC's working directories and configuration files"
         >
            <p> By default, the CEC uses a fixed directory-structure for
               its configuration and working files.</p>
            <pre> 
                  (base)/ 
                  (base)/temp 
                  (base)/records 
                  (base)/config
                  (base)/config/registration-template.xml
                  (base)/config/app-description.xml</pre>
            <p>
               In this structure,
               <i>(base)</i>
               is the directory you specify by setting the environment
               entry
               <i>cea.base.dir</i>
               . By changing this entry, you can move the directory
               structure anywhere you like. However, it is 
               usually best to place the structure at the location outside the tomcat directory tree. That way, the
              the configuration will be saved when updating either the CEA CEC or Tomcat itself. 
            </p>
            <p>
               The file
               <i>(base)/config/registration-template.xml
               </i>
               is the registration-template document.
            </p>
            <p>It is always possible to check the the configuration with the <a href="../admin/configuration-describe.jsp">Show current configuration</a> sidebar menu.</p>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section name="Edit the registration template">
         <p> The CEC uses an XML document called a registration template
            to generate the registration documents that it submits to
            the IVO resource-registry. You need to edit this template.
         </p>
         <p>
            To find the registration template, use the
            <i>show current configuration</i>
            link in the sidebar. You need to replace the copy at that
            location with a customized version.
         </p>
         <p>To create a new registration document use <a href="../config/registration-template.xml">this template</a>. The template initialized by the CEC has extensive comments
            to tell you what to set; please read them. Note that this template
             is for the service registration, the applications are configured separately.</p>
     
      <subsection name="Preview the registration document">
         <p> When you have the environment set, including the entry that
            leads the URL to your edited copy of the registration
            template, you should check that the registration documents
            are coming out satisfactorily. Use the "show registration
            document" link in the side-bar.</p>
         <p> The registration document is what will eventually be sent
            to the IVO resource registry to identify your CEC and its
            applications. These documents are public and are read both
            by human users of your service and by machines. Therefore,
            they need to be both scientifically useful and technically
            correct. You need to check them at this stage before going
            on to registration.</p>
         <p>
            The most important thing to check is the
            <i>identifier</i>
            element in the service description. This is the formal name
            for your service in the registry, and you can't change it
            once you've registered (changing the name creates a second
            registration; it doesn't rename the original one). Almost
            anything else can be patched up by registry updates, but you
            have to get the identifier right first time. Things to
            check:
         </p>
         <ul>
            <li>
               Is the authority ID part of the identifier (e.g. the
               <i>foo.bar</i>
               in
               <i>ivo://foo.bar/baz</i>
               right for the registry where you're publishing? A given
               registry accepts registrations only under a limited,
               pre-agreed set of authorities.
            </li>
            <li>
               Is the resource-key part (e.g. the
               <i>baz</i>
               in
               <i>ivo://foo.bar/baz</i>
               unique within the naming authority?
            </li>
            <li>Is the resource key a sensible and memorable name for
               the service?</li>
         </ul>
      </subsection>
       </section>
       <section name="Application Configuration">
       <p>In order for the CEC to have a useful function at least one application needs to be configured - This is covered in detail in the <a href="ApplicationConfiguration.html">Application Configuration page</a></p>
       
       <p>In addition to this documentation there are also examples of previous <a href="./config/">example configurations</a> for a range of applications that can serve as a template for creating a suitable configuration for a new application.</p> 
       </section>
      <section name="Restart the web application">
         <p> The CEC web-service needs to be restarted to pick up the
            changed configuration. This means that you have to restart
            the whole web-application. Either restart Tomcat itself, or
            use the Tomcat Manager application to restart the current
            web-application.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="Using the CEC">
        <p>Once you have restarted the CEC you may start to <a href="Use.html">use</a>it, or in the event of failures try <a href="SELF-TEST.html">further testing</a>.</p>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>