<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
   <properties>
      <title>CEA Java Class Application</title>
      <author email="pah@jb.man.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="HTTP Application">
        
        <p> This component provides a Common Execution Connector web-service for HTTP
            applications (HTTP-CEC for short). The HTTP-CEC makes astronomy applications available to the
            virtual observatory; notably, it makes them visible to AstroGrid's web portal, desktop UI
            and workflow system.</p><p> Suitable applications for this kind of CEC (there are other kinds) run on external web-servers
            (i.e. they need not be co-located with the CEC) and can be invoked using the HTTP-get protocol;
            the CEC does not work with HTTP-post services. The HTTP-CEC acts as a proxy for the HTTP application,
            translating between the standards CEA protocols and the application's own protocol. This has 
            two advantages.
         </p><ul>
            <li>Non-standard applications become accessible to the IVO.</li>
            <li>IVO-standard HTTP-get services (e.g. SIAP), which are already accessible
            to the IVO in a basic form, become accessible as CEA applications and can be
            used from all AstroGrid UIs.</li>
         </ul><p>
            One HTTP-CEC can stand as proxy for any number of HTTP applications. Therefore, if
            you have an HTTP application on your web-server you can use associate it with an
            HTTP-CEC in two ways.
         </p><ol>
            <li>Run your own HTTP-CEC.</li>
            <li>Have your application configured onto someone else's HTTP-CEC.</li>
         </ol>
         
         <subsection name="Extra configuration for the HTTP Applications">
            <p>For HTTP applications the applicationDefinition should be of xsi:type="impl:CeaHttpApplicationDefinition" which allows a CeaHttpAdapterSetup element to be written after the interfaces element. This CeaHttpAdapterSetup element allows the location of the web application that is to be proxied to be specified.
            </p>
         </subsection>
       
      
</section>
</body>
</document>