<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="pah@jb.man.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
		<title>CEC: overview</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Overview">
			<p> This component provides a Common Execution Controller (CEC) web-service for running various asynchronous applications. It is part of the 
         Common Execution Architecture (CEA) suite of software from Astrogrid.
             </p>
                <p>This component is highly compliant with all the general IVOA Standards</p>
                <ul>
                  <li>UWS</li>
                  <li>VOSI</li>
                  <li>General Security</li>
                  <li>Registry</li>
                  <li>Delegation</li>
                  <li>VOSpace</li>
                </ul>
            <p>
            </p>
            <p>
              This component can be used to "wrap" existing applications so that they are presented as IVOA standard web services. The applications are
              formally exposed to the rest of the VO as CEAApplications, which have initial parameter lists defined by their registry entries.
               This component provides support for wrapping
            </p>
            <ul>
              <li>Commandline applications</li>
              <li>Existing web form based HTTP applications</li>
              <li>Custom written Java applications</li>
            </ul>
            
			<p> Suitable applications are subject to two main constraints</p>
                <ol>
                  <li>have no graphical interface</li>
                  <li>need no user interaction once launched</li>
                </ol>
			<ul>
         <p>These
            are some of the commandline applications already in use in AstroGrid.</p>
				<li>SExtractor</li>
				<li>HyperZ</li>
				<li>BPZ</li>
				<li>Pegase</li>
				<li>Galaxev</li>
			</ul>
			<p> You should install this component if you wish to allow virtual-observatory users to run
				selected applications on your computer. You choose the applications that may be run.
				You must obtain and install these applications; they are not supplied with the CL-CEC.
				The applications will run on the computer where you install
				the service, and you must provide sufficient resources (CPU, memory, disc space) for the
				applications to run efficiently.</p>
            
          <p> There is also a variant of the Common Execution Controller that is customised to serve other standard IVOA Protocols including</p>
            <ul>
              <li>SIAP</li>
              <li>SSAP</li>
              <li>TAP</li>
            </ul>
            <p>whilst still retaining the CEA flexibility of choice in how to configure the back end implentation.</p>
            
            <p> However, at this time, if your application is to serve archive data then this may not be the ideal component. You
            should look first at the Data Set Access (DSA) component of AstroGrid, which specializes in connecting directly to a variety of database backends.</p>
           
 
			
			<subsection name="Internal web-pages and local controls">
				<p>
					The CEC web-application contains a copy of these web-pages. If you install the web
					application as, say, <i>CEC-1</i> on server <i>my.cea.server</i> on port <i>8081</i>,
					then the internal web pages are at
				</p>
				<pre>
http://my.cea.server:8081/CEC-1/
				</pre>
				<p>	
					The copy of these pages that is bundled with the web service components
					has, in its sidebar, extra links leading to local controls for configuration, testing and
					registration. Therefore, while setting up the CEC, you should look at the internal pages.
					If you can't find the controls, you're probably reading the web pages on 
					<i>software.astrogrid.org</i> instead.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
