<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="gtr@ast.cam.ac.uk">Guy Rixon</author>
        <title>Registration</title>
</properties>

<body>

  <section name="Required registrations">
  	<p>
	    To make your CEC useful in the Virtual Observatory, you must register, in an
	    IVOA-compliant resource registry, the CEC as a service. 
    </p>
  	<p>
		  The service registration states the service endpoint (the URL for access)
		  and lists the applications that the CEC can run. For each registration,
		  you submit a resource document (an XML file) stating the necessary metadata
		  in a machine-readable format.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		  The CEC presents the possible registration documents at the "<span class="ceconly"><a href="../uws/reg">Manage Registration</a></span>" side bar menu. 
The resource documents have to be registered manually with a registry, the method of doing this with an Astrogrid registry below.
  	</p>
  </section>

	<section name="Registering individual applications">	
		<p>
			It is not always possible or necessary to register all of the applications that your CEC is capable of running. If the CEC is mirroring 
         an application that was originally published by another CEC (and consequently already registered), then it is not necessary to try to reregister that application. The "manage registrations" page indicates when a particular application is already present in the registry.
		</p>
	</section>
		
  <section name="Manual registration">
  	<p>
  		Most registries have a web-browser interface whereby you can submit 
  		resource documents manually. Typically, and especially in the AstroGrid
  		implementation of the registry, you can upload the registration documents
  		from files on disc or better in this instance via a URL (see below).
  	</p>
  	<p>
  		You can get a registration document using the "show registration document"
  		link in the sidebar. Save this to disc and edit it as necessary. You need
  		to be very careful not to "break" the structure of the document. Refer to
  		the registration template in your configuration directory for advice on
  		what to write.
  	</p>
   
   <p>
     The Astrogrid registry is capable of loading a registration document directly from a URL. This is probably the easiest way to register from the CEC as it is possible to use
     a web browsers "copy link" operation on one of the application registrations and then paste that URL to the registry upload page on the registry application. 
   </p>
	</section>

<section name="Deregistering obsolete resources">
	
	<subsection name="Ceasing service of an application">
	  <p>
		  If you want to cease service of an application, then you should update the list 
		  of managed applications in the service registration of your CEC. Do this by
		  changing the configuration - see the manual-registration section, above
		  - and repeating the registration of the CEC as described above. This states to the IVO
		  that your own CEC no longer provides the application. It doesn't eliminate the
		  registered description of the application; thus you can do this whether or not
	  	you originally registered the application and whether or not other services are
	  	offering the same application.
	  </p>
	</subsection>
	
	<subsection name="Unregistering an application">
		<p>
			Unregistering an application removes it from the IVO resource-register causing 
			the IVO to forget its details. You must do this if you control the 
			application implementation - i.e. the HTTP service that the CECs call -
			and you are taking it out of service permanently.
		</p>
		<p>
			To deregister an application, use the controls for the registry; you can't do this
			from the CEC's local controls. The exact technique varies between registry 
			implementations, but typically you set the <i>status</i> attribute of the
			registration to "deleted".
		</p>
	</subsection>
	
	<subsection name="Deregistering the CEC service">
 	  <p>
		  If you want to withdraw your CEC from service permanently or for a lengthy period 
 	  	(but not just for short down-time), then you should deregister it. You do this by 
 	  	editing the service resource-document, changing the value of the <i>status</i> 
 	  	attribute on the <i>Resource</i> element to "deleted" and re-registering it, 
 	  	as described above, under the same identifier.
 	  </p>
	</subsection>
	
</section>

</body>
</document>
