<document>
   <properties>
      <author email="pah@jb.manac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
      <title>Security</title>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="Introduction">
         <p>To utilise the CEC capabilities to the full you will need
            to configure the container to be able to use TLS/HTTPS.
            There are two main reasons for wanting to configure security
         </p>
         <ol>
            <li>To be able to interact with other services requiring
               security - the most likely of these being VOSpace</li>
            <li>The CEC itself can be configured to only allow
               authorised users to run jobs</li>
         </ol>
         <p>It is perfectly possible to run a CEC without configuring
            security as detailed on this page, but then it will only be
            able to interact with other non-secure services and be open
            to all callers.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="TLS">
         <p>Transport layer security (TLS) is the name for the
            general approach of ensuring that HTTP communications are
         </p>
         <ol>
            <li>Encrypted</li>
            <li>Authenticated - at the server, and
               optionally the client end</li>
         </ol>
         <p> - this is typically known as "enabling HTTPS".</p>
         <subsection name="Certificates">
         </subsection>
         <subsection name="Trust Anchors">
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section name="Authorization">
      <p>
        The CEC can have an authorization policy applied to the job control which can specify which users are allowed to perform various operations on the CEC.
        The policies need to implement org.astrogrid.applications.authorization.AuthorizationPolicy to allow or disallow operations. The authorization policy is configured
        in the WEB-INF/cec-spring.xml file, and the supplied file comes with a commented out bean (id="AuthorizationPolicy") that implements a useful policy that allows only authenticated access to the CEC and only allows the job owner to manipulate a job. There are other
        experimental policy implementations such as org.astrogrid.applications.manager.agast.PolicyDecisionPoint that use an external service to make the authentication decision.
        
      </p>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>