<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
   <properties>
      <author email="pah@jb.man.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
      <title>Upgrading</title>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="Upgrading">
         <p> This page describes how to install a new version of the
            CEC. component while retaining the configuration from your
            previous version.</p>
         <p> An upgrade is supplied as a new version of the WAR file
            containing the CEC. This new WAR replaces the old version.
         </p>
         <p>
            First, install the WAR for the CEC in Tomcat's
            <i>webapp</i>
            directory, as you did in the initial installation of the
            CEC. Tomcat detects the change in the WAR file and reacts
            thus:
         </p>
         <ol>
            <li>
               It "undeploys" the old copy of the web application. This
               destroys the old WAR file and all files associated with
               it,
               <em>except</em>
               the files in the directory structure at
               <i>cea.base.dir</i>
               ; Tomcat does not know about these.
            </li>
            <li>It deploys the new WAR, putting the web application
               and the CEC on-line with a default configuration.</li>
         </ol>
         <p> At this stage, the CEC won't work satisfactorily as the
            application configuration file format is different in this
            release. The following section details how an existing
            application configuration file and registry template can be
            updated for this release.</p>
         <p>
           If for some reason the updating does not work correctly, then some manual editing might be necessary. In all cases the configuration files should be 
           xml schema validated as the first stage in ensuring that the 
         </p>
         <subsection
            name="Automatic updating the application configuration files"
         >
            <p>
               If the war has simply been installed on top of an
               existing version of CEC the the environment should be
               pointing to the old configuration files. In this case
               there is a
               <a href="../admin/updateConfig.jsp">update configuration</a>
               page that is capable of reading the old configuration and
               transforming it.
            </p>
            <p>When running this page you should check that the
               paths to the configuration files are correct and then
               press the update button. This will create the correct
               contents for a new format app-description.xml file in the
               text area. This content should then be manually copied to
               the app-description.xml file.</p>
         </subsection>
         <subsection name="Manual updating of the configuration files">
         <p>If for some reason the automatic upgrade does not work, then there is an <a href="../config/CEA_UpdateConfigTo1.0.xsl">xsl script</a> that can be used to update an
            existing configuration</p>
         <p>This script can be run using an standard XSLT transformation tool such as Saxon on the app-description.xml file with the location of the registration-template.xml file as a stylesheet parameter called "regtemplate"</p>
         </subsection >
      </section>
   </body>
</document>