<document>
   <properties>
      <author email="pah@jb.man.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
      <title>USE of the CEC</title>
   </properties>
   <body>
      <section name="Using this service">
         <p>
            This server provides a dual interface for using the remotely
            defined applications, and it it possible, though perhaps not
            recommended, to control a single job with either interface.</p>
            <subsection name="SOAP services">
               The SOAP interface is the so called CEA Common Execution
               Connector interface defined by this
               <a
                  href="http://software.astrogrid.org/schema/cea/CommonExecutionConnector/v1.0/CommonExecutionConnector.wsdl"
               >WSDL</a>
               and described in this
               <a href="http://www.ivoa.net/Documents/latest/CEA.html">IVOA Note</a>
               . It is possible to write a custom application to access
               this web service with any standard SOAP toolkit. However,
               we recommend that you use one of the clients listed
               below.
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="UWS">
               The server also supports a Universal Worker Service (UWS)
               REST style interface described on the
               <a
                  href="http://www.ivoa.net/internal/IVOA/AsynchronousHome/UWS-0.4.pdf"
               >IVOA Site</a>
               . This is generally easier to drive than the SOAP
               interface, making it possible to use, for example, a web
               browser to interact with a UWS service. This CEC has a
               basic web interface for interacting with UWS built-in,
               and accessible via the side-menus.
               <dl>
                  <dt>Test Run Application</dt>
                  <dd>This allows the installed applications to be
                     run in a simple fashion via a web form. After the
                     application parameters are set a job is created in
                     the UWS system.</dd>
                  <dt>UWS Root</dt>
                  <dd>This is the root of the UWS system as defined
                     in the IVOA Standard. The initial URL gives a list
                     of jobs known to the CEC, which links to each job
                     to allow further control such as aborting or
                     deleting the job.</dd>
               </dl>
            </subsection>
      </section>
      <section name="Clients">
         <p></p>
         <subsection name="VODesktop">
            <p>
               The recommended client for this CEC is the
               <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/wiki/Home/AboutAGDesktop">Astrogrid VODesktop</a>
               .
            </p>
            <p>This client not only provides a GUI for running the
               applications on the CEC, but also provides support for
               all of the interacting services that make up the Virtual
               Observatory - for example discovery and security are
               handled seemlessly.</p>
            <p>The VODesktop also provides a programatic interface to
               access all aspects of the VO via the AstroRuntime.</p>
         </subsection>
         <subsection name="Java client">
            <p>Astrogrid supplies a Java client for the SOAP
               service that deals with creating a authenticated SOAP
               connection to the server.</p>
         </subsection>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>