<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="gtr@ast.cam.ac.uk">Guy Rixon</author>
        <title>Upgrading</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Upgrading"><p>
	This page describes how to install a new version of the CEC.
	component while retaining the configuration from your previous version.
	</p>
<p>
	An upgrade is supplied as a new version of the WAR file containing the CEC.
	This new WAR replaces the old version.
</p>
<p>
	First, install the WAR for the CEC in Tomcat's <i>webapp</i> directory, as you
	did in the initial nstallation of the CEC. Tomcat detects the change in the WAR file
	and reacts thus:
</p>
	<ol>
		<li>It "undeploys" the old copy of the web application. This destroys the
		old WAR file and all files associated with it, <em>except</em> the files
		in the directory structure at <i>cea.base.dir</i>; Tomcat does not know about these.</li>
		<li>It deploys the new WAR, putting the web application and the CEC on-line
		with a default configuration.</li>
	</ol>
<p>
	At this stage, the CEC won't work satisfactorily as it doesn't have the correct
	environment settings. You need to reapply the settings held over from before
	the upgrade.
</p>
	<p>
		The environment settings are saved in a file in the <i>config</i> directory
		underneath <i>cea.base.dir</i>. If you have used the default value for
		<i>cea.base.dir</i> then the web application can guess where it is. In this case,
		you can use the <i>reload saved environment</i> link from the sidebar to reapply
		the environment. After you've done this, the CEC should be using exactly the same
		configuration as before the upgrade.
	</p>
	<p>
		If you redefined <i>cea.base.dir</i>, then the web application cannot find the 
		saved environment and so cannot reload the configuration without help. In particular,
		the <i>reload saved environment</i> link in the sidebar will not work. In this case,
		you can recover the configuration in one of two ways. 
	</p>
	<ol>
		<li>Re-enter the environment entries using the environment editor. This includes 
			re-establishing <i>cea.base.dir</i> so that the CEC can then find the other, saved
			parts of the configuration.</li>
		<li>Find the old <i>cea.base.dir</i> and copy the file holding the environment into
			Tomcat's configuration directory. The configuration directory for Tomcat is <em>not</em>
			<i>(cea.base.dir)/config</i>; it is the directory <i>conf/Catalina/localhost</i> under
			the top directory of the Tomcat installation.</li>
	</ol>
	<p>
		If the new version of the CEC component has different configuration details, then you
		may need to change the environment or the configuration files or both. Read the release
		notes (use the link in the sidebar in the new web application) to check.
	</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
