<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Glossary</title>
    <author email="jl99@star.le.ac.uk">Jeff Lusted</author>

    <author email="Noel.Winstanley@manchester.ac.uk">Noel
    Winstanley</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
                <section name="Glossary">
   <dl>
        <dt>Workflow</dt>

        <dd>
          <p>There are a few nuances surrounding the term
          workflow.</p>

          <p>A workflow is a set of pieces of work coordinated to
          achieve a target of some astronomical investigation. Each
          piece of work is considered a step in the workflow, and
          will be undertaken by running a computer program.</p>

          <p>A concise and somewhat abstract definition such as the
          above leaves a lot to be desired and inevitably sounds
          somewhat pompous. However, in concrete terms a workflow
          is described in XML and is stored as an XML document, ie:
          as a file on a file system. When we refer to a workflow,
          the reference is often to such an XML document. A
          workflow XML document has an XML schema to describe it,
          and so the structure of a workflow has an abstract design
          that all workflows should adhere to.</p>

          <p>A workflow consists of a hierarchical structure of
          parts (steps, tools, flows, sequences). We currently use
          Castor to generate the Java classes from the XML schema.
          And a particular instance of a workflow XML file may be
          deserialized or instantiated into a set of Java objects.
          So, when we refer to workflow, we can also be referring
          to the Java class named Workflow, or even more probably
          to a particular object of type Workflow.</p>

          <p>To further complicate matters, in the round a workflow
          usually refers to the design, whereas a job is the
          execution-time equivalent, somewhat in the way that a
          blueprint of a building is not the building. In Astrogrid
          parlance, a job is a workflow that has been submitted for
          execution.</p>

          <p>Sorry. Anyone familiar with software development will
          recognize this confusing level of meaning. It&#39;s part
          of the job (no pun intended). Most meanings are clear
          from the context.</p>
        </dd>
      </dl>
                </section>

    </body>
</document>
