<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Overview of Astrogrid</title>
        <author email="jdt@roe.ac.uk">John Taylor</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Overview of AstroGrid">
            <p> The AstroGrid project (<a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/">http://www.astrogrid.org/</a>) aims to 
                produce a working datagrid for key selected databases, with associated datamining facilities, by late 
                2004. It is part of the world-wide drive towards the concept of a Virtual Observatory (VO), and can be 
                seen as the UK contribution to this vision. However in various ways it is both wider and more focussed 
                than other initiatives. It is wider in that it covers astronomy, solar physics, and space plasma (solar 
                terrestrial) physics, and covers all wavelengths from radio to X-ray. The project is also part of a 
                coherent UK e-science programme, with links to projects in particle physics, bio-informatics, and basic 
                grid technology development. </p>
            <p> AstroGrid is however focused in that it aims to develop something recognisably like a working VO on a 
                short timescale, so that science can start getting done and technological lessons can be learned. This 
                requires concentrating on selected datasets. Our priority is to develop a virtual observatory 
                capability to support efficient and effective exploitation of key astronomical data sets of importance 
                to the UK community: for example data from WFCAM, VISTA, XMM-SSC, e-MERLIN, SOHO and Cluster. It seems 
                clear that good data curation, archive management, and datamining services all need to be closely 
                linked together. AstroGrid is therefore a partnership formed by UK archive centres and astronomical 
                computer scientists. </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Further Information">
            <p> The links on the left of the page offer comprehensive information on AstroGrid, including how to obtain 
                and use the software, tutorials, background information on the science cases driving the software 
                development, and <a href="faq.html">frequently-asked questions</a>. </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
