<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="gtr@ast.cam.ac.uk">Guy Rixon</author>
		<title>HTTP CEC: overview</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Overview">
			<p> This component provides a Common Execution Connector web-service for HTTP
				applications (HTTP-CEC for short). The HTTP-CEC makes astronomy applications available to the
				virtual observatory; notably, it makes them visible to AstroGrid's web portal, desktop UI
				and workflow system.</p>
			<p> Suitable applications for this kind of CEC (there are other kinds) run on external web-servers
				(i.e. they need not be co-located with the CEC) and can be invoked using the HTTP-get protocol;
				the CEC does not work with HTTP-post services. The HTTP-CEC acts as a proxy for the HTTP application,
				translating between the standards CEA protocols and the application's own protocol. This has 
				two advantages.
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Non-standard applications become accessible to the IVO.</li>
				<li>IVO-standard HTTP-get services (e.g. SIAP), which are already accessible
				to the IVO in a basic form, become accessible as CEA applications and can be
				used from all AstroGrid UIs.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				One HTTP-CEC can stand as proxy for any number of HTTP applications. Therefore, if
				you have an HTTP application on your web-server you can use associate it with an
				HTTP-CEC in two ways.
			</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Run your own HTTP-CEC.</li>
				<li>Have your application configured onto someone else's HTTP-CEC.</li>
			</ol>
			<p>
				If your application has a command-line interface instead of a web interface
				you should run the command-line CEC (CL-CEC) instead.
			</p>
			<p> If your application is to serve archive data then this may not be the ideal component. You
				should look first at the Data Set Access (DSA) component of AstroGrid. It is possible to use
				the HTTP-CEC as an archive interface, but the DSA component provides better support
				for archive queries. </p>
			<subsection name="Internal web-pages and local controls">
				<p>
					The CEC web-application contains a copy of these web-pages. If you install the web
					application as, say, <i>CEC-1</i> on server <i>my.cea.server</i> on port <i>8081</i>,
					then the internal web pages are at
				</p>
				<pre>
					http://my.cea.server:8081/CEC-1/
				</pre>
				<p>	
					The internal copy of the pages
					has, in its sidebar, extra links leading to local controls for configuration, testing and
					registration. Therefore, while setting up the CEC, you should look at the internal pages.
					If you can't find the controls, you're probably reading the web pages on 
					<i>software.astrogrid.org</i> instead.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
