<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="gtr@ast.cam.ac.uk">Guy Rixon</author>
		<title>Command-line CEC: overview</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Overview">
			<p> This component provides a Common Execution Connector web-service for Java-class applications.
				applications (JC-CEC for short). The JC-CEC makes astronomy applications available to the
				virtual observatory; notably, it makes them visible to AstroGrid's web portal, desktop UI
				and workflow system.</p>
			<p> Suitable applications for this kind of CEC (there are other kinds) are Java classes with
				static methods, have no graphical interface, and need no user interaction once launched.
				</p>
			<p> You should install this component if you wish to allow virtual-observatory users to run
				selected applications on your computer. You choose the applications that may be run.
				You must obtain and install these applications; they are not supplied with the JC-CEC.
				The applications will run on the computer where you install
				the service, and you must provide sufficent resources (CPU, memory, disc space) for the
				applications to run efficiently. </p>
			<p> If your application is to serve archive data then this may not be the ideal component. You
				should look first at the Data Set Access (DSA) component of AstroGrid.</p>
			<p>
				If your applications are not Java classes but are runnable from a command line, then you
				should look instead at the command-line CEC (CL-CEC).
			</p>
			<p> If your application has a web interface instead of a command-line interface then you
				should not use this component but should use instead the HTTP-CEC component of AstroGrid
				(but only if the interface is based on the HTTP-get protocol; HTTP-post is not supported).
				If the application has both command-line and web interfaces then you can use either of the
				two components. </p>
			
			<subsection name="Internal web-pages and local controls">
				<p>
					The CEC web-application contains a copy of these web-pages. If you install the web
					application as, say, <i>CEC-1</i> on server <i>my.cea.server</i> on port <i>8081</i>,
					then the internal web pages are at
				</p>
				<pre>
					http://my.cea.server:8081/CEC-1/
				</pre>
				<p>	
					The internal copy of the pages
					has, in its sidebar, extra links leading to local controls for configuration, testing and
					registration. Therefore, while setting up the CEC, you should look at the internal pages.
					If you can't find the controls, you're probably reading the web pages on 
					<i>software.astrogrid.org</i> instead.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
