<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Java Webstart Userguide</title>
        <author email="nw@jb.man.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Java Webstart Userguide - work in progress">

	<subsection name="What is Java Web Start?">
		<p>
	<a href="">Java Web Start</a> is a mechanism for program delivery through a standard Web server. 
	Initiated through the browser, these programs are deployed to the client and executed outside the scope of the browser. 
	Once deployed, the programs do not need to be downloaded again, and they can automatically download updates on startup 
	without requiring the user to go through the whole installation process again. 
	</p>
	<p>
Since these programs run outside the browser, you might think they can freely perform operations - but that is not the case. 
They continue to run within a restricted container, or sandbox. 
 Since Java Web Start runs on top of the Java 2 platform, you also have access to the underlying security architecture. 
</p>
<p>
To use Java Web Start, you only need to install the client piece.
You may not already 
users probably don't. In that case, when someone without Java Web Start tries to initiate a JNLP-packaged application, t
he user is prompted to install Java Web Start. Once installed, with a possible reboot, the user can then go on and run the desired program. 		
</p>
	</subsection>
   <subsection name="Install Java Web Start">
	<p>
To see Java Web Start in action, 
you can visit a set of five demonstration applications that Sun has available: Draw, The SwingSet Demo, Military Game, 
A Simple Notepad, and Application Manager. 
If you don't have Java Web Start previously installed, click on any of the Launch buttons to be redirected to a download page 
where you can download Web Start for your platform. 
Java Web Start itself is only about 1 MB. However, it requires the Java Runtime Environment (JRE), so if a 
you (or a user) don't have a JRE, the download size increases accordingly, to just under 6 MB on Microsoft Windows platforms. 
</p>		
	</subsection>
<p>
	TODO:
  requires that <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart/">Java Web Start</a>
	is installed on your machine <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart/download.jsp">(download web start)</a>. 
</p>		
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
