
	<document>
	<!-- see http://maven.apache.org/reference/plugins/changes/index.html 
	     
	     action - type="add|fix|remove|update"
	     	     - issue="bug-id"
	     -->
	<properties>
		<title>Workbench / ACR Changes</title>
		<author email="noel.winstanley@manchester.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
	</properties>
	<head>
		<link rel="alternate" title="RSS" 
		  href="changes.rss" type="application/rss+xml"/>		
	</head>
<body>
<release version="2008.2.rc1" date="unreleased">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2494">
        sesame service endpoint can now be altered.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2778">
        File Explorer - 'new folder' dialogue now displays correctly.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.snapshot03" date="unreleased">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2253">
        AR now accepts CEA tool structures with repeated parameters.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Altered registry resource caching scheme -faster and better cache usage.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        pre fill search form in astroscope with testquery parameters, if available.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.snapshot02" date="2008-05-12">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    Updated astroscope registry querying to process as a stream
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2718">
    errors when sending plastic messages are now displayed in click-to-dismiss dialogues.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    slightly improved presentation of STC coverage - still no STC renderer through
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    added waveband column to voexplorer / astroscope resource table
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    Altered voexplorer, astroscope, AR to work with new CDS resource format.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.snapshot01" date="2008-04-29">
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2756">
    Cures loss of focus after certain edits in QB
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2757">
    Tool tips for columns and tables in menus and tree view
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="update">
    Checked all dependent libraries for updates.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="update">
updated build and source to work with Java 1.5 (and start to take advantage of it)
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="remove">
Removed separate builds for asr, hub, etc.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2733">
    ROUND and TRUNCATE fixed.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2735">
    Fixed cardinalities for Maths and Trig functions.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2736">
    Explicit joins are now carried out more tastefully.
    The join condition is checked for tables. If required, tables
    are included automatically.
</action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2724">
        Fixed obscure race-condition in astroscope.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1" date="2008-03-31" >
    <action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2679">
    force update of vospace filesizes.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.rc2" date="2008-03-30">   
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2689">
    Improved SSAP handling in astroscope
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Fixed race condition at startup of fetching helpmap (as seen by Dave).
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2681">
        fixed code error in content-type filter.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Increased defensive coding in resource parser. This will fix problems seen when doing reg query through AR
     </action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.rc1" date="2008-03-28">
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
added to, and made uniform, UI help tags.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2640">
    Freshened all example resource lists. Made the examples location a preference
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2609">
    VOExplorer left-right resizing now works properly.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="update" issue="2677">
    Updated to latest browser-control library
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2665">
    Improved synchroniation to prevent concurrent modification exceptions in helio/astroscope.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2675">
    Added preference to enable chunking of transfers to filestore.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
    Added button to fire an availability query from voexplorer
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2640">
    Altered initial capacity settings of HtmlBuilder and reviewed instances of StrBuilder
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add" >
    Added tooltip of login information - including DN - to login indicator.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
Improved display of security info in voexplorer, and force login when trying to execute
a secured service in taskrunner.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2673">
    Minor fix to style sheets to correct Group By error in ADQL.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2649">
    Another minor fix to the sizing of Query Builder.
    Renamed the comment tab in QB to Comment rather than Information plus icon change.
    Slightly more tasteful failure if tabular metadata not found.
    Improved comment processing. (added C and C++ style)
</action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.beta5" date="2008-03-25">
<action dev="nw" type="add">
Display test queries in resources, and allow them to be executed.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2666">
Query size estimator gives total size of registry.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="update">
Upgraded parser to handle SSAP v0.4 resource schema
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
FileExplorer: fixed handling of spaces in filepath.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
Improved appearance on windows
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
System tray now responds to right and left mouse clicks
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
Provide better info when sending vizier tables via plastic.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
Improved filenames generated when downloading vizier tables.
</action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.beta4" date="2008-03-17">
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2639">
    Tables should not be case sensitive in ADQL.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2632">
    Execute button enabled and populated within TaskRunner.
    Some failsafe checking when trying to retrieve tabular metadata.
    Some ivorns within registry inconsistent on case when used as a foreign key.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2624">
    Renable astroscope search button when resolve fails.
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2610">
    Resource list popup menu on OS X no longer deselects selected resource.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2422">
    File dialogue remembers position last browsed to.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2439">
    File dialogue can now display in list view.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2629">
    Improved progress display of self tests.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2613">
test for running on low memory.
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2532">
    Changed text colour in smart list progress bar for readability.
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2430">
    Finally fixed problems with initial expansion state of resource list tree.
</action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.beta3" date="2008-03-10">
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2362">
    Resizing query builder.
</action>
<action dev="pah" type="fix" issue="2578">
    Fix VOSpace problems via AR (now use filemanager-client-2008.0b2).
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2595">
    Work around bug which caused preference saving to fail at java 1.6.
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2562">
    Multiple capabilities (even of the same kind) per resource now supported
    in AstroScope.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2418">
    In-context menu reintroduced into Query Builder
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="add" issue="2559">
  New network preferences configuration panel enables configuration of
  HTTP proxy and other network system preferences.
</action>
<action dev="mbt" type="fix" issue="2430">
  Make sure resources tree is expanded when first viewed.
</action>
<action dev="pah" type="fix" issue="2547">
 "concrete" myspace ivorns used to call cea server
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2546">
    Final aspects of ADQL folded into Query Builder
</action> 
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2560">
    Retrieval of metadata for Query Builder now at Registry v1.0
</action>
</release>
<release version="2008.1.beta2" date="2008-01-30">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2520">
    URLs now visible in voexplorer resource display
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" due-to="silvia">
    Corrected labelling of STAP services
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" issue="2526">
        Pointed help at beta site
        </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Upgraded registry client and parser to registry v1.0
        </action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2419">
    TabularMetadataViewer.
    Fixed NPE when column value null.
    Fixed incorrect inclusion of columns after a sort.
</action>        
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2466">
    Improved :8080 selftest.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2465">
        Fixed filename-related bug on windows. 
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.beta1" date="2007-12-12">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2348">
    Astroscope: made popup query failure messages configurable.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    Astroscope: Added icons to service types, and nodes that have result files associated - assists navigation,
    and makes it clear where results are present in the tree.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
     Astroscope: completed results table view.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="remove">
    Astroscope: removed Vizier search protocol, as the search url format
    used (e.g. http://vizier.u-strasbg.fr/viz-bin/votable/-dtd/-A?RA=10.674458&amp;DEC=40.865889&amp;SR=0.01 )
    has stopped working. A replacement is not documented on the CDS site.    
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    Helioscope: Implemented as a subset of Astroscope resources
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="kevin">
    TaskRunner: fixed missing class error when executing an ADQL query.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Astroscope: Hide service-type balloons for those service-types that are not being queried.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1729">
        Astroscope: Corrected parsing of siap and ssap service responses.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha8" date="2007-11-27">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2427">
    System tray: added additional armour to fallback if system tray fails after initialization.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    AR: added configuration preferences to assist running in low-bandwidth environments
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    UI: improved interface to background processes - progress reporting, viewing, retry.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    VOExplorer: improved formatted of resource contents
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    UI: reviewed modal dialogues, replaced with non-modal where sensible
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2415">
        Self tests: added a 'help' button
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2417">
        VOExplorer: Fixed word-wrapping in annotation boxes
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2420">
        Task Runner: enabled refresh operation
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2414">
    Self tests: made tests less twitchy, improved ui, and made less intrusive.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2409">
        Task Runner: Improved formatting and accessability of error messages
        and transcripts.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2411">
    fixed misconfigured registry endpoint
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    improved usability of astroscopes position-resolving input field.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha7" date="2007-11-13">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2317">
     Added upload and download buttons to fileexplorer
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2389">
    repaint of status balls in login dialogue
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    Filled out the application menubars, guided by Apple usability docs. Added cut / copy / paste support. Some work still to do on astroscope menus.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2377">
        Made any plastic operation selectable, regardless of whether type information matches.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Extended drag-n-drop integration with host OS
        (drag files between fileExplorer and local text editor / file manager). Works on OSX, partly on Ubuntu, not yet on Windows
    </action>
    <action dev="mbt" type="add">
       Changed VOExplorer resource lists component from a JList to a JTree.
       Associated changes include providing subscribed lists/folders and
       folder import/export.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1837">
    Astroscope / AR: improved detection of DAL error responses.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2189">
        AR: made STAP service accessible from XMLRPC
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2372">
        Fixed vizier search with +ve declination
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2148">
        Implemented missing registry method.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2116">
        AR: util.tables now accepts CSV as input.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Updated AR dialogues: login, toolEditor, fileChooser and resourceChooser to use latest UI
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added self-tests on startup to detect and warn about common problems (no network, core services unavailable, etc)
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha6" date="2007-10-08">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2334">
        Taskrunner: myspace outputs now appear
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2349">
        Taskrunner: fixed access to results.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2354">
    Fileexplorer: can now send fits files over plastic.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add" >
        Taskrunner: passes a menu to QB to be used as a context-menu
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1894">
        Taskrunner: more helpful handling of file:// indirect parameters
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update" >
        Taskrunner: improved form layout and help display, based on review suggestions
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Xmlrpc AR interface: serialized beans now provide type information
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    Activities: when an activity is triggered on a large selection (> 30 items), user is prompted to confirm.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    File dialogue: added separate input field to specify filename.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        General: Improved error handling and reporting
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Taskrunner: records parameter set used in each invocation, and offers ability to reload this parameterset back into the editor.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    Taskrunner: renamed and debugged the 'reveal file' action.
        - now does a refresh if file is not present.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Voexplorer: Tidied up annotations xml format - all previous annotations will be lost.
        Improved annotation store performance, and annotation ui.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Voexplorer: Added 'select all' and 'invert selection' menu operations.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2300">
        Voexplorer: fixed ui snag
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="remove">
        Activities: Removed scirpting again - very memory inefficient - need to rethink and come up with a different approach.
    </action>    
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha5" date="2007-09-11">
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added ability to directly download / send to plastic vizier tables from voexplorer 
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Improved layout of voexplorer window
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Improved display of annotations in resource table and details pane.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    Implemented new list of resourcelists in voexplorer 
    </action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2277">
    Query Builder.
    Reinstated one-touch expansion for split pane.
    Corrected inability to see diagnostics and history panes.
    Eliminated Adql/x validation messages in favour of AdqlCompiler messages.
</action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        VoExplorer sends and accepts bibcode plastic messages - for paperscope integration
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Fixed fileexplorer window size.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Altered tables to have white background in metal LAF
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="remove" issue="2301">
        Removed misleading 'test' button.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" >
        Fixed construction of UI code so it's always on eventDispatchThread.
        This fixes some of the problems seen under Windows / Java 6
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Updated file chooser dialogue to use new FileExplorer UI
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Indicate 'handoff' with a transient popup notification when 
        plastic message is sent to another application
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha4" date="2007-08-23">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    in smart list query editor, form values persist when switching between criteria.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added a 'rename' operation to tasks list.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added a starter XQuery to the xquery editor box.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added filterwheel options for ImageServiceType
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2274">
        Fixed colours of query size indicator
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2293">
        File explorer views now clean up on user logout - 
        now possible to cleanly switch between different user accounts.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2279">
        Fixed selection shading for 'list' view.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Minor improvements to file explorer
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2285">
    Astroscope now launches again.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha3" date="2007-08-13">
    <action dev="mbt" type="add">
        Provided option to configure which columns are displayed in VOExplorer
        resource display table.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Implemented the basic operations in fileexplorer - copy, delete, rename, move, newFolder
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added a column number column to table metadata viewer.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2272">
        Improved error trapping and reporting in taskrunner
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    Added operation to task runner results view to reveal indirect results 
    in file explorer.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Result files in task runner can be dragged and dropped to file explorer to  save them
        to myspace or local disk.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2273">
        Execute button now populates in query builder.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2270">
        TaskRunner doesn't barf when encountering an unknown cea server
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Improved efficiency and caching behaviour of myspace file view
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha2" date="2007-08-06">
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        VOExplorer searches halt completely when pressing the 'stop search' button.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
        Fixed a problem with displaying contents of a voexplorer folder after
        creating / editing that folder.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2260">
        Usability enhancements to task runner: made full adql editor resizable, 
        remembered adql editor expansion state and parameter values when 
        flipping between tool interfaces
    </action>

    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Improved presentation of vomon information in login dialogue
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Reimplemented taskrunner 'execute' button to present a choice of
        available servers.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2255">
        Clarified the function of the filter field by adding 'gray text' and a 'clear filter' button.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Altered persistence format for resource lists to more human-friendly xml.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
       TaskRunner: Added tooltips showing message history for tasks
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    Task Runner now shows file results even when in myspace root directory
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2261">
    Removed the 'load from storage' button for simple types -  boolean, enumeration, integer and float-like types.
    Show a specialzed input for radius parameters - detected when name=Radius or ucd=PHYS_SIZE_RADIUS.
    Added ability to 'pin' parameter help by clicking on the parameter heading. 
    Made an effort to get parameter help to appear when mouse-overing input dialogues.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="2257">
        Improved progress reporting of tasks - progress starts earlier, and shows more, more often.
    </action>
</release>
<release version="2007.4.alpha1" date="2007-07-26">
    <action dev="mbt" type="fix">
    Fixes related to entering positions and radii in AstroScope.
    Only 1-d radius can now be entered; sexagesimal-&gt;decimal conversion 
    bugs are fixed; position and radius parsing is more lenient (e.g. 
    permits embedded spaces and leading + signs); and 'sexagesimal' display of
    radius is now in decimal arcseconds rather than dd:mm:ss.ss.
    See bugs 1824, 1939, 2185.
    </action>
    <action dev="jdt" type="fix">
    Improved the way the PLASTIC hub deals with orphaned .plastic files - no more annoying user messages.  See bug 2248.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added the first few operations to file explorer.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
        Added the first few operations to file explorer.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    Implemented Task Runner UI
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    Integrated ADQL Query Builder with Task runner, and enabled it
    to operate on catalogues and cea applications.
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
        Merged tabular metadata viewers used in voexplorer and query builder
    </action>   
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    Reworked remote execution framework
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="removed">
    Removed old application launcher UI
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    Implemented minimalistic ui for when system tray is not available
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    remote execution framework consults vomon to choose suitable server
    </action>
    <action dev="nw" type="fix">
    Debugged AR ADQL parser
    </action>            
</release>
<release version="2007.3.alpha4" date="unreleased">
<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Added icons for types / capabilities of resources to voexplorer.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Added filtering of boring system services from voexplorer
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="dave@ast.cam.ac.uk">
	Debugged -configFile and -configURL options. 
	Updated -list to generate a configuration file that can be passed back to AR.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="remove" due-to="dave@ast.cam.ac.uk">
Removed confusing -D commandline option.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="dave@ast.cam.ac.uk">
Fixed error reported as 
org.astrogrid.desktop.modules.system.HivemindFileSystemManager does not contain a property named 'temporaryFileStore'.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
  Added Configuration.reset() to the public AR interface. Provided access to this
  from HTML and UI preferences interfaces.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
fixed system-properties-overriding-preferences bug. System properties now take precedence.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="remove">
	Removed scripting activities - performance was poor in the current approach.
	Replace with a wizard-driven implementation.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	Improved logging of startup process, and configured logging to a file.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	Re-worked UI to remove use of popup modal dialogues where possible
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	Fixed behaviour of vomon on shutdown of cache.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	Streamlined the startup process - parsing of CertificatesList, etc now
	more on background threads.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	Mended build process, added generation of javadoc, hivedoc, and configuration key docs.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	Javadoc improvments
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2152">
    First bug fixes for Query Builder after VOExplorer development.
    Requires new version of AdqlStoX: astrogrid.adqlstox.version=2007.2sx
    Requires new version of adql xmlbeans: astrogrid.adql_v1_0a2.version=1.2-b000xmlbeans 
</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.3.alpha3" date="unreleased">
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Denoted which features of the UI are alpha / beta / unimproed quality.
	</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.3.alpha2" date="unreleased">
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
		Implemented script frameworks.
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="update">
		Merged astroscope and helioscope, integrated with action system.
		Added support for space + time STAP queries.
		Implemented tabular result display in astroscope
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Various fixes and relabelling suggested by Andy
		Reworked menus.
	</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.3.alpha1" date="unreleased">
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
		Added search builder, split voexplorer and fileexplorer into separate windows,
		and other suggestions from Andy.
	</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.2.pre7" date="unreleased">
<action dev="nw" type="add">
Made a start on an activities framework.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="remove">
Removed old main window
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Implementing File Explorer
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Session support - AR is now multi-user.
</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.2.pre5" date="unreleased">
<action dev="nw" type="add">
   First draft of voexplorer
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="remove">
	Removed workflow editor, parameterized worlflow launcher, various other bits
	that won't be in voexplorer
</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.2.pre1" date="unreleased">
<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Implemented Registry Explorer
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="update">
	Reviewed and tidied up icons.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="add" issue="2032">
    (1) Removal of Adql/x view unless in advanced mode. Read only when present.
    (2) Partial merging of tree and Adql/s views.
    (3) Introduction of an edit history pane.
    (4) Introduction of Edit drop down menu.
    (5) Now uses a more advanced version of AdqlStoX.	 
</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.1.1" date="2007-02-06">
	<action dev="nw" type="remove">
		Removed stripping of axis and security jars. Larger filesize, but ukidss access works again. 
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	  Improved display of registry entry content - type of registry entry.
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Improved astroscope service response parsing - handles ISO response correctly.
	</action>
</release>
<release version="2007.1" date="2007-01-31">
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1970">
	registry explorer renders urls with odd schemes correctly.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1855">
	Fixed xml display when reg explorer is empty.
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Implemented preference system. Makes it simple to: altering caching behavior, 
	location of working directory, registry endpoint, etc. 
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="update">
	Replaced javahelp system with linkage to website 
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	Cleaned out and improved unit and integration tests
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="add">
Added AR interface to vomon monitoring service.
Used this to improve UI (login dialogue, registry google)
</action>
<action dev="nw" type="fix">
	On startup, workbench will fallback to local copies of config if wiki is unavailable.
	Set shorter timeout for connecting to wiki. 
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="2022, 2023, 2025">
		Combination of fixes.
		Dependent on fix #2020 on the AdqlStoX compiler.
		Solves bugs #2023 and #2025
		(1) The different views for Adql are consulted before executing a query just in
		    case there are errors or uncommitted edits. 
		(2) Quoted identifiers are allowed (eg: "2xmmp" for a table name) but the xml
		    given to the dsa remains the same.		 
</action>
</release>
<release version="2006.4.151106" date="2006-11-15">
	<action dev="jl" type="add" issue="1794">
		Workbench - Query Builder: Adql/s view now uses new AdqlStoX compiler.
		AdqlStoX dependency added. 
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Workbench - Myspace: fles of size less than 1kb are reported as 1kb, not 0kb.
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="update">
		Packaging: Updated plastic library to latest release
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="update">
		Packaging: Updated various 3rd party libraries to latest releases - xfire, ehcache
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="update">
		Packaging: Updated minimum supported java version to 1.4.2
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1958">
		Workbench: Improved reliability of opening web pages from workbench
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add" issue="1885">
		Workbench - Usability:  Reimplemented file chooser dialogue, based in dialogue used in Topcat. Still experimental.
	</action>
</release>
<release version="2006.4.rc1" date="2006-11-06">


	<!--  new additions -->
	<action dev="gtr" type="add">
		Workbench: Enabled UKIDSS access. UKIDSS ADQL and Cone services can now by queried from Task Launcher. 
	</action>
    
	<action dev="nw" type="add" issue="1814">
	Workbench - Registry Search:  Task Launcher, Workfllow Editor and Astroscope components use fast streaming
	registry client.  Formatting of registry entries 
	is improved. Responsiveness improved by caching registry records. Deleted applications and services aren't displayed anymore.
	</action>

	<action dev="jl" type="add" issue="1790">
		Workbench - Query Builder: sort columns within metadata display.
		Clicking on column header sorts alphabetically, either ascending or descending. 
</action>

	<action dev="nw" type="add" issue="1788">
	Workbench: Added list of available communities to login dialogue
	</action>
	    <action dev="pjn" type="add" issue="1882">
        Workbench - Science workflows: added ability to save the workflow without executing it.
    </action>

	<action dev="nw" type="add">
		Packaging: stripping unused code to reduce executable size.
	</action>	
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Plastic: Astroscope, Myspace, Lookout now send Spectra Plastic Messages.
	</action>

    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    	AstroRuntime: DAL (Cone, SIAP, SSAP) interface - Added methods to return a parsed
    	version of the query response, and to save selected datasets.
    </action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add" issue="1413, 1574">
		AstroRuntime: Implemented interface to standard IVOA registry; Uses a streaming parser and improved data model.
	</action>
    <action dev="nw" type="add">
    	AstroRuntime: Improved Sesame name resolver interface.
    </action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add" issue="1585">
	AstroRuntime: Added votable manipulator (STIL) interface
	</action>
	
	
	<!--  updates -->
	<action dev="pjn" type="update">
		Workbench: Reorganized front pane tabs and buttons.
	</action>    
	<action dev="nw" type="update">
		Workbench: Updated helper application links
	</action>
    <action dev="nw" type="update">
    	Workbench: Updated splashscreens and icons
    </action>

<!--  fixes -->
	<action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1719">
	  Astroscope - Usability:
	   Save object names in search history;
		Indicate completed searches; Indicate number of results from each service;
		Added save button to heliscope;
		Corrected 'Go To Top' button label and set added shortcut key.	
	</action>
	
    <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1889,1892,1896">
        Workbench - Usability: Changed file open icon;
        Improved MySpaceBrowser menus
    </action>
    
    <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1836, 1726">
       AstroRuntime: honours user registry endpoint settings;  no longer fails if connected to by applications a second time.
    </action>    

	<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1780, 1777">
		Astroscope: handles non-standard siap responses; updates display when plastic application connects.
	</action>

	<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1710">
		Workbench - Lookout: can now delete from list of workflows.
	</action>
	
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="1768">
		Workbench - QueryBuilder: Sorting of tables before metadata display.
		Correction of bug in metadata display preventing display when archive separately chosen.
		Correction of displaying of brackets in Query Builder
</action>

	<action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1366">
		Workbench - Usability: Fixed 'enter' or 'return' to work on Registry panel for workflow.
	</action>
 
    <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1762, 1734, 1757">
        Plastic: Improved concurrency behaviour of Plastic hub, added more tests; 
         Made hub more robust to duff clients;  Hub now only unregisters xmlrpc clients when there's an
        IOException, not if the client faults; fixed XML-RPC return type conversion;
         Assorted other fixes: hub now self registers properly and responds to messages such as getName;
         Rephrased pop-up text on plastic registration;  Removed "list" plastic applications button from all variants except plastic hub-only AR.
    </action>
	
</release>
<!--  last 'major' release -->
<release version="2006.3.rc1" date="2006-06-28">
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Implemented a right-click 'Send-To' menu to send a data item to browser, local disk, or PLASTIC application.
	Send-To menu is available in Lookout, Myspace Browser, Astroscope and Helioscope.
	</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
		Implemented snitching and update checking.
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
		Added menubar to astroscope and helioscope
	</action>
	<action dev="gtr" type="add" issue="1537">
		Added MyProxy Authentication
	</action>
<action dev="jl" type="update" issue="1626">
	Query Builder: Nesting of logical constructs AND/OR massaged.
	Plus minor refactoring.
</action>	
<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="1664">
	Query Builder: 
	Adql/x pane now makes explicit call to org.astrogrid.oldquery.sql.Sql2Adql 
</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Reworked scheduled tasks - update of all  are displayed in UI
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Added back in missing registry chooser
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Improved handing of name resolving in astroscope
	</action>
	<action dev="kmb" type="fix">
		Improved Astroscope and Helioscope window layout
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="fix">
   		Plastic: HubStopping message is sent. 
   	</action>
   	<action dev="jdt" type="update">
   	 Plastic: if you now register with an empty list of supported messages then you get what you asked for - ie nothing. 
   	  In other words, an empty list no-longer means "send me everything"
	</action>
</release>
<release version="2.2-beta-2" date="2006-04-27">
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Fixed startup problems with windows webstart version of workbench.
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
		Added 'halt query' button to astroscope. Also added a 'halt all tasks' button to the tasks list (which does much the same
		thing, but is available in all windows)
	</action>
	<action dev="kmb" type="add">
		Added the ability to toggle and convert when needed between degrees and sexagesimal numbers for Astroscope.
		required new dependency from a stilt package, visually new toggle button.  PositionTextField now used
        for input boxes, but will require refactoring later to pull out conversion routines to a better class.
	</action>
	<action dev="gtr" type="add">
		Added in MyProxy stubs
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add" due-to="Francesco Pierfederici">
		Added configuration option to set IP address for the webserver to use (necessary for dual-nic machines)
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix">
		Made helpsets configurable
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="Mark Taylor">
		Added browser control for non-webstart versions
	</action>
</release>
<release version="2.2-beta-1" date="2006-04-25">
	<action dev="nw" type="update">
		Split monolithic Workbench into AR family
		Converted system from picocontainer to hivemind.
	</action>
</release>
<release version="1.6-beta-1" date="2006-04-12">
<action dev="jdt" type="fix">
Made the Finder more robust to orphaned ACR config files.  Also now can prompt the user before starting the ACR, and prompt if the start up is taking too long.
</action>
<action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1624">
	Plastic: showObjects message wasn't working for xml-rpc.
	Plastic: added an option to show debug information from the workbench
	console.
</action>
<action dev="jl" type="update" issue="1605">
	Query Builder: Command structure in place and working.
	Visually the only change is the addition of an undo/redo facility.
</action>
</release>
<release version="1.5" date="2006-04-10">
	<action dev="kmb" type="fix">
		Corrected astroscope to show offset in arcseconds (previously was in decimal degrees)
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="update">
	Updated Plastic version to 0.4
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="add">
	Hub now writes out its ivorn into the .plastic file
	and only overwrites this file (if found) if it belongs to the
	ACR.  Polite behaviour in case other hubs are running.
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="add">
	Hub is now protected against Exceptions thrown by RMI clients.
	</action>	
	<action dev="nw" type="update">
	Updated to use AstroGrid release 2006.2
	</action>
	<action dev="kmb" type="add">
			Helioscope: minor changes to make the combo box editable and val node to show only the startdate as the label.
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="fix">
			Fixed Plastic hub shutdown message, which wasn't always
			getting sent.
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="update">
			Upgraded the Plastic Library.
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1610">
			Fixed problem with xml-rpc apps not receiving messages when they register for specific messages.
	</action>				
	<action dev="pjn" type="add">
			Workflow builder: Feedback from Silvia - stripping
			transcripts opens new builder window, and tooltips altered.
			Registry browser: Basic tree view panel onto returned data
			added
	</action>
	<action dev="kmb" type="fix">
			Helioscope/Stap: Just small clean up areas really. such as
			siap->stap in comments. Changed helioscope date to back date
			such as year 2000-1-1T00:00:00.
	</action>
	<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="1606">
			Query Builder: Problem inserting column references with new
			template query.
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
	Added ability to access VizieR tables as Cone Search. Appears in Application
	Launcher. Not yet in astroscope - needs a stream-reading soap client for registry entries.
	</action>
 	<action dev="jl" type="add" issue="1542">
	    Query Builder: Improvements to low level editing of tree view.
	</action>
	<action dev="pjn" type="add" issue="1234">
			WorkflowBuilder: details of any workflows loaded from storage now displayed - was a request for portal, but added to workbench.
		</action>
	    <action dev="pjn" type="add">
			Various useability improvements: Menubar on application launcher and new tool clears old info, 
			dialog sizing issue, parameter editor column headings less criptic
		</action>
    	<action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="1542">
		Helioscope: Rough draft of the first helioscope.
	</action>
</release>
<release version="1.4" date="2006-03-06">

 	<action dev="jl" type="add">
	    Query Builder: structured adql added. Metadata pane displays table structure.
	    Synchronized editing of adql/s and adql/x; Auto-chooses dataset if possible.
	</action>
    	<action dev="pjn" type="add">
	   Workflow Transcript Viewer added. Integrated with Lookout; can strip transcript and re-open
	   in workflow editor
	</action>
	<action dev="pjn" type="add">
		Workflow Editor: Added script validation; Added cut/copy/pase and import/export to script editor; added menu options for insert, for use with Macs
	</action> 
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
		Astroscope: summarizes services called; displays spectra; 
		integration with ESA VoSpec; 
		datatips remain visible as long as mouse hovers over;
		plasticized
	</action>
	<action dev="kmb" type="fix">
		Astroscope: Improved tooltips; made table of services sortable; improved node display
	</action>	
	
	<action dev="kmb" type="add">
	    Registry Search: enabled use of AND / OR in searches; enabled filters in full-text search.
	</action>
    	<action dev="pjn" type="fix">
	    Registry Search: Improved display
	</action>
	<action dev="jdt" type="add">
		Plastic: Implemented polling listeners for applications that can't directly
		receive messages; added methods to allow clients to get information about each other.
	</action>	
	<action dev="jdt" type="fix">
		Plastic: bug fixing; lots of unit tests; consistency between RMI and XMLRPC; 
	</action>
	<action dev="nw" type="add">
		ACR: SSAP component
	</action>	
	</release>
	
	<release version="1.3-1" date="2005-12-02">
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			updated to latest version of stil (2.3-1)
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Improved votable parsing in astroscope
		</action>
		<action dev="kmb,gtr,nw" type="fix">
			Improved parsing of registry entries, made more error-tolerant
			- more services displayed in astroscope.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Thread-pooling, leads to speedups, and better 
			reporting - esp in astroscope
		</action>
		<action dev="pjn" type="fix">
			fixes, help added application launcher.
		</action>		
		<action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="1478">
            Merged in Plastic.
		</action>		
	</release>
	<release version="1.3" date="2005-11-23">
		<action dev="kmb" type="add">
			AstroScope - query all registered siap and cone services, 
			vizualize and navigate results, save data locally or to myspace
		</action>

		<action dev="pjn" type="add">
			Completed JES Workflow editor.
		</action>
							
		<action dev="pjn, nw" type="fix">
			Improved Query and Application launcher for CEA / SIAP / CONE services.
			Handles repeating and optional parameters.
		</action>	
				
		<action dev="kmb, pjn, nw" type="add">
			Registry  Google - search, browse and select formatted registry entries. 
		</action>

		<action dev="kmb" type="add">
			NVO DataScope launcher - saves results from datascope into myspace
		</action>		

		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			VO Lookout - launch, monitor, and control remote processes 
			(CEA / SIAP / Cone queries and tasks, JES workflows). View results.
		</action>

		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			In-program help - some documentation there, more to come
		</action>
		
		<action dev="nw" type="add" issue="1392">
			ACR support for Siap and Cone services - low level interface, plus
			integration with remote process system.
		</action>		
					
		<action dev="kmb" type="add">
			Upload and unzip archives to myspace
		</action>		

		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			hide left-hand button bar on startup - less daunting for beginners.
		</action>

		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Basic ADQL query builder
		</action>

		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			added fallback registry endpoint to configuraiton
		</action>		

		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			Moved more jars into extensions, updated versions.
			(Axis 1.3, new Astrogrid libraries)
		</action>	

		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="Mark Taylor">
			Fixed myspace upload to work under java 1.5.
			Fixed documentation for getWriteContentURL()
		</action>	

		<action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1448">
			Broken report a bug link in help.
		</action>			

		<action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1365">
			Stopped VOSpace browser intialising with a disabled tab selected.
		</action>		
		
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Improved icons and other cosmetic improvements
		</action>

	</release>





	
	
	<release version="1.1" date="2005-09-01">
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			Based on 1.1-beta-3
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.1-beta-3" date="2005-08-25">
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1328">
			myspace tree is cleared on logout
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1327">
			improved display of folders in myspace.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="Mark Taylor">
			fixed bug in 'Myspace.getWriteContentURL()' and improved documentation
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add" due-to="Richard Holbrey">
			Added 'reset configuration' option to help menu
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added user information object to community
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added listener interface to acr shutdown - so clients 
			have chance to veto, and are at least notified of this happening
		</action>		
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Fixed parsing of application registry entries to
			make more quirk-tolerant
		</action>			
		<action dev="nw" type="add" due-to="Thomas Boch">
			Added summary-returning search methods to registry interface.
			Removed wrapping elements from results.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Changed listener implementation to handle disappearance of client
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add" >
			Added final 'prompt-user' fall-through to finder.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add" due-to="ael">
			Added keyword Search to registry interface
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add" due-to="Thomas Boch">
			Added CDS interfaces
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			Updated JDIC lib to 0.9.1
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.1-beta-2" date="2005-08-12">
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="jdt">
			Fixed broken links in webstart associations
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add" due-to="Thomas Boch">
			Added 'listMetadata' method to myspace interface
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="jdt">
			grayed-out 'help' menu option until some is written
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="jdt">
			solved blank screen at startup problem
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.1-beta-1" date="2005-08-12">
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			split acr interfaces into separate project
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			updated to latest version of registry delegate
			 - now caches results, and provides xquery.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			added system tests that exercise ag components
			through rmi and xmlrpc
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			cleaned up acr public interface
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			added java rmi interface to acr
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.6-beta-1" date="2005-07-25">
		<action dev="pjn3" type="fix">
			assorted improvements of the workflow viewer
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.5" date="2005-07-10">
		<action dev="pjn3" type="add">
			Added beta of workflow viewer
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="anita">
			Improved workbench function descriptions
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			tidied up example python scripts
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added example script for connecting to ACR from perl
		</action>		
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			Updated list of external apps
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.4-beta" date="2005-07-08">
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added real splash screen
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Fixed endpoint configuration, logging configuration,
			and possible ipv6 problem.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Removed 'indirect' buttons from parameter editor for
			parameterized workflows - doesn't make sense to have it.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1221">
			Improved resource chooser dialogue to make
			it easier to use.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="remove">
			Removed 'show in portal' from job monitor - 
			never worked.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Replace file chooser dialogue by resource chooser dialogue
			throughout - means many things can be loaded / saved to myspace.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Relocate operation in myspace browser lists available stores.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Removed 'file' tab from resource chooser for indirect parameters
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Fixed error on logout
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Applications in monitor now persist between workbench sessions
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Creating a new file in the filemanager selects that filemanager
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			filemanager improvements: starts with 'home' folder selected;
			selecting a file removes selection of folder, and vice-versa;
			improved refresh; fixed folder tree vanishing.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1263">
			Made display of workflows more tolerant
			of oddities in workflow
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.3" date="2005-06-23">
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			Based on 1.0.3-beta-2
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.3-beta-2" date="2005-06-23">
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added 'system.apihelp' component - 
			returns documentation for ACR methods
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="pah">
			Fixed nulls in parameter editor
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="gtr">
			Altered query so only active applications are visible
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added map-style methods for building tool documents
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.3-beta-1" date="2005-06-22">
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added link to JDIC (Desktop Integration) JNLP Extension.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added System tray icon. Displays GUI when hidden.
			(Not on Macs).
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="pah">
			Fixed duff ivorn on repeated application launch. 
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1223">
			fixed typo.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Made application launcher remember window position.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="gtr">
			Removed inactive registry entries from app and server lists.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Made parsing of application descriptions tolerant of 
			missing data.
			Still need to fix castor problems with namespaces - until then some reg. entries will
			still cause errors.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1245">
			Improved display of loooong error messages
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="eduardo">
			Fixed 'cancel' button on parameterized workflows
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added rudimentary help set
		</action>		
	</release>

	<release version="1.0.2-eso" date="2005-06-20">
		<action dev="nw" type="update">
			Based on 1.0.2-alpha-2
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.2-beta-2" date="2005-06-20" >
		<action dev="nw" type="add" due-to="eduardo">
			Added changes report.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Bundled set of docs into jnlp site
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="1186">
			Fixed Race condition on startup - reliable, but
			perceived startup is now slower.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added cheezy splash screen to hide startup time.
			Better graphics needed.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added JavaHelp browser - now need to write helpset.
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix">
			Moved large jars into jnlp extensions - should improve download
			time for desktop updates
		</action>
		<action dev="nw" type="fix" due-to="naw">
			Added bounds checking for position-remembering windows
			Should mean that all windows are visible onscreen.
		</action>
	</release>
	<release version="1.0.2-beta-1" date="2005-06-16">
		<description>Beta Release</description>
		<action dev="nw" type="add">
			Added CEA Application Launcher GUI
		</action>
	</release>
	
</body>
</document>
