<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="noel.winstanley@manchester.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
        <title>Commandline Options</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Commandline Options">
<p>
VODesktop can be passed a number of commandline options, which alter
it's behaviour.
</p>

<subsection name="-help">
<p>
Passing the <tt>-help</tt> flag returns the following message.
</p>
<source><![CDATA[
usage: vodesktop <options>
 -addModule <module file>          file location of additional module file
 -addModuleURL <URL>               URL location of additional module file
 -debugEDT                         Enable UI Debugging
 -headless                         Run in Headless AR-only mode (no user
                                   interface)
 -help                             Shows this help and exit
 -hivedoc                          Generate Hivedoc and exit
 -list                             List configuration properties and exit
 -propertyFile <properties file>   file location of properties file
 -propertyURL <URL>                URL location of properties file

]]></source>
</subsection>

<subsection name="-headless">
<p>
This flag causes vodesktop to run  in headless mode. No user interface 
or windows will be shown. This flag makes it possible to run an AstroRuntime
on a server with no attached display; or to run an AstroRuntime in the 
background of the user's computer as a scripting host.
</p>
<p>
If the machine <i>does</i> possess a display, then a splashscreen will be shown 
at startup.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

<section name="Configuration">
<p>
The following flags are used to control the configuration of vodesktop.
Through these flags, it's possible to alter many of the runtime settings.
For further information, see the note on <a href="configuration.html">Configuration</a>.
</p>
<subsection name="-list">
<p>
Lists the configuration keys, and their current values. 
</p>
<p>
Note: the output of  <tt>-list</tt> can be saved to file, edited, and then used to configure VODesktop by using it with
 the <tt>-propertyFile</tt> or <tt>-propertyURL</tt> commandline arguments
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="-propertyFile">
<p>
Load configuration settings from the specified file
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="-propertyURL">
<p>
Load configuration settings from the specified URL
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="-Dkey=value">
<p>
Set a configuration key on the commandline. This is a JVM argument, and must occur 
before the vodesktop jar name. For example, to set the key 
<tt>system.checkForUpdates</tt> to <tt>false</tt>, do the following
</p>
<source><![CDATA[
java -Dsystem.checkForUpdates=false -jar vodesktop-app.jar <other arguments>
]]></source>
<p>
This key may be repeated. However, when setting many keys <tt>-propertyFile</tt>
is more convenient.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Extension">
<p>
The features and functionality of VODesktop can be altered radically
by implementing extension code and adding this to the application.
For further information, see the note on <a href="extending.html">Extending VODesktop</a>.

</p>
<subsection name="-hivedoc">
<p>
Generate documentation describing the internal architecture and extension
points of vodesktop, leaving results in a subdirectory called <tt>hivedoc</tt>. 
A standard copy of this documentation is 
<a href="hivedoc/index.html">here</a>. 
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="-addModule">
<p>
Load an additional XML hivemind module from a file.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="-addModuleURL">
<p>
Load an additional XML hivemind module from a URL
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="Development">
<subsection name="-debugEDT">
<p>
Enable additional debugging of the Swing Event Dispatch Thread (EDT). This should assist in catching programming errors where
long-running or IO-bound methods are called from the EDT. Any such coding violations are logged.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>