<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
        <author email="noel.winstanley@manchester.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
        <title>Configuration</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Configuration">
<p>
Many of the operating parameters of VODesktop are controlled
by configuration settings. Each setting has a name, and a value.
</p>
<p>
The available configuration settings are listed in the file  <a href="config.txt">config.txt</a>.
An equivalent file that contains the current setting values can be generated from VODesktop by using the <tt>-list</tt>
commandline flag (see <a href="commandline.html">Commandline</a>).
</p>
</section>


<section name="Changing Configuration">
<p>
The configuration of VODesktop can be altered in a number of ways.
</p>
<subsection name="Preferences Dialogue">
<p>
A subset of the most useful configuration settings can be edited using the VODesktop Preferences Dialogue.
Configuration changes made using this dialogue persist between invocations of VODesktop.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Preferences Webform">
<p>
This is a web-form that provides equivalent functionality to the preferences dialogue - it lists the same set of configuration settings, 
and any changes made persist between invocations. It's convenient to use in a headless setting where the preference dialogue cannot be displayed.
The web-form can be accessed at the <tt>preferences</tt> page relative to the context url given in the file <tt>~/.astrogrid-desktop</tt>. Alternatively, 
navigate to the context url given in <tt>~/.astrogrid-desktop</tt>, from where there's a link to the preferences webform.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Commandline">
<p>
The configuration can also be altered using the commandline. See <a href="commandline.html#Configuration">Commandline</a> for details of the flags.
Any configuration changes made via the commandline apply only for that invocation of VODesktop: they override any configuration
provided using the preferences dialogue, but these overrides do not persist between invocations.
</p>
<p>
Note: the output of the <tt>-list</tt> commandline flag can be saved to file, edited, and then used to 
configure VODesktop by passing it in using the <tt>-propertyFile</tt> or <tt>-propertyURL</tt> commandline arguments
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section name="Advanced">
<subsection name="Disabling parts of the application">
<p>
Many of the components of VODesktop and Astro Runtime can be disabled by setting commandline properties. For example, to disable RMI access to Astro Runtime,
set the configuration property  <tt>system.rmi.disabled</tt> to <tt>true</tt>. Some of the other keys that can be used in the same way are.
<table>
<tr><th>Key</th><th>Description</th></tr>
<tr><td><tt>astrogrid.myspace.disabled</tt></td><td>remove support for myspace</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>astrogrid.loginDialogue.disabled</tt></td><td>disable the login dialogue - all logins must be programmatic</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>plastic.hub.disabled</tt></td><td>disable the internal PLASTIC hub</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>system.preference.servlet.disabled</tt></td><td>disable the preferences web-form</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>system.webservice.disabled</tt></td><td>disable the internal webserver (which in turn will disable HTTP and XML-RPC access, PLASTIC, and preferences web-form)</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>system.xmlrpc.disabled</tt></td><td>disable XML-RPC access to AstroRuntime</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>system.rmi.disabled</tt></td><td>disable RMI access to Astro Runtime</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>system.html.disabled</tt></td><td>disable the HTML (HTTP) access to AstroRuntime</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>system.systray.disabled</tt></td><td>disable support for the system tray</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>util.selftest.disabled</tt></td><td>disable selftesting</td></tr>
</table>


Inspect the <a href="hivedoc/index.html">Hivedoc</a> for other components that can be disabled in the same way.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Contribution to Configuration Points">
<p>
More extensive configuration - such as providing new plugins and extensions to the application - can be achieved
by using commandline parameters to add additional Hivemind descriptors. See  <a href="extending.html">Extending VODesktop</a>.

</p>
</subsection>

</section>

<section name="Implementation">
<p>
Within the code, individual configuration settings are modelled by 
<tt>org.astrogrid.desktop.modules.system.pref.Preference</tt> objects.
These are produced and managed by <tt>org.astrogrid.desktop.modules.system.pref.PreferenceManagerImpl</tt>.
Individual preferences are declared and documented in the hivemind configuration
<tt>framework.preferences</tt>, and are available to be passed into 
other components using the <tt>preference:</tt> prefix.
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>