<document>
<properties>
        <author email="noel.winstanley@manchester.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
        <title>Files and Directories</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Files and Directories">
<p>
VODesktop stores information in a number of places on local disk. Some of these filenames are historical, and a little misleading.
</p>


<subsection name="Data Directory">
<p>
VODesktop stores caches, resource lists, and other downloaded material in the directory <tt>~/.workbench</tt>. Deleting this directory
has the affect of <b>losing all user data</b> and resetting much of the application behaviour. The files of interest within this directory are
<table>
<tr>
<th>Filename</th><th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr><td><tt>resourceLists.xml</tt></td><td>VOExplorer tree of resource lists</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>scopeHistory.xml</tt></td><td>Astroscope search history</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>storageFolders.xml</tt></td><td>File Explorer list of shortcuts</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>trusted-certificates</tt></td><td>directory of downloaded trust anchors</td></tr>
<tr><td><tt>user-annotations.xml</tt></td><td>User-provided annotations of resources in VOExplorer</td></tr>
</table>
The user / sysadmin should consider backing up these files.
</p>
<p>
Other files in this directory (with file types <tt>.data</tt> or <tt>.index</tt>) contain cached information about: registry resources;
 annotations; object positions; and  query sizes. They can be safely deleted or not backed up.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Configuration">
<p>
VODesktop uses the Java library <tt>java.util.prefs</tt> to persist it's configuration. Where this is stored is 
an implementation-specific detail of the particular Java Virtual Machine.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Logs">
<p>
Log messages from VODesktop and Astro Runtime are written to 
<tt>~/astro-runtime.log</tt>. Once this file reaches a certain size, it is rotated, which produces files named
<tt>~/astro-runtime.log.1</tt> etc. See <a href="logging.html">Logging</a> for more information.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="AstroRuntime">
<p>
When Astro Runtime is running, two files are written to the user's home directory. 
<tt>~/.astrogrid-desktop</tt> describes how a client should connect to AR using XML-RPC or HTTP. <tt>~/.acr.rmi.port</tt> descibes how a client should connect to AR via RMI.
When the application halts, this file is deleted.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="SAMP">
<p>
The SAMP hub within VODesktop write the file <tt>~/.samp</tt>, which, as per the SAMP specification, describes how other application may connect to the 
messaging hub.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="PLASTIC">
<p>
The PLASTIC hub within VODesktop writes the file <tt>~/.plastic</tt>, which describes how PLASTIC applications may connect to the hub.
When the application halts, this file is deleted.
</p>
</subsection>


</section>
</body>
</document>