<document>
<properties>
        <author email="noel.winstanley@manchester.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>
        <title>Web Interface</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Web Interface">
<p>
As well as a Graphical User Interface, VODesktop also exposes a web-based html user interface. 
When VO Desktop is running, it writes the base URL of it's web interface in the <tt>~/.astrogrid-desktop</tt> file. This can be read by external programs who wish
to connect, or alternately, you can simply copy and paste this URL into a webbrowser.
</p>
<p>
The web page of the base URL contains links to the following functionality:
</p>
<subsection name="Access to Astro Runtime">
<p>
The web interface provides access to the functions of the Astro Runtime, both at an XML-RPC endpoint and as a nested hierachy of webforms.
So, for example, to experiment with the Astro Runtime function to query a registry, from the top page navigate to <tt>ivoa - registry - keywordSearch</tt>. At this point
the behaviour of the function is documented, and there's a simple web form for you to try out the function. Details on how to call this function from another program
or script are also provided. For more details consult the Astro Runtime documentation.
</p>
<p>
These webpages can be used to perform simple low-level tests and experiments without going to the trouble of writing scripts.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Configuration Editor">
<p>
The web interface provides a page that lists all the current preferences, and allows their values to be changed. See <a href="configuration.html">Configuration</a>.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Registry XML Access">
<p>
Provides Quick and Dirty access to the raw XML of a registry entry. Useful for debugging of registry entries, producing simple scripts, etc.
The IVO-ID of the registry entry to retrieve must be provided using the <tt>?id=</tt> query parameter. 
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="File Access">
<p>
Similar to Registry XMl access, but this provides quick and dirty acess to the contents of a file, in any of the recognized types of filesystem
(currently this includes ftp, sftp, http, vospace and myspace). Useful for quick scripts, etc.
The URI of the file to read must be provided using the <tt>?id=</tt> query parameter.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>