<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community install</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Installation">
      <p>
         The installations below have mainly been tested on tomcat versions 5.0.19-5.0.28.  But the "Manual Installation" could be carried out on 
 other servlet/j2ee containers.  For the purpose of most instructions here the guide will refer to tomcat.
      <br />
      Download Location of war: http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/org.astrogrid/wars/
      <br />See astrogrid-community-???.war  where ??? is a version number.  Look at dates for latest release.
      
      </p>
      <subsection name="Manual installation/Drop-In - Preferred">
      <p>
         Most of the work is in the configure page, for installation. 
         <ul>
            <li>Take the war file and rename it if you do not like the name (be sure to keep the .war ending).  Typical names are "astrogrid-community.war" or "community.war"</li>
                <li>Now simply drop it into the webapps directory under where your tomcat is installed.</li>
                <li>Tomcat by default should unpack the war file into a directory in that webapps directory.  Directory Name should be the same as the war file minus the ".war" part.</li>
                <li><strong>Your done Read "Database" section below; then go to Configuration.</strong></li>
                <li>If it does not unpack it then you may have it turned off in your tomcat.  This will require you to deploy it through the tomcat manager.</li>
                <li>Go to your tomcat manager and login.  A link is found at the main tomcat page example if tomcat is on the local/same machine with default port set: http://localhost:8080</li>
                <li>If you relize you don't know how to login, then you will need to view a particular file located where you installed tomcat at: {tomcat install}/conf/tomcat-users.xml</li>
                <li>Unless your admin has setup tomcat to run on ldap or relational db for users; then this file should give you the username, password, and there roles for logging in.</li>
            <li>If this is a brand new tomcat then you will need to make a "manager" role and add it to a user or create a user in this file.  You should go ahead and add a "admin" as well for configuration purposes later.</li>
         </ul>
      </p>      
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="CommandLine installer">
      <p>
         Most of the work is in the configure page, for installation.  This step is quite easy take the war
 file and drop it into the webapps directory.
      </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Database installatin">
         The community webapp is intended to be able to work with any database and hence is expected for you to setup and connect it to a known database in your environment.
         If you do not have a database to connect to, then below are instructions on how to install a hsqldb database.  This is the installation part of the database, the configuration is in the configure page.
               <li> Find the hsqldb database driver. You can download from here: 
                  <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/hsqldb/jars/hsqldb-1.7.1.jar">HSQLDB 1.7.1</a> </li>
               <li> Place the hsqldb jar into a place that can be located by the servlet container, ex: for tomcat is the common/lib directory is the recommendation, You may elect to put it in your community/WEB-INF/lib but remember you will need to place it back on any upgrading.</li>
               <li> Restart tomcat this is so that tomcat will pickup this new jar</li>
               <li>That is all.</li>         
      </subsection>
    </section>
   </body>
</document>