<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community quick install</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Quick install">
            <p>
                The InstallToolkit contains all of the components required to install and configure the AstroGrid Community WebService.
                <ul>
                    <li>Ant script</li>
                    <li>Ant properties</li>
                    <li>WebService war file</li>
                    <li>3rd party libraries</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <subsection name="Required components">
                <p>
                    The InstallToolkit requires the following pre-requisites installed on the target system(s).
                    <ul>
                        <li>Apache Ant <i>(recomended version 1.5.4)</i></li>
                        <li>Apache Tomcat <i>(version 4.1.24 to 5.0.18)</i></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Local install">
                <p>
                    The InstallToolkit can install the WebService directly into a Tomcat instance on the local system.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Assuming that the pre-requisites are already installed, executing the <code>install</code> Ant task will automatically install and configure the WebService.
<source>
ant -f install.xml install
</source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Remote deploy">
                <p style="font-size:x-small;font-style:italic;margin:20px">
                    <img style="float:left;margin-right:5px" src="images/note.gif"/>
                    Remote deployment is not implemented in the current release.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The InstallToolkit can also deploy the WebService into a Tomcat server running on a remote system.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Deploying the WebService on a remote system requires Tomcat installed and running on the target system, and Ant installed on the local system.
                    Assuming that the pre-requisites are already installed, executing the <code>deploy</code> Ant task will automatically deploy the WebService on the target machine.
<source>
ant -f install.xml deploy \
    -Dtomcat.host=host.astrogrid.org \
    -Dtomcat.manager.name=xyz \
    -Dtomcat.manager.pass=xyz
</source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Alternatively, the Tomcat properties can be set by providing a local properties file, <code>tomcat.properties</code>.
<source>
#
# Target deployment hostname.
# Used by the remote deployment task.
# Change this property to specify a remote system.
tomcat.host=localhost

#
# Tomcat manager name and password
# Change these properties to match the settings on the target system.
tomcat.manager.name=QWERTY
tomcat.manager.pass=qwerty
</source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    In which case, the Ant command can be simplified to the following.
<source>
ant -f install.xml deploy
</source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Default properties">
                <p>
                    The InstallToolkit uses the following properties, configured in the <code>install.properties</code> file supplied with the toolkit.
                    <ul>
                        <li>config.home <i> - the location of the Community configuration files.</i></li>
                        <li>database.home <i> - the location of the Community database files.</i></li>
                        <li>community.name <i> - the ivo name of your Community.</i></li>
                    </ul>
<source>
# Your community name.
# The default is to use the local host name.
# Change this property if you want to change your community name.
community.name=test.astrogrid.org

# Config files location.
# The default is to put the configuration files in '/etc/astrogrid'.
# Change this property if you want to relocate the config files.
config.home=/etc/astrogrid/community

# Database files location.
# The default is to put the database files in '/var/astrogrid'.
# Change this property if you want to relocate the database files.
database.home=/var/astrogrid/community
</source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
