<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="Noel.Winstanley@manchester.ac.uk">Noel Winstanley</author>

    <title>Script Client Developer Kit</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
	<section name="Astrogrid Scripting Client Developer Kit">
    <p>
    This project assembles a Client Developer Kit (CDK) for developers that wish to
	interact with the Astrogrid Scripting Interface. This combines the delegates for accessing the Astrogrid workflow 
	services (JES, CEA) and the core Astrogrid services (Myspace / VoSpace, Registry, Community) with some scripting objects and helper
	libraries.
	</p><p>
	The workflow delegates, and the core delegates are also available separately in the smaller Workflow CDK and Core CDK.

    </p>
	</section>
	<section name="Documentation">
	<p>
    The scripting environment provided by astrogrid is documented in the Workflow userguide: <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/jes/">html</a>, 
	<a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/jes/astrogrid-workflow-userguide.pdf">pdf</a>
	</p>
  </section>
    <section name="Configuration"><p>
    All astrogrid components use a common configuration system.
    This allows properties to be set using either JNDI (if available), a configuration file, or System properties.
    The simplest method is to have a file named <code>astrogrid.properties</code> on the classpath.
    See the <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/common/apidocs/org/astrogrid/config/package-summary.html">javadoc</a>
    for further details.

    This CDK requires the following keys to be set:
    <dl>
    <dt><code>org.astrogrid.community.ident</code></dt>
        <dd>The identifier of the local community. For example <code>org.astrogrid.release</code></dd>
    <dt><code>org.astrogrid.registry.query.endpoint</code></dt>
        <dd>Endpoint of the registry query service. For example
        <code>http://katatjuta.star.le.ac.uk:8080/astrogrid-registry-SNAPSHOT/services/RegistryQuery</code></dd>
    <dt><code>org.astrogrid.registry.admin.endpoint</code></dt>
        <dd>Endpoint of the registry admin service. For example
        <code>http://katatjuta.star.le.ac.uk:8080/astrogrid-registry-SNAPSHOT/services/RegistryAdmin</code></dd>
    <dt><code>jes.job.controller.endpoint</code></dt>
        <dd>The endpoint of the jes server. For example
        <code>http://katatjuta.star.le.ac.uk:8080/astrogrid-jes-SNAPSHOT/services/JobControllerService</code>		
        </dd>
	<dt><code>org.astrogrid.community.default.vospace</code></dt>
		<dd>Registry key for default myspace service for this community. E.g. <code>ivo://org.astrogrid.release/myspace</code></dd>			

    </dl>
    </p></section>

    <section name="Development"><p>
    It's possible to deploy a mini-astrogrid (<i>Astrogrid in a Box</i>) to a single machine. This provides
    a convenient target to test clients against.
    <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/integrationTests/install.html">Installation Instructions</a>
    </p></section>
    
  </body>
</document>

