<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Changes since previous release</title>
        <author email="jdt@roe.ac.uk">John Taylor</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
    	<release version="(Pending Integration)">

          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
       Branch KEA_2715.  
      * Ticket BZ2127:
        Adjusted column descriptions for derived columns, so that if the JDBC
        results supply the source expression for that column, it is included
        in the output column description.

      * Ticket BZ2657:
        Adjusted HTML results output to show published table and column names
        rather than internal table and column IDs.

      * Ticket BZ2720:
      * Ticket BZ2721:
        Adjusted HTML and VOTable output so that catalog, table and column names
        are visible for all (recognised) non-derived columns.  In the VOTable
        view, this information is present both in each field's ID attribute
        and in the field DESCRIPTION tag.

      * Ticket BZ2759:
        Adjusted results processing so that data type of unrecognised columns
        (e.g. derived columns) is obtained (where possible) from JDBC results;
        it was erroneously defaulting to "String" for all unrecognised columns.

      * Ticket BZ2036:
      * Ticket BZ2643:
        Webapp JSP pages now using standard container security rather than
        custom login forms, for consistency with other webapps and better
        browser behaviour.  This has fixed the login problems previously
        seen with the Opera browser.
          </action>

          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
             Branch PAL-KEA-2499.  Updated registration JSP page for
             new-style registration.
          </action>
          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
             Branch PAL-KEA-2442.  Addition of VOSI endpoints etc.  
             POINT-RELEASE FOR TESTING ONLY!
          </action>

          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
             Branch PAL-KEA-2314.  Merge of CEA multicone work in progress
             so Mark T can take a fresh branch - PLEASE DON'T MAKE A NEW
             DSA RELEASE FROM THIS BRANCH!
          </action>

          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
             Branch PAL-KEA-2213.  Enhanced embedded installation 
             documentation.
          </action>
     
          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
             Branch PAL-KEA-2119.  This reduces the memory used by 
             storing records of completed queries (by slashing the amount
             of detail stored once queries are actually complete).
             Also contains preliminary architecture work for supporting 
             v1.0 VOResources as well as v0.10 (though the v1.0 resources
             are not active/available yet).
          </action>

          <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="2056">
            Branch apps-gtr-2056. This fixes BZ2056 such that Optionlist element
            in the application-description are propgated to the application
            registration. I have also added a contracts jar such that the
            installation tests work. The changed components are
            astrogrid-cea-server-2007.1.03.jar and
            astrogrid-cea-commandline-2007.1.02.war. The app-servers for
            HTTP and Java-class applications haven't been changed. There are
            no changes to the CEA client.
          </action>
          
    	<action dev="kea" type="fix">
        <em>Branch FM_KEA_2136.</em> One-line change to fix critical
        race in creating new nodes in same parent node.  See
        bugzilla ticket 2136.
      </action>    	  


        </release>
        
        <release version="(Undertest)">
        	<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    	    <em>Branch security-gtr-2191.</em> The SSL implementation is the reason for the new release. 
    	    It allows RFC3820 proxy-certificates to be used for HTTPS requests handled by Tomcat, 
    	    in accordance with IVOA standards. We can use this, e.g., to restrict access to 
    	    Cone search services in DSA/catalogue.the POM is made independent of maven-base;
    	    Changes: 
    	    <li>the POM is made independent of maven-base</li>
			<li>the unit tests work;</li>
 			<li>there is a new implementation of SSL for Tomcat</li>
    	  </action>  

        </release>
		
        <release version="HEAD">
        
         <action dev="kea" type="fix">
             Branch PAL-KEA-2378.  Final merge of CEA multicone work,
             plus other bugfixes:
             Bug 2225 
             Bug 2318
             Bug 2160 
             Bug 2407
             Bug 2227
             Bug 2392
             Bug 2374
             Bug 2311
             Bug 2405
             Bug 2412
             Bug 2402
             Bug 2433
          </action>

          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
             Branch PAL-KEA-2235.  Enhancements and fixes including bugzilla tickets :
             2219: Configuration documentation update 
             2221: Improved error reporting for missing metadoc file
             2230: HTML output available from CEA interfaces
             2003/2237: VOResource 1.0 support
             2118: HTTP chunking property now compulsory
             1962: Enhanced self-registration interface, including proper
                reporting of outcome and tests for appropriate authority ID
             2222: Fix (I hope) for EJBException problem in tomcat 5.5
          </action>
                  
        <action dev="kmb" type="fix">
        <li>Reg_KMB_Translate0_100nHarvest registry</li> for changing client lite to suit pal
		<li>KMBComms_SmallChange_RegClientUse community</li> changes to suit reg-client
		<li>KMBApps_SmallChange_RegClientUse applications</li> changes to suit reg-client
		<li>KMBDeploy_SmallChange_RegClientUse deployment </li> changes to suit reg-client
		also built components: filemanager/filestore/workflow. CEA binaries are not released, awaiting for Guy to tidy things up.
        </action>
        
        <action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    	    <em>Branch security-gtr-2244-3</em> 
    	    <li>astrogrid-security-2007.2.04.jar</li>
			<li>astrogrid-cea-server-2007.2.01.jar</li>
			<li>astrogrid-cea-commandline-2007.2.01.war</li>
			<li>astrogrid-cea-http-2007.2.01.war</li>
			<li>astrogrid-cea-javaclass-2007.2.01.war</li>
			<li>astrogrid-common-2007.2.01.jar
			fixes BZ2266 see gtr email date: 11:46 22nd Aug 2007 </li>
    	  </action>  
        
          <action dev="gtr" type="fix">
          <em>community-gtr-2241</em>This branch carries changes to the Maven project astrogrid/community/webapp.
          The sibling project astrogrid/community/server is also branched but there
          are no changes there. 
          There is also a new maven project: astrogrid/community/cagenerator. This latter project is already committed to the CVS trunk. 
          All the community artifacts, including the new cagenerator-app-xyz.jar, need to be be built and released. 
          This is a production version that I will be deploying around the project. 
          In this build, most of the artifacts take their version number from astrogrid/maven/base/project.properties, 
          which you will need to update, except cagenerator-app-xyz.jar which has the fixed version 2007.2. 
          Apart from the new application, the changes are to documentation. There are no changes to the service contract or to the delegate. 
          </action>
          <action dev="kmb" type="fix">
            Fix to fallback to backup registry appropriately for registry clients.  Change was in
            registry/client-lite jar only.  Does require a build of other components so it gets the new 
            registry client jar.
          </action>        
          <action dev="gtr" type="update">
            Branch Contracts_KMB_RegStoreValidate. Various changes and additions
            to schemata in support of the move to VOResource 1.0.
          </action>
           <action dev="kea" type="update/fix">
          Branch PAL_KEA_2062.
          Covers the following bugzilla tickets:
          2054, 2064, 2016, 2013, 2004, 1984, 2073, 2069, 2078, 1699, 2053,
          2059, 2091, 1949, 1956, 2019, 1831.
          </action>                 
          <action dev="gtr" type="update">
            Branch apps-gtr-2061. The project is refactored: maven-base is no
            longer used and the Java-class-application server is split into
            a separate sub-project from the server framework. A new sub-project
            for integration tests is added. In support of the integration tests,
            the server framework now adds a built-in application to its jar.
            This addresses issues 2061 and 2071.
          </action>
          
          <action dev="gtr" type="fix">
          <em>Branch apps-gtr-2051</em>: fix for BZ2051. This alters 
          astrogrid/applications/server to use the SchemaMap class from
          contracts (current) rather than the one from workflow-objects 
          (obsolete). The contracts jar is added as a dependency.
          </action>
          
          <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1942">
            Branch wo-gtr-1942. Deleted lots file for ease of make registry and CEA evolution.
          </action>  
          <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1981">
            Branch jes-gtr-1981. This breaks JES' dependence on the schema and
            WSDD files in workflow-objects. The build is simpler, the coupling
            is reduced and it allows the schemata to be dropped from workflow-objects
            in favour of the current ones in contracts.
          </action>          
    	  <action dev="gtr" type="add">
    	    <em>Branch common-gtr-1933.</em> I have added code to AstrogridAssert
            such that it reports line and column numbers when it finds invalidities
            while validating an XML file against a W3C XML schema.
            See bug 1945 before finishing this branch -CLQ 
    	  </action>		
          <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1966">
            Branch community-gtr-1966: fix the password-change and account-deletion
            features in the community component.
          </action>			
			<action dev="jl" type="add" issue="1496">
				Branch common-jl-1496
				Addition of new folder structure to cover xmlbeans generated for v1.0a1 of adql schema
				1496 was regarding the autogeneration of xmlbeans using maven build. the jar is currently hand generate, 
				ignore this branch until Jeff's update - CLQ
			</action>		
          <action dev="kea" type="fix">
            Branch PAL_KEA_1950.
            Fixes and enhancements for bugzilla tickets 1951 (disabling
            registration of samplestars plugin), 1957 (removing clear-status
            command), 1961 (showing endpoint for default registry in
            registration form box) and 2028 (fixing conesearch haversine
            maths).
          </action>		
		
		<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
          <em>Branch contracts-gtr-1922.</em> This branch replaces/reindexes
          missing schemata. Please see BZ1922 for detailed instructions about
          merging and publishing these fixes.
          see bug 1946 before finishing this branch -CLQ
    	</action> 
          <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1986">
            Branch cea-gtr-1986. This refactors the mavenation of astrogrid/applications
            to eliminate the use of XML schemata from workflow-objects and to
            loosen the coupling between the astrogrid/applications/* sub-projects.
            At the same time, I have encorporated the fix for BZ2010 concerning
            HTTP chunking. At this version, the CEA app-servers are cleared
            to run with Java 5 and Tomcat 5.5 and I now recommend those versions
            in the documentation.
          </action>		
          <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1800">
            Branch security-gtr-1800: fixes to astrogrid/security in respect of
            digital signatures. This cures two bugs: one where digital signature
            fails with a "signature is cryptographically invalid" error; one
            where services fail to load trusted certificates from a default
            location.
            This branch I can't find the tag name anywhere but Guy checked seems it's already in CVS head -CLQ
          </action>		
		<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
                  <em>Branch community-gtr-1954.</em> The community service is fixed internally in respect of handling the CA passphrase.
                  There are no changes to the web-service contracts or to the delegates, or to the resolver library.
		</action>
         <action dev="kea" type="add">
           <em>Branch PAL_KEA_1869 in astrogrid/pal, fixes after contracts 
             issues.</em>
       	</action>		
    	<action dev="dave" type="fix">
          <em>Branch dave-dev-200610091558.</em> The only changes should be to filestore/common and filestore/stress. The changes add a new config 
          property to enable chunked data transfer when sending data to myspace.(# Enable chunked data.)(#org.astrogrid.filestore.chunked.send=enabled)
          If the config property isn't set, then everything should behave as before. If the component (DSA or CEA) is running in JDK-1.4, then the 
          property is ignored, and it continues to behave as before. The change only takes effect if the component (DSA or CEA) is running in 
          JDK-1.5 _and_ the property is 'enabled'.If both conditions are met, then it will use the chunked data option to send data to the FileStore.
          This means that we can update all our existing DSA services without any side effects.
    	</action> 		
         <action dev="kea" type="add">
           <em>Branch PAL_KEA_1794 in astrogrid/pal AND ALSO astrogrid/xml,
             and branch SLI_KEA_1794 in astrogrid/slinger.</em>
        		Fixes and enhancements
        		for bugzilla tickets referenced in placeholder ticket 1794. 

            Note that the branch SLI_KEA_1794 DISABLES ALL JAR BUILDING IN
            THE SLINGER PROJECT;  the relevant slinger functionality has 
            been merged back into astrogrid/pal, which now builds a new jar 
            called astrogrid-pal-slinger which replaces all previous slinger 
            jars.  THE astrogrid/slinger PROJECT SHOULD NO LONGER BE REQUIRED
            OR USED.
       		</action>		
    		<action dev="clq" type="fix">
    		  <em>Branch clq_helpdocs_1570 helpdocs.</em> This branch had been merged in Aug 2006
    		</action> 		
    		<action dev="kmb" type="add">
    		  <em>Branch Contracts_KMB_XForms n astrogrid/contracts:</em>  Only merge in src/java and src/schema stuff.  Originally
    		  this branch was for Xforms stuff, but that has not gone through, but still added a lot of new schemas 1.0.
    		  This needs Guy Rixon approval though. - Kev will let me know when this is ready - CLQ
                  I have modified Kevin's branch slightly in the light of discussions: CEAService v0.3 instead of the more-ambitious
                  v1.0; astrogrid-software-site added to branch and schemata index updated; maven-base added to branch and version
                  of contracts raised to 2006.3.02. Note that astrogrid-software-site needs to be built after contracts. The branch is now
                  ready to merge - GTR
    		</action> 		
    		<action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1789, 1793">
          	Branch community-gtr-1722-2. The password-change code does better
          	checks on the old password. The registration type is pinned to use
         	 the v0.10 schema. There are also some fixes to the experimental CA.
    		</action>		
      	 	<action dev="kea" type="add">
        		<em>Branch PAL_KEA_1716 in astrogrid/pal AND ALSO astrogrid/xml:</em>
        		Fixes and enhancements
        		for bugzilla tickets referenced in placeholder ticket 1716. 
        		NOTE THAT THE astrogrid/xml BRANCH WAS CREATED SEPARATELY AND SHOULD
        		PROBABLY BE MERGED SEPARATELY, AFTER THE MAIN astrogrid/pal BRANCH.
       		</action>		
			<action dev="kmb" type="add">
    			<em>Branch Pal_KMB_XMLDB in astrogrid/pal:</em>  No Hurry.  Added back the xmldb but tried to make it more generic.  
				Before it was only tied to fits stuff now it is generic to work with any xmldb:api database.  
				Still lacks some commenting and docs but doubt anybody 
				will try to use this for awhile, I will try to add the docs at some other time. 
				<b>don't have to merge this branch, merged into PAL_KEA_1612 - 24-April-2006 - Catherine</b>
    		</action>		
    	<action dev="jl" type="add" issue="1652">
			Branch contracts-jl-1652
			Addition of new folder v1.0a1 to cover minor changes to official v1.0 adql schema
		</action>		
     		<action dev="kea" type="add">
           <em>Branch PAL_KEA_1771 in astrogrid/contracts (NB contracts
             project, NOT pal project!!!):</em>  Added two DSA metadoc
           schemata, and added entries for these in the SchemaMap.
    		</action>   			
    		<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    		  <em>Branch community-gtr-1722</em>: This updates the community project and introduces two new features: 
    		  1. ability for users to change their own password, requested by John in support of ROE installations;
    		  2. a prototype of the certificate authority that we need for secured access to service. 
    		  I haven't changed the web-service contracts, so I expect it to pass the integration tests as well as the last one. 
    		  The certificate-authority stuff is dormant in this version.  If people want to wake it up then they can configure it and experiment. 
    		  Otherwise, it doesn't get in the way of traditional operations. -- community is not deploying - clq 14th Aug.2006
    		</action>		
   		<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    		  <em>Branch security-gtr-1717</em>: fixes for BZ1717 "Digital signature does not work".
    		  There are changes to astrogrid/security and a one-line change in astrogrid/desktop/impl. These
    		  may be independent; the fix fof the current bug is in astrogrid/desktop/impl and the astrogrid/security change
    		  is to avoid future problems. However, the astrogrid/desktop/impl changes were tested with the astrogrid/security
    		  changes so the two should be merged at the same time.
    		</action>		
    	<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    		<em>Branch cea-gtr-1648:</em> fixes to astrogrid/contracts and astrogrid/applications/commandline to make it 
    		easier to validate application-description files. <strong>NB:</strong> the astrogrid-software-site module is
    		also updated and should be merged and built. Before building the latter component, its project.properties file
    		needs to be updated with the version of the contracts jar assigned in this merger.
    	</action>		
		   <action dev="gtr" type="add">
    	    	<em>branch apps-gtr-1617:</em> additions to the CEA infrastructure to support authentication with digital signature.
    	    	In the released configuration, CEA services authenticate and log user identities where signatures are present, but
    	    	do not enforce authorization policy.
    	   </action>
		   <action dev="kea" type="major_release">
          	 <em>Branch PAL_KEA_1612 in astrogrid/pal</em>  The initial
          	 release of DSA/catalog, a major revamping of PAL with a new
          	 Query model and SQL translation mechanism, improved interface
         	 and various incidental fixes.
           </action>
            <action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch apps=gtr-1651:</em> Fixes in astrogrid-applications to allow STILTS to run as a wrapped application.
    		</action>		
		    <action dev="gtr" type="add">
    			<em>Branch security-gtr-1593:</em> major changes to the security facade to support digital signatures.
    		</action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch dave-dev-200605311657:</em> fix the broken selftest page.
    		</action>
    		<action dev="jdt" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch cea-jdt-1639 in astrogrid/cea:</em>  No Hurry.  
    		</action>
			<action dev="gtr" type="add">
    			<em>Branch wb-gtr-1537:</em> Additions to the community/resolver project to allow logging in at a MyProxy service.
    			Please note that there are changes to the security and desktop projects also on these branch and these should <em>not</em>
    			be merged at this time; please merge only the changes in astrogrid/community.
    		</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch Reg_KMB_ErrorMessages in astrogrid/registry:</em>  This is only server side stuff no need to make new
				compiles for other components.  General tidy up with some error messages and a fix on the OAI
           		query to make it quicker, it had a couple of problems on full registries being slow because the xquery not
             	right or not good performance wise, its now correct.
    		</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch Reg_KMB_WBDocs1_Fix in astrogrid/registry:</em>  Okay you only need to get the 
				webapp/src/sebapp-java/astrogrid/registry/oai/XMLExistOAICatalog.java file, all the other files were merged in some weeks
				ago before release, but this one being a java file was decided to wait.  Now we can go ahead and merge it in since release 
				and demos are over.The fix is actually sort of important the query for oai was  not quite right and also slow on "full" 
				registries it is now been fixed.
    		</action>
			<action dev="kea" type="fix">
           <em>Branch PAL_KEA_1534 in BOTH astrogrid/pal and astrogrid/xml</em>  Preliminary work fixing adql parser and adding unit tests.  Have decided to move to xmlbeans-based parsing, so terminating this branch early.  Unit tests added/extended will be incorporated in new work. 
    		</action>
    		<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch apps-gtr-1489:</em> General tidying up of the deployment controls, which has involved
    			some heavy refactoring to work round Picocontainer problems. The deployer documentation is much
    			better now (IMHO), and the chance of getting duff registrations is less.
				Merged but jes and pal are not compiling see bug 1500, Rolled back for now until problem solved - CLQ
    		</action>
			<action dev="dave" type="fix">
				branch <em>dave-dev-200601051057</em> contains Multiple changes to the workshop code, Plus changes to JSP pages in :
                    <li>Community</li>
                    <li>FileManager</li>
                    <li>FileStore</li>
		    </action>
		<action dev="kmb" type="add, fix">
    			<em>Branch Reg_KMB_WSDLS (in astrogrid/registry):</em>  *Note: it should be okay to overwrite Dave's jsp's if you see a merge conflict there, notice his fix below* 
                 Now works with contracts for obtaining wsdls, along with other bug fixes for XQuery Search and when there 
                 are no results.  Plus new eXist db backend.  And some added features. And finally fixed jars in repository, will give you a zip file to help with that.<br />
                 Okay just made the zip file you should be able to find it at http://msslxv.mssl.ucl.ac.uk:8080/servlets-examples/downloads called reg_repository.zip this is a zip
                 file of all the jars that need to go into the maven repository.  Hopefully I did not miss any, but if so then just e-mail me it and I will send you the missing jars.<br />
    			<em>Branch Reg_KMB_WSDLS (in astrogrid/contracts):</em> New Filter to help construct wsdls and schemas, plus additional schemas added.<br />
    			<em>Branch REG_KMB_WSDLS (in astrogrid/xmldb "ALL CAPS"):</em> refactor of xmldb.<br />
    			<em>Branch Pal_KMB_WSDLS (in astrogrid/pal):</em> removed reference to xmldb for a short term, since xmldb was refactored.  Will add back at a later date currently
                   nothing in pal uses xmldb.
			    <p>Note: astrogrid/integrationTests/auto-integration project has also been changed (with branch Reg_KMB_WSDL) to fit the above changes - CLQ </p>
    		</action>	  
		<action dev="kea" type="fix">
               <em>Branch: KEA_PAL_1512</em><br/>
               Placeholder branch for a number of bugzilla ticket fixes
               on astrogrid/pal projects.
               <ul>
               <li>Bug 1508: reversed unit/ucd field order in registrations
               to be schema-compliant</li>
               <li>Bug 1479: VOTable "int" types should be "long"</li>
               <li>Bug 1480 : Fixed and re-enabled conesearch
               registration</li>
               <li>Bug 1515 : Added logoURL to registration, and 
               default logo to installations </li>
               <li>Generally tidied registration data and added 
               schemaLocation attributes for referenced schemata.</li>
               </ul>
     </action>

			<action dev="dave" type="fix">
				branch dave-dev-200512141139 contains 
				1) Minor changes to JSP pages in registry webapp (which will mean new version of registry)  
				2) New sub-project called workshop - contains maven build scripts for the workshop tomcats. 
		    </action>	 
			<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch jes-gtr-1462</em> Various incremental improvements: environment entries declared in wb.xml; 
    			new configuration editor; changes to logging; 
    			fixes for some broken unit tests; 
    			fixes for some code that was misrepresenting integration-test results.
    			This version seems to be fully compatible with the A/G v1.1 system.
    		</action>
		<action dev="kea" type="fix">
               <em>Branch: KEA_PAL_1474</em>
               Placeholder branch for a number of bugzilla ticket fixes.  NB This branch involves astrogrid/pal and astrogrid/status projects.
           </action>
			<action dev="gtr" type="add">
    			<em>Branch common-gtr-1459:</em> new code providing an editor for environment entries in
    			web applications.
    		</action>
		   <action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch contracts-gtr-1373:</em> I have fixed the <i>schemaLocation</i> attributes in the schemata to be
    			systematically relative to each other. There are now many extra schemata copied from IVOA and imported
    			schemata are taken from our tree not from the IVOA site. There is also a new stylesheet in astrogrid-software-site
    			to make the schemaLocation absolute again in the published schemata on the web-site.
    		</action>
			<action dev="jdt" type="fix">
				<em>Branch: Reg_JDT_anti1350</em>
				Removed the edits mistakenly applied to the registry installer during the merge of 1350.
			</action>
			<action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="1347"><em>Branch: por-jl-1374</em>
                This moves as much as I can at present from login to first use of MySpace.
                Still some room for improvement. Please note the branch name as compared with
                the bugzilla number. It is a typo when I was creating the branch.
    	</action> 	    
		<action dev="gtr" type="add">
    			<em>Branch architecture-gtr-1454-2:</em> I added the architecture document for system v1.1 to astrogrid-software-site.
    			I also fixed BZ1457, making the module buildable on Windows.
    		</action>
		<action dev="kmb" type="fix">
				<em>Branch: Reg_KMB_1350</em>
				Fixed a few areas.  Harvesting can now use specefic sets for certain registries determined in Properties.
                Server now always returns a VOResoruces element, it wasn't earlier for some reason.  Commented out some exceptions
                in the client area to make sure yet again it is backwards compatible. Finally  a small fix on jsp's to highlight invalid entries as well
                as deleted ones. <p>new version project.properties 1.212 </p>
			</action>
		<action dev="gtr" type="fix">
    			<em>Branch axis-gtr-1406:</em> I have upgraded everything to Axis 1.3 and fixed the major problems resulting plus some
    			small errors in AGINAB. On my test-system, 88.80% of integration tests are passed, compared with 85.19% on head. I think
    			a number of the remaining failures are bad tests. There are a few FileStore problems and some NPEs in JES that may be real
    			bugs.
    			see: http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/backupReports/integrationTests/20051104-17:27:18/junit-report.html  -- CLQ
    		</action>
			<action dev="clq" type="fix" issue="1367"><em>Branch: clq_reg_1367</em>
				Rolled back QueryRegistry.java to suits the backward compability issue. recompiled relevent components with projec.properties version 1.206
			</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1097"><em>Branch: Comm_KMB_1097</em>
				Added xerces (2.7.1) as a dependency and bundled in the webapp.  This fixes the problem with jdk1.5.
                Also small fix to Permission and GroupMember jsp pages so they would work correctly.
                Finally small doc change if they wanted to run community with a different db like mysql.
			</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1323"><em>Branch: Common_KMB_1323</em>
				1 file is changed on this branch (DomHelper) to look at the "*" namespace. if it does not find results for a element
                with no namespace as a parameter.  Requires to be merged with Registry.
			</action>  
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1097"><em>Branch: IntTests_KMB_1097</em>
				Actually just small fix tests for the registry, this branch was for fixing Permission page with community, but come
                to find out that was all in the community area nothing in auto-integration.
			</action>    	
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1323"><em>Branch: Reg_KMB_1323</em>
				Sorry forgot to re-branch from head, but that should not matter, just merge this one branch like any other branch.
                (there is no double branching :) )
                Common_KMB_1323, and IntTests_KMB_1097
                Added keywordSearch in the delegate (search elements though are on the server side.).  External tests added more for
                IVOA and finally fixed small bug with ListIdentifiers and XquerySearch.                
			</action>    	 
			<action dev="dave" type="fix"><em>Branch: dave-dev-200507251101</em>
				Added stress test to trigger OutOfMemoryError in FileStore transfers.
				Added JDK 1.5 fix for FileStoreOutputStream (client side).
				Removed deploy sub-project from the automatic build (tests need to be run manually).
			</action>
			<action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1337"><em>Branch: security-gtr-1337</em>. A major reworking of 
    	astrogrid/security to use digital signatures. Dependencies have changed greatly and there are
    	some new ones to be added to our Maven repository.
		    </action>
			<action dev="gtr" type="add" issue="1230" note="priority"> Documentation for astrogrid/applications/commandline.
    			Branch apps-gtr-1230 is incompatible with the changes from issue 1317 and should be abandoned.
    			Branch apps-gtr-1230-2 has the same new documentation and configuration changes as the former
    			branch but is branched after issue 1317 was merged; this one is OK to merge with head.
    		</action>
        </release>
		
		<release version="1.1" date="31/08/05" description="AG 1.1 Release">
			
			<action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="1198"><em>Branch: aginab_jdt_1198</em>
				Minor fix to the installer.
				The installer now modifies web.xml, rather than using context.xml, and thus works with Tomcat 4.
			</action> 	
			<action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1336"><em>Branch: por_jdt_1336</em>
				Minor fix to the installer.
				Added a warning to the installer that it must be run from the cmdline with
                extra memory (thanks, cocoon!).  Also changed the default reg and jes to point
                at the ones installed in Leicester.
			</action>  			
			<action  dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: Portal_KMB_1276_2 </em>
				Fix portal to fit new registry client-lite.
			</action>	
			<action dev="jl" type="fix"><em>Branch: com-jl-1315</em>
				Extended coverage of community unit tests in server subproject
			</action> 
			<action dev="pjn3" type="fix" issue="1307"><em>Branch: pjn_portalWF_1307</em>
				Can delete empty multiple cardinality parameter values
			</action> 
			<action dev="nww" type="fix"><em>Branch: cea-server-nww-improve-tests</em>
				Fixed failing unit tests and improved test coverage in cea-server
			</action>
			<action dev="pah" type="add" issue="1317"><em>Branch: cea_pah_1317</em>
				Commandline CEA will now remove any files associated with input parameters for a successful run. Also added jsp page to clean up all working files older than specified date.
			</action>
			<action dev="dave" type="fix"><em>Branch: dave-dev-200508090435</em>
				Fixed broken <xml/> tags in xdocs.
				Fixed change to CEA return type (String to Document).
				Added .cvsigore files where missing.
				Updated .cvsignore files to ignore target.
			</action>
			<action dev="mch" type="add" issue="1228"> Documentation for astrogrid/pal. Branch MCH_1228_Docs. </action>
			<action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="477"><em>Branch security-gtr-477-2:</em> a rearrangement of the tests for the 
    			security facade plus some trivial cleaning up of the production code. Both astrogrid/security and astrogrid/integrationTests
    		  are branched but only astrogrid/security has committed changes.</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: Reg_KMB_1323</em>
				added oai set support (plus has previous branch stuff which was: added xquery, caching, and unit tests), tagged b4_Kev_reg_app_commu
			</action>						
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: IntTest_KMB_1093</em>
				uses resetdb.jsp for community now only change was maven.xml. 
                Which should only be in the community-database(goal area) of maven.xml.
				(plus has previous branch stuff in it IntTest_KMB_FixTests branch), tagged b4_Kev_reg_app_commu 
			</action>					
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: Comm_KMB_1190</em>
				added dependency for registry caching for this merge.  
				Still factoring out the reset db on this branch. taged b4_Kev_reg_app_commu
			</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: App_KMB_1276</em>
				added dependency for registry caching for this merge. tagged b4_Kev_reg_app_commu
			</action>
			
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: IntTest_KMB_FixTests</em>
				 Branch under integrationTests/auto-integration, fixed some of the tests and no longer required 0.9 from the registry.
                 See next 2 branch Jes_KMB_1293, FM_KMB_1293_2 it is required for this merge.
			</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: Jes_KMB_1293</em>
                Changed it to no longer need 0.9 registry, and dropped castor for looking up registry identifier.
			</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: FM_KMB_1293_2</em>
               Drop the 0.9 need of the registry it works with anything now so no need for translation.
			</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: Portal_KMB_1276</em>
				added dependency for registry caching.
			</action>	
			<action dev="kmb" type="fix"><em>Branch: FS_KMB_1276</em>
				added dependency for registry caching for this merge.
			</action>
			<action dev="nww" type="fix"><em>Branch: jes-nww-review-unit-tests</em>
				 Fixes to improve unit test coverage and bring pass rate to 100% - don't merge if any unit tests fail.
			</action>
			<action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="1235"> <b>astrogrid/registry</b> Branch <em>Reg_KMB_Xforms2_Jun01</em>. Mainly added xforms plus small 
                correction on harvesting and OAI areas to correct duplicates being returned in OAI and not die badly on invalid harvesting of other registries. 
            </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1295">
                The CEA was able to pass parameters to applications in the wrong order.  This has been (partially) fixed.  See bugzilla report.
			</action>              
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix">
                A bug in the CEA (Java) server was registering the standard siap-image-fetch app with the wrong authorityID.
			</action>            
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="1275"> Improvements to the Registry Deployment Script - the installer now
                offers the user the option of storing the data outside the registry webapp, and also configures harvesting
                <b>astrogrid/registry</b> and 
                <b>astrogrid/integrationTests</b> 
			</action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="1182"> <b>astrogrid</b> Branch <em>aginab_jdt_1182</em> Minor changes to all the install scripts to make sure 
                that they work offline. You should see changes to aginab, and the deployment and installer folders of all components except community. The 
                changes are minor and shouldn't affect integration tests. 
			</action>            
			<action dev="pjn" type="add" > <b>astrogrid/desktop</b> Branch <em>desktop_pjn_14_6_5</em> Phil's new workbench for wf
			</action>
			<action dev="jl" type="add" issue="1173"> <b>astrogrid/portal</b> Branch <em>por-jl-1173</em>. Partly dependent upon bug 1279, in that filestores 
                created during an aginab build need to register with a relationship set within the registry. <ul> <li>Refinements to MySpace Explorer 
                controls</li> <li>Password change</li> <li>Ability to move files between filestores</li> </ul> 
		    </action>
            <action dev="pah" type="fix" issue="559"> Make all of the CEA servers self register with v10 compliant schema - This involved <ul><li>workflow 
                objects - wfo_pah_559b</li> <li>applications - cea_pah_559c </li> <li>jes - jes_pah_559b</li> <li>integration project - int_pah_559b</li> </ul> 
                </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="add"  version="1.0.1-b006pl"> <b>pal</b> Branch <em>dave-dev-200506281816</em>. One change to a property in 
                default.properties in pal/skycatserver. </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="add" version="1.0.1-b005pl"> <b>pal</b> Branch <em>dave-dev-200506281451</em>. Small change to the metadata 
                tools in PAL, no external side effects expected. </action>
            <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1255"> <b>astrogrid/contracts</b>, branch <em>contracts-gtr-1255</em>. More XML schemata added to the contracts 
                project so that they can be published in the software site. After this branch is merged, please rebuild the software site so that it picks up 
                the new schemata from the updated contracts jar. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="881"> Created a GUI installer for the registry, and plumbed it into AGINAB. See <a 
                href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/installers.html">installers</a> </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1177"> <b>astrogrid/filestore</b>, <b>astrogrid/filemanager</b>and <b>astrogrid/integrationTests</b> 
                <em>aginab_jdt_1177</em> Plumbed the FileStore and FileManager installers into AGINAB. The GUI installers and AGINAB now use the same script 
                for deployment, which has got to be a good thing. </action>
            <action dev="gtr" type="add" issue="1208"> <b>astrogrid/applications</b> Branch <em>cea-gtr-1208</em>. Enhancements to the JSPs for test-running an 
                application that support indirect input parameters. </action>
            <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1027"> Changes to TableMetaDoc.xsd to make it match the DSA software. Branch dsa-gtr-1027 Waiting for a big 
                merge from mch before proceeding. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1180"> <b>astrogrid/applications</b> and <b>astrogrid/integrationTests</b> <em>cea_jdt_1180</em> Minor bug 
                fixes to installer and build. Also fixes bug 1182 (for CEA only). Already merged. </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix" > <b>dave-dev-200506100249</b> Changes to navigate and header </action>
            <action dev="pjn3" type="fix" issue="1200"> <b>astrogrid/workflow + portal resources</b> Branch <em>portalRE_pjn_1200 + workflow_pjn_1200</em> Only 
                active tasks returned from registry in both workflow builder and resource browser. </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix" > <b>dave-dev-200506081212</b> - Bug fixes to the pal metadata generator.No external side effects 
                expected. </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix" > <b>dave-dev-200506071500</b> - Fixed double(), power() and circle() in PostgreSQL SQL writer. </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="add" issue="1111(again)"> <b>desktop-nww-1111</b> and <b>workflow-nww-1111</b> - added Applications component to ACR, and 
                Applications Launcher Proglet. This branch has already been merged into head once - hope merging it again doesn't cause trouble . </action>
            <action dev="pfo" type="add" issue="1217"> <b>portal_pjn_1225</b> - microbrowserResults.xsl change to handle tables with '+' in their name </action>
            <action dev="pjn3" type="add" issue="1217"> <b>portal_pjn_1217</b> - Webstart applications page added with more information. </action>
            <action dev="pjn3" type="add" issue="1226"> <b>portalRE_pjn_1226</b> - the smallest branch ever! - single missing space in ResourceAction.java 
                causing SAXParseException when muliple keyword search attempted when looking for catalogs. </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1193"> Branch <em>portalWF_1193_pjn</em> Fix for orig. bug #942 which has been over-written at some point since 
                Feb. </action>
            <action dev="pjn3" type="add" issue="1218"> <b>portal_pjn_1218</b> - Astrogrid status added to homepage plus ability to take portal 'out of action' 
                </action>
            <action dev="mch" type="fix" > <b>MCH-v1</b> v1.0 release for datacenter, slinger and xml projects. (awaiting for root tag from Martin) </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" > Doc_Template_KMB_May112005 - docs template for astrogrid/registry </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" > Doc_Template_KMB_May112005Comm - docs template for astrogrid/community </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1191"> portalWF_pjn_1191 - fixes for parameter indirect flag in workflow builder </action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.1" date="20/05/05" description="AG 1.0.1 Release">
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="383"> Since we're now on maven 1.0.2 I've refactored the property files to remove common and duplicated stuff 
                to maven-base. All components will need to be rebuilt after this merge, which should have no side effects. Branch maven_jdt_383: </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="1012"> <b>cea_jdt_1012</b> Created Installers for the CEA apps and plumbed them into AGINAB. Added some 
                cea-cmdline tests for windows. The windows tests will fail on Unix. Equally the Unix tests will fail on Windows, so we should get the same pass 
                rate in both environments. </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="add" issue="1169"> <b>portalWF_pjn_1169</b> 1169 is a minor layout change and also removes a couple of stylesheet 
                attributes that were causing transform errors that I spotted in the portal-core logs. However this also includes fix for bug#931 which is more 
                serious and relates to workflow builder/m-b interactions. </action>
            <action dev="pfo" type="fix" issue="1106"> <b>portal_pfo_1106</b> taking out the excute button for now from query page since it's not working 
                anyway. see bug 1172 </action>
            <action dev="pjn3" type="add" issue="1157"> <b>portal_pjn_1157</b> Parameterized workflows added to portal </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="add" issue="1111"> <b>desktop-nww-1111</b> Lots of minor fixes and improvements to desktop - mostly suggested by Nick. Plus 
                javadoc. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1056"> Added an about page to each war. Not going to rebuild just for this... will let it be absorbed naturally 
                as new builds take place. However if there are any problems building war files then this should be your first suspect! Contact jdt in case of 
                problems. Branch all_jdt_1056 </action>
            <action dev="pfo" type="fix" issue="1106"> Taken out cicle from query example. Branch portal_pfo_1106 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="1125"> Fix int tests to use new filemanager. Should see improvments in the applications tests. Branch 
                int-nww-1125 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="381"> (astrogrid/common) - now uses InputSource? for newDocument(string) Fixed bug with certain characters in 
                DOM. Branch Reg_KMB_381_WS </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="381"> (astrogrid/registry) - fixed several small bugs plus fixed relationship query now. Added removeResource 
                ability. Fixed major bug with embedded eXist. Branch Reg_KMB_381_WS </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="381"> (astrogrid/registry/webapp) - Yes I know a sub-branch below registry in the webapp directory. Small 
                changes to jsp pages and added removeResource. Xforms stuff is in there, but still hidden because it does not still quite work. Branch 
                Reg_KMB_381_Xforms </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="972"> (astrogrid/xmldb) - Small change to add removeResource and a few other storage type methods. Branch 
                Reg_KMB_972 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="972"> Fixed how it queries on relationships on the registry for groupmembership area. Branch Comm_KMB_381_WS 
                </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1008"> (astrogrid/integrationTests/auto-integration) - bad branch name should have been a different number. 
                Anyways small fixes to registry-entries. And added community stress test. Branch Reg_Comm_1008_Factor </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1004"> (astrogrid/filestore) - A small change to the xml to add relationship elements to it now. Branch 
                FS_KMB_1004_2 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="930"> (astrogrid/portal/workflow) Jobs displayed in date order. Branch portalWF_pjn_930 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="1035"> Fix for 'delete' and 'move' bugs. minor changes to filemanager-client and filemanager-server.bug. Branch 
                filemanager-nww-1035 </action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0" date="01/05/05" description="AG 1.0 Release">
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="748"> Removed footer from workflow and job status pages; help links now temporarily point to wikki help page. 
                Branch portal_pjn_748 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1100"> Ensure workflow credentials match user credentials on submit, set to those of current user if different. 
                Branch portalWF_1100_pjn </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="860"> Ability to delete optional parameters. Branch portalWF_pjn_860 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="1082"> Fix for 2 parameterized-workflow-builder bugs; fixes to make list-applications work with reg v10; added 
                'change store' 'copy' 'move' and 'rename' to vospace browser; split interfaces into separate packages, javadocs bug; also rebuilt filemanger 
                for it to take common 1035. Branch desktop-nww-1082 and workflow-nww-1082 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="959"> Major speed improvement to job status pages, plus removed some more trace. Branch portalWF_pjn_959 
                </action>
            <action dev="gtr" type="fix" issue="1074"> Declares environment entities in web.xml and adds activation-1.0.2.jar to the WAR. Branch 
                applications-gtr-1074 </action>
            <action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="1085"> Improvements to MySpace Explorer to ensure views were updated to show latest file activity of user. 
                Branch wor-jl-1085 </action>
            <action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="1046"> Improvements to MySpace Explorer to ensure views were updated to show latest file activity of user. 
                Branch por-jl-1046 (1046 is dependent upon 1085.) </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="766"> Changes to use Noels fix (jes-nww-776-again), plus changes to front page job list to remove delete/cancel 
                buttons, plus bug #771. Branch portal_pjn_766_again </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="776"> Fix for displaying list of jobs efficiently (jes-delegate and jes-server). Also some performance tweaks 
                to the jes server. NB - this requires the common-nww-1035 to be merged first. Branch jes-nww-776-again and workflow-objects-nww-776-again 
                </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="1035"> Moved some common classes from filemanager to common (nameGen package)., so they can be reused in jes. 
                Not expected to break anything. Filemanager client needs to be rebuilt at the same time. Branch common-nww-1035 </action>
            <action dev="clq" type="fix" issue="1120"> Same problmes of adding utils dependencies testing together. Branch 
                jes_clq_1120/wf_clq_1120/por_clq_1120 </action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.10.0" date="11/04/05" description="Post NAM release">
            <action dev="clq" type="fix" issue="1079"> Fixed storeclient/xml/status overwriting AG main site docs. Branch sc_clq_1079 </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="remove"> Removed MySpace related tests from integration. Branch dave-dev-200503181302 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="1008"> In astrogrid/community/webapp, added new JSP and web.xml files. Branch Comm_KMB_1008_2 </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix" issue="1059"> Fixed FileManager web.xml config settings. Branch dave-dev-200504041023 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1033"> slight tweak to the installer to make it less confusing. No effect on int tests. Branch 
                Filestore_jdt_1033 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1045"> trace turned off in worflow xsp's (job-list and job-status) Branch portalWF_pjn_1045 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1054"> links to workflow in current jobs list on homepage removed (login-pass.xsp, workflow sitemap and 
                job-list.xsl). Branch portal_pjn_1054 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1062"> The last test run's results are now saved, so even if you don't stick the baseline in cvs,you can 
                immediately see if anything has changed since last time you ran aginab. Branch aginab_jdt_1062. </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="972"> In astrogrid/registry, ONLY .JSP AND .WSDL files should be merged. Branch Reg_KMB_972_2 </action>
            <action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="908"> Portal myspace update and etc. Branch por-jl-908 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1047"> DesignAction changed to add missing ivo:// to indirect ivorns. Branch portalWF_pjn_1047 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="972"> In astrogrid/registry; harvest bug fixed, commenting better now; in astrogrid/xmldb; small tweak to let a 
                user get right at a XQueryService? or XPathQueryService?. Branch Reg_KMB_972 </action>
            <action dev="mch" type="add" > Rebuilds of PAL and slinger </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1044"> Adding wsdd from workflow-objects to wars. Branch pal_jdt_1044 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="1040"> New webstart links; only affects login-pass.xsp. Branch portalLogin_pjn_1040 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="1007"> Filemanager jsp. Branch FM_KMB_1007 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="1031"> Added an installer. Branch FMGR_JDT_1031 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1021"> Adjustments to the schema for configuring catalogues inside DSA. This is important for the current 
                deployments. Branch dsa-gtr-1021 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="1022"> Added a subproject to create a single jar from all the dependencies. Branch Slinger_jdt_1022 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1004"> Filestore jsp. Branch FS_KMB_1004 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="1005"> Added a deployment script and installer, integration tests should be unaffected. Branch JES_jdt_1005 
                </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix"> Community to register home space with FileManager; Changes to Community server and webapp; Changes to FileManager? 
                test; Added new integration test. Branch dave-dev-200503150513 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="966"> FileStore? Installer. No impact expected on Int Tests, since I've just added a couple of subprojects to 
                build the installer and deployment script. Branch FLSTR_JDT_966 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="972"> For integrationTests some entries changed for registry v10 upgrade. Branch Reg_KMB_972 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="986"> Upgraded jes to use groovy-beta-10 - which claims to fix some memory leaks. No impact expected on 
                integration tests. Branch jes-nww-986 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="972"> For registry and portal fixes a small harvest bug, it should work fine with TabularDB now. Branch 
                Reg_KMB_972 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" > Registry to v1.0. </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="994"> Adjusted int tests for cea and jes to use FileManager. Branch auto-integration-nww-994 </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix" issue="991"> Installation instructions for FileStore, also added a test suite for deployed services (see deploy 
                sub-project). Branch dave-dev-200503140252 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="686"> Infrastructure for dispatching other kinds of step / random select of servers to dispatch to / upgrade 
                picocontainer to 1.1 / moved from myspace to filemanager. Branch jes-nww-686 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="686"> Small tweak to support jes-nww-686. Branch common-nww-686 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="996"> Moves workflow over to using filemanager. Branch workflow-nww-996 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="995"> Moves scripting over to using filemanager. Branch scripting-nww-995 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="994"> Moved cea over to using fileManager. Branch cea-nww-994 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="838"> Added webstart applications link to home page (login-pass.xsp and minor tweak to 
                microbrowserResults.xsl). Branch portalWEBSTART_pjn_838 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="975"> Removed bogus dependency on astrogird-datacenter-client. Adjusted one deprecatred class so it won't be 
                missed. Don't expect it to effect anything else. Branch scripting-nww-975 </action>
            <action dev="nww/jdt" type="fix" issue="903/943"> Refactored client and server, implemented persistence for node metadata, node caching on client, 
                bundling on server, getIvorn() returns homespace-style Ivorns, WSDL-based SOAP (to be moved into contracts later), deprecated and implemented 
                Aladin Adapter interfaces. Branch filemanager-nww-jdt-903-943 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="965"> Alterations to config for filestores, new integration tests. Branch Auto-integration-nww-965 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="965"> Minor change to a mock to support filemanager build. Branch filestore-nww-965 </action>
            <action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="904"> JavaScript fix aimed at Windows IE6. MySpace micro-browser should now work. (BTW...I've not bothered to 
                include testing for files created with folders of the same name. I've tried but cannot reproduce the error now. Some extra checking 
                should/needs to be included, but this part will be rewritten soon in any case.) [accidently committed to head by jeff - small changes] Branch 
                por-jl-904 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="add" issue="979"> Branch portalRESOURCE_pjn_979 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="720"> Shift to new resource browser style for microbrowsers. Branch portalWF_pjn_720 </action>
            <action dev="gtr" type="add" issue="945"> First release of contracts project. Please merge only astrogrid/contracts and astrogrid-software-site; no 
                other parts of CVS need to change. Note that the build of the software site now has a dependency on the astrogrid-contracts jar in order to 
                publish the schemata. The contracts project needs to be added to the scheduled build and to be given a version number in the maven-base 
                properties. Branch gtr-contracts-BZ945 </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="942"> Prevent parameters being removed when step details change. Branch portalWF_PJN_942 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="889"> Branch REG_kmb_889/REG_kmb_889_2 </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="913"> Community (changes to web.xml from KMB); had to change LoginAction see version 1.35. Branch Reg_KMB_913 
                </action>
            <action dev="pah" type="fix" issue="910"> Some changes to the logging to make it easier to obtain usage metrics via a script from the log files. 
                Branch community_pah_910 </action>
            <action dev="pah" type="fix" issue="910"> Some changes to the logging to make it easier to obtain usage metrics via a script from the log files. 
                Branch myspace_pah_910 </action>
            <action dev="grt" type="fix" issue="879"> Viewer and editor for web.xml. Branch GTR-properties-BZ879 </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="fix"> Filemanager - Fixed failing server tests; Modified client and mock implementations to enable Portal dev on a full 
                mock service. Added full mock test sample, in example project. Changes to FileManager? client and server, added FileManager example. List of 
                changed files is here, no conflicts expected Build logs from local integration build docs and logs Integration test results on local machine 
                results. Branch dave-dev-200502010902 </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="fix" issue="903"> Branch filemanager-nww-903 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="936"> Community webapp not building under Maven 1.0.2. Branch COMM_JDT_936. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="933"> Registry not building under Maven 1.0.2 due to mismatch between package and directory structure. 
                Temporary fix. Branch POR_JDT_933 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="882"> 1. Rationalising config properties 2. Redirecting the logs to $CATALINA_HOME/logs to allow a clean 
                uninstall on windows 3. Creation of a graphical installer Note: the portal now requires the javaapp plugin for Maven. This can be installed by 
                executing maven -Dmaven.repo.remote= http://www.ibiblio.org,http://maven-plugins.sf.net/maven -DartifactId=javaapp -DgroupId= maven-plugins 
                -Dversion=1.3 plugin:download. </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" > Added configuration pages to FileStore webapp. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" > Created a graphical installer for the JES. Download from <a 
                href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/installers.html">here</a>. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="966"> Created a graphical installer for FileStore. Download from <a 
                href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/installers.html">here</a>. </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add"> New xmldb project for Registry. </action>
            <action dev="pah" type="fix" issue="910"> Added some logging to myspace and community </action>
            <action dev="gtr" type="add" > Created some jsp pages to allow admins to edit web.xmls when our components are deployed in Tomcat containers. JSP 
                pages have been put into the common project, but will need to be copied out by anyone that wants to use them in their wars. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="936"> Community now builds under Maven 1.0.2 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="933"> Registry now builds under Maven 1.0.2 </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" issue="882"> Created a graphical installer for the portal. Download from <a 
                href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/HEAD/installers.html">here</a>. </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="623"> Portal now undeploys cleanly. (fixed as part of bug 882) </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="909"> All config properties are now set in web.xml. Obsolete properties removed. </action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.8.0" date="02/02/04">
            <action dev="pah" type="fix" issue="540"> some very small config changes for the AVO demo </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="902"> An update to cea-http (ie SIAP applications), required following changes to the registry. </action>
            <action dev="nww" type="add" issue="890"> A fix to the myspace interface requested by the Aladin team. </action>
            <action dev="jl" type="fix" issue="670"> MySpace Explorer changes aimed largely at (1) eliminating errant nesting of folders. There appear to be 
                three sources for this error. Two have been eliminated. The other (introducing a file on the same level as a folder with the same name) I am 
                raising another bug for. But also included...(2) Tidied up headings and field names on micro-browser. and (3) Partly strengthened the error 
                checking on the m-b aswell. </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="fix" issue="787"> Pending.... </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="fix" issue="858"> Build problem in eXist for maven 1.0.1+ </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="605"> registry entries should be validated by a schema </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="613"> Need to add eXist permissiong with username and passwords more restrictive on the updates. </action>
            <action dev="kmb" type="add" issue="728"> Misc updates to community and registry. </action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.7.0" date="20/12/04" description="The release demonstrated at the AstroGrid consortium meeting">
            <action dev="kea" type="fix" issue="862"> Cosmetic tweak to portal </action>
            <action dev="gps" type="fix" issue="724"> myspace browser perf. enhancements </action>
            <action dev="pfo" type="fix" issue="845"> Pat's fixes for metadata WFS and registry browse </action>
            <action dev="pjn" type="fix" issue="839">
            </action>
        </release>
        <release version="Baseline-20041208" date="7/12/04">
            <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="776"> Summary objects return more data. </action>
            <action dev="mch" type="add"> New <a href="slinger">Slinger </a> project. </action>
            <action dev="nw" type="fix" issue="805"> Added some VOTable arithmetic </action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.7-b001g,0.7-b001h,0.7-b000r" date="25/11/04" description="FileManager Project Integrated">
            <action dev="dave" type="add" > FileManager project integrated into AGINAB </action>
            <action dev="jdt" type="remove" issue="781"> Second community. Deploying the second community was causing setup problems. Some tests associated 
                with the second community have obviously regressed. </action>
        </release>
        <release date="23/11/04" description="New projects">
            <action dev="nw" type="add" > New Aggregate project. </action>
            <action dev="dave" type="add" > New FileManager project. </action>
            <action dev="mch" type="add" > New Slinger project. </action>
        </release>
        <release version="astrogrid-portal-SNAPSHOT" date="16/11/04" description="head rebuild">
            <action dev="rtp" type="fix" issue="683" > Browsing for Tools picks up Extraneous Material </action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.6.0" date="14/11/04" description="Iteration 6 Release">
            <action dev="jdt" type="add" > The iteration 6 release offers a large number of enhancements and fixes over iteration 5, including: <ul> <li>A 
                graphical query builder</li> <li>SIAP services</li> <li>An enhanced mySpace Explorer</li> <li>Real datasets in AGINAB</li> <li>more.....</li> 
                </ul> </action>
        </release>
    </body>
</document>
