<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<document>
<properties>
	<author email="pah@jb.man.ac.uk">Paul Harrison</author>
	<title>Application Controller Installation Information</title>
</properties>

<body>
<section name="Common Execution Architecture Design">
    <subsection name="Introduction">
        <p>The Common Execution Architecture (CEA) is an attempt to create a reasonably small set of interfaces and schema
           to model how to execute a typical Astronomical application within the Virtual Observatory (VO). 
           In this context an application can be any process that consumes or produces data. </p>
           <p>The CEA has been primarily designed to work within a web services calling mechanism, although it is possible to have specific language bindings using the same interfaces. 
               For example Astrogrid has a java implementation of the interfaces that can be called directly from a java executable. </p>
        
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Motivation">
        <p>The primary motivating factors behind creating this architecture are;</p>
        <ul>
            <li>To create a uniform interface and model for an application and its parameters. This has twin benefits;
                <ol><li>It allows VO infrastructure writers a single model of an application that that have to code for.</li>
                    <li>Application writers know what they have to implement to be compatible with a VO Infrastructure.</li></ol>
                </li>
                <li>To provide a higher level description than WSDL can offer.
                    <ul>
                        <li>Restrict the almost limitless possibilities into a managable subset</li>
                        <li>Provide specific semantics for some astronomical quantities</li>
                        <li>Provide extra information not allowed in WSDL - e.g. default values, descriptions for use in a GUI etc. </li>
                    </ul>
                    
                    </li>
                    <li>To provide links with the VO Resource schema <a href="http://www.ivoa.net/twiki/bin/view/IVOA/IVOARegWp03#VOResource_a_Resource_Metadata_S">(See the IVOA WG)</a></li>
        </ul>
        
        
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="History">
        <p>The design for this architecture was started as part of the Workflow/Job Execution System within astogrid</p>
        
        <p>The <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org">Astrogrid</a> projects that implement parts of this architecture are</p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/snapshot/applications/">Applications Integration</a> This implements the core CEA functionality</li>
            <li><a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/snapshot/astrogrid-workflow-objects/">Workflow objects</a> which contains the schema and wsdl definitions</li>
            <li><a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/maven/docs/snapshot/jes/">Job Management System</a> This does not strictly implement part of the CEA, but does act as the component that invokes the CEA within AstroGrid</li>
        </ul>
        
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Actors">
        <ul>
            <li>Application - This is the process that is to be executed. It is defined as a process that can consume or create data. So this can include unix command line tools, database queries, web services etc.</li>
            <li>Common Execution Controller - this is the component that implements the CommonExecutionConnector interface, and actually controls the execution of the application. There can be various specialisms of this service, such as the CommandLineApplicationContoller, which can be configured to invoke a general unix command line tool, a WebServiceApplicationContoller, which can be configured to act as a proxy to call a general web service in a uniform manner</li>
            <li>Invoking process</li>
            <li>Monitoring Service - This is a service that the Common Execution Controller can report status to - it can of course be </li>
            <li>Storage Service</li>
        </ul>
    </subsection>
    
</section>
<section name="Formal Definition">
    <subsection name="Interactions">
        
        <img src="http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/applications/design/CEACallSequence.gif?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=image/gif"></img>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Interfaces">
         <subsubsection name="CommonExecutionConnector">
             <p>This is the main interface that is used to communicate</p>
             <p>The WSDL definition of this interface is stored in cvs at <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/CommonExecutionConnnector.wsdl?rev=HEAD">http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/CommonExecutionConnnector.wsdl?rev=HEAD</a></p>
             <iframe src="http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/CommonExecutionConnnector.wsdl?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/plain" width="100%" height="400">
this should display http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/CommonExecutionConnnector.wsdl?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/plain
</iframe>
             
         </subsubsection>
         <subsubsection name="JobMonitorService"></subsubsection>
             <p>The WSDL definition of this interface is stored in cvs at <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/JobMonitor.wsdl?rev=HEAD">http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/JobMonitor.wsdl?rev=HEAD</a></p>
             <iframe src="http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/JobMonitor.wsdl?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/plain" width="100%" height="400">
this should display http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/workflow-objects/wsdl/JobMonitor.wsdl?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/plain
</iframe>
        
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Objects">
        <subsubsection name="Application"></subsubsection>
        <p>uml model</p>
                <img src="http://www.astrogrid.org/viewcvs/*checkout*/astrogrid/applications/design/ceaApplication.gif?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=image/gif"/>
        <p>schema representation</p>
             <img src="ApplicationBase.png"></img>
        
        <subsubsection name="Parameter"></subsubsection>
        <p>Parameter Descriptions</p>
        
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Schema">
        <p>The schema associated with the CEA fall into two categories</p>
        <ol>
            <li>The schema used to define the messages within the CommonExecutionConnector interface</li>
            <li>The schema</li>
        </ol>
        <p>These schema are strongly interelated, which aids programming with automated object generation tools.</p>
    	
    </subsection>
    
</section>
<section name="Deployment">
    <subsection name="Typical Scenario"></subsection>
    <subsection name="Astrogrid Implementation"></subsection>
</section>
<section name="Future Directions">
    
</section>
</body>
</document>