<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author>Guy Rixon</author>
    <title>Installing a certificate authority</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Installing a certificate authority">
      <p>
       Members of your community will need identity certificates for access
       to controlled resources in the IVO. They need these certificates to
       use VOSpace, so every user needs one.
      </p>
      <p>
        Certificates are issued by certificate authorities (CA). Your users can
        get their certificates either from the national-level science CA in your
        region, or you can issue them yourself using a CA installed in your
        community software. 
      </p>
      <p>
        If you choose to install your own CA, follow the
        instructions on this page. The AstroGrid community software works
        with a specific kind of CA software provided by AstroGrid. The Java
        software for the CA is already built into your community web-application.
        You need to add a copy of the OpenSSL package and some files of
        credentials for the CA.
      </p>
      
      <subsection name="Install OpenSSL">
        <p>
          The AstroGrid CA software is a Java wrapper for the OpenSSL
          package. It assumes that the user running the community
          web-application - i.e. the account from which Tomcat is run - has
          the <i>openssl</i> executable programme on its path; you need to make
          sure that this is so.
        </p>
        <p>
          OpenSSL is installed by default with many operating systems.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Create and install the CA files">
        <p>
          The generic CA-software in the web-application is made to behave as
          <em>your</em> CA for your specific community by installing
          three configuration files.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>A root certificate.</li>
          <li>A private key.</li>
          <li>A file noting the serial number of the last certificate issued.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The CA's root certificate defines the formal name of the CA and that
          name defines the formal naming of the users.
        </p>
        <p>
          These files are produced by a CA-generator application supplied by
          AstroGrid. Please refer to the 
          <a href="CA-generator.html">documentation for the generator
          utility</a> which describes both how to run the utility and how 
          to pick the CA's formal name.
        </p>
        <p>
          When you have created the CA files, make a back-up copy of them, and
          keep that copy safe and private. If the files are lost or corrupted,
          or if the private key becomes known to strangers, then you will have
          to install a new CA and issue new certificates to all your members.
        </p>
        <p>
          Having generated the CA files, install them to these locations:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>/etc/grid-security/ca/cakey.pem</li>
          <li>/etc/grid-security/ca/cacert.pem</li>
          <li>/etc/grid-security/ca/ca.ser</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          These are the default locations expected by the community
          web-application. If you cannot use these locations (e.g. you
          do not have sufficient permission) then you can put the files
          elsewhere and tell the web-application where to look by changing
          these configuration keys:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>org.astrogrid.community.cakey</li>
          <li>/etc/grid-security/ca/cacert.pem</li>
          <li>org.astrogrid.community.caserial</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
      
    </section>
   </body>
</document>