<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community configure</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Configuration">
      
      <subsection name="Database">
        <p>
          This version of the community uses a HypersonicSQL database for which 
          the software is embedded in the community web-application. The database files
          are kept on disc in a filesystem accessible to the web application.
        </p>
        <p>
          The default location for the database files is the directory
          <em>/tmp/community-db/</em> and <em>you should consider carefully
          whether this is a safe and suitable location for your installation.</em>
          (On Solaris, /tmp is wiped at each reboot, so this is not a
          good place.)
        </p>
        <p>
          To relocate the database, edit the file 
          <em>WEB-INF/classes/astrogrid-community-database.xml</em>
          inside the deployed web application, following the instructions in
          that file's comments. Then restart the web application.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you have never before had a community database in your chosen 
          location, then you need to initialise it in order to create the
          empty tables. Use the "initialize-DB" link on the community's web 
          interface. <em>Don't</em> do this if you already have data in the
          database that you want to keep.
        </p>
        <p>
          When you have done all this, check the configuration by following
          the "view or change user accounts" link in the communty's web
          interface. You should see a note at the top of the page saying that
          the database is healthy.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Properties">
         <p>
           These are required for the community to function.
         </p>
           <ul>
               <li>org.astrogrid.community.ident - community identifier, must be changed.</li>
               <li>org.astrogrid.community.default.vospace - default vospace identifier (normally a filemanger)</li>
               <li>org.astrogrid.registry.query.endpoint - regustry query endpoint normally.</li>
               <li>org.astrogrid.registry.admin.endpoint - your publishing registry to send your registry. (may be or may not be the same as the query endpoint)</li>
           </ul>
         <p>
           These are to do with the certificate authority and MyProxy service, which are experimental.
           Don't bother setting these in a production community.
         </p>
         <dl>
           <dt>org.astrogrid.community.cacert</dt>
           <dd>The absolute name of the file containing the certificate authority's root certificate.
               The file should be a PEM file.</dd>
           <dt>org.astrogrid.community.cakey</dt>
           <dd>The absolute name of the file containing the certificate authority's private key.
               The file should be a PEM file. Don't make this file world-readable.</dd>
           <dt>org.astrogrid.community.caserial</dt>
           <dd>The absolute name of the file containing the certificate authority's serial-number
               record. The file should be a text file containing one line. That line contains the
               last serial number to be used in an issued certificate (which is zero for a new
               certificate authority, since the authority's own certificate is number zero).
               The number must be written as hexidecimal digits, padded on the left with zeros
               to make an even number of digits. E.g., 00, 01, 42 and 0fff are all valid;
               1 and 123 are not as they have odd numbers of digits.</dd>
           <dt>org.astrogrid.community.myproxy</dt>
           <dd>The absolute name of the directory in which MyProxy keeps its records. By
               convention, this is /var/myproxy for a MyProxy installation owned by root
               or $GLOBUS_LOCATION/var/myproxy for a MyProxy installation owned by another user.</dd>
         </dl>
         </subsection>
         
 
    </section>
   </body>
</document>