<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Release notes</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Release notes">
      <p>
        This version of the community has the following changes from version
        2006.2.
      </p>
      <subsection name="Password-changing facility">
        <p>
          Users may now change their own passwords; previously, only the 
          community administrators could change passwords.
        </p>
        <p>
          The password-changing facility is a page within the community
          web-application, linked from the menu on the community's front page.
          Passwords may not be changed from the AstroGrid workbenmch
          via the web service.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Passwords must be at least six characters long">
        <p>
          Starting with this release, all user passwords must be at least
          six characters long. This restriction is introduced for
          compatibility with MyProxy.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Experimental certificate authority and MyProxy linkage">
        <p>
          The community may now operate a certificate authority and use a
          MyProxy installation if appropriate software is installed on the
          community host. Certificates may be issued for community members
          and installed in MyProxy.
        </p>
        <p>
         To use the certificate authority, OpenSSL and MyProxy must be installed
         on the machine running the community web-application. The authority 
         itself must be manually installed in three files (private key,
         root certificate and serial-number record).
        </p>
        <p>
          There are some extra environment entries in the configuration that
          configure the certificate authority. These locate the files and
          directory noted above.
        </p>
        <p>
          This feature is currently experimental and should not be used in
          production communities. Service providers should not, at this stage,
          trust identities certified by this community software to be secure
          against misuse. The certificate authority should be made ready for
          production use in the next version of this component.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you want to experiment with the certificate authority, please
          contact Guy Rixon 
          (<a href="mailto:gtr@ast.cam.ac.uk">gtr@ast.cam.ac.uk</a>)
          To run a community without a certificate authority, simply do not
          install MyProxy and the certificate-authority files.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Web-page menus rearranged">
        <p>
          The menus in pages of the community web application have
          been rearranged. All the features useful in a production community
          are now available in the menu on the front page of the community.
          There are many other administration commands, all to do with features
          not yet used in real communities, and these are grouped on their
          own page.
        </p>
        <p>
          The "health" indicator for the commnity database is now shown in the
          title bar of the administration pages.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    </body>
</document>