<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Release notes: version 2008.1</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Release notes">
      
      <p>
        These are differences between version 2008.1 and version 2008.0.01.
      </p>
      
        <subsection name="Password and credential problems">
          <p>
            In the previous version, there were three major problems with 
            passwords and credentials:
          </p>
          <ul>
            <li>a user couldn't log in until he had reset his password 
            (<a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=2694">Bugzilla ticket 2694</a>);</li>
            <li>credentials for new accounts were created with wrong
              passwords and were therefore unavailable to users
            (<a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=2686">Bugzilla ticket 2694</a>);</li>
            <li>passwords on credentials were not being changed by the
              password-reset pages for either the user or community
            administrator (no ticket issued).</li>
          </ul>
          <p>
            These issues are all related and have been fixed by an emergency
            patch in the current version. This quick solution is imperfect and
            may give further problems as follows.
          </p>
          <p>
            A user's password is held in two places: in the community database
            and in the user's private-key file (in the community's credentials
            directory). These two passwords should have the same value, but a
            failed password-change could leave them with different values. 
            In this case, the user will
            probably be unable to log in and the password-change buttons
            won't work for either the user or the community administrator.
            If an account gets into this state, the administrator should:
          </p>
          <ol>
            <li>resissue the user's credentials;</li>
            <li>reset the user's password to a temporary value;</li>
            <li>contact the user, tell him the temporary password and ask him
            to change his password to his preferred value.</li>
          </ol>
          <p>
            (The first step synchronizes the passwords in the database and
            key file.)
          </p>
          <p>
            A better solution for password handling is known but will take
            some time to develop. It will be included in version 2008.2.
          </p>
       </subsection>
    </section>
    </body>
</document>