<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Release notes: 2008.1.01</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Release notes for community service 2008.1.01">
      
      <p>
        V2008.1.01 is released to cure a problem reported in operation. This
        release is recommended for all operators of communities.
        These are differences between version 2008.1.01 and 2008.1.
      </p>
      
      <subsection name="Generation of proxy certificates by accounts service">
        <p>
          In 2008.1, it was possible for the community to load incomplete 
          cryptography code. This showed up as an inability to decrypt the
          private-key files written by the community CA when changing passwords
          or signing proxy-certificates. In the current version, the community
          is forced to load suitable cryptographic libraries.
          This issue is 
          <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=2750">BZ2750</a>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Accounts service v2">
        <p>
          This release introduces v2 of the accounts protocol; v2008.1
          supported v1 of the accounts protocol. V2 is fully compatible with
          clients written for v1 of the protocol. Clients for this protocol will 
          be included in a later version of VODesktop and the Astro Runtime. 
        </p>
        <p>
          In v2, each account has a web resource called <i>home</i>, e.g.
          <i>http://some.domain/community/accounts/gtr/home</i>. This
          resource lists the location of the home-space (in VOSpace) for the
          account.
        </p>
        <p>
          In v2008.2 of the community service, this new accounts protocol
          will replace the SOAPy policy-manager service. At that time, all
          users will need to upgrade to clients that understand accounts
          protocol v2.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Registry-client updated">
        <p>
          The client code for the IVO registry has been updated to the latest release.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    </body>
</document>