<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Cache directory and job database</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="The cache directory and job database">
      <p>
    Asynchronous queries have their
    progress records recorded in a database -- the "job" database --
    and their results recorded in files
    on disc. This means that the results of queries persist across restarts of
    the service and that less bulk data is kept in memory. These arrangements
    apply to both the TAP and CEC interfaces, but not to cone searches.
  </p>
  <p>
    The database and the results files are kept in a single cache directory.
  </p>
  <p>
    The job database is entirely separate from the database
    of science data served by DSA/Catalogue. The job database is internal to
    the DSA/Catalogue web-application (it uses an embedded copy of HSQL). The
    web application writes frequently to the job database but will never
    write to the science database.
  </p>
  <subsection name="Setting the cache directory">
    <p>
      The cache directory is selected in <i>astrogrid.properties</i> by the
      property <i>datacenter.cache.directory</i>. You will
        need to think carefully when choosing the directory. This directory
        must be:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>a directory not used for any other purpose (so not the same
        place as the configuration directory, but it could be
        a sub-directory of the latter);</li>
        <li>on a disc local to the web server;</li>
        <li>unique to one DSA installation (if two DSA/Catalogue services
        share one cache directory then they can overwrite each other's files);</li>
        <li>writeable by the account running Tomcat;</li>
        <li>on a disc with enough space to store the results from 24hrs of
        queries (24 hours being the time after which queries are purged from the system);</li>
        <li>in a file system that survives reboots of the host (e.g. not
        <i>/tmp</i> if you have a Solaris host).</li>
      </ul>
    <p>
      You must create the cache directory manually when doing the installation.
      The web application doesn't create it for you.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Initializing the job database">
    <p>
      You should initialize the job database whenever you install a new copy
      of DSA/Catalogue. You might get away with using the existing database,
      but DSA upgrades may need a different database-schema and that can only
      be created by reinitialization.
    </p>
    <p>
      First, stop Tomcat. Now delete all files in the cache directory (don't
      delete the directory itself). You have to delete the files manually
      due to issues in the HSQL database-engine, and you can only do it when the
      database is not running, hence the need to have Tomcat stopped.
    </p>
    <p>
      Second, start Tomcat and go, with your web browser, to the administration
      pages of your installation. Follow the link
      "view job database" in the left-hand menu. The button for initialization
      is at the bottom of the page.
    </p>
  </subsection>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>