<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Annotating the metadoc file</title>
  </properties>
<body>

  <section name="Annotating the metadoc file">
    <p>
      The web-application generates the metadoc file for you but it cannot
      know the scientific details such as units, UCDs and column descriptions.
      You need to add these by editing the file.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you are a sysadmin, you may need an astronomer to help with
      this step.  Producing useful metadoc requires familiarity with
      astronomical rather than technical features of the data.
    </p>
    <p>
      The file needs to be valid XML after your changes or DSA will break.
      If you have XML tools then it would be sensible to validate the file
      after editing. If you don't have these tools then please just be careful!
      Note these points:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>don't change the structure of the XML tags;</li>
      <li>if you need the characters &amp;, &lt; or &gt; in your column names or
          descriptions then you have to escape them: write &amp;amp; &amp;lt; and
          &amp;gt; respectively;</li>
      <li>don't delete any XML elements except as noted below;</li>
      <li>don't add any elements.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      You'll see that tables and colums have both an <i>ID</i> attribute and
      a nested <i>name</i> element. The <i>ID</i> specifies the name known
      to the RDBMS; don't change these or you will break things. The <i>name</i>
      element is the name by which the table or column will be identified in
      the registry and in ADQL queries. You can change these to more meaningful
      names if you wish.
    </p>
    <p>
      The generated metadoc covers all the tables in the database and all the
      columns of each table. You should delete from the file the <i>table</i>
      structures for any tables that you don't want to expose in the service.
      Once you decide to keep a table, however, you shouldn't delete the
      metadata for any of its columns. (If you do so, DSA gets miserably confused
      by <i>SELECT * from ...</i> as it can't work out what to do with the
      unmapped columns in the results. This is arguably a bug and might get
      fixed in a later release.)
    </p>
    <p>
      You need to set the UCDs, descriptions and units (where appropriate)
      for each column. The IVOA provides information about
      <a href="http://cdsweb.u-strasbg.fr/UCD/old/">the UCD1 controlled vocabulary</a>
      and
      <a href="http://www.ivoa.net/Documents/latest/UCDlist.html">the UCD1+ controlled vocabulary</a>
      online. UCD 1+ is the more-useful vocabulary, but, sadly, the cone-search
      standard requires the older UCD 1, so please set both.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you want the cone-search facility, enable it on your tables of
      choice by setting the ConeSettings element on those tables.
    </p>
  </section>

</body>

</document>