<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Registration</title>
  </properties>
<body>

  <section name="Registration of your service">
    <p>
      Before your service is visible and useful for end users you must
      register it in the IVOA registry. This means that you add metadata
      describing the service and the database to a "publishing" registry (usually
      a local service) from where it is collated into a central "harvesting"
      registry.
    </p>
    <p>
      DSA/Catalogue needs many metadata, particularly concerning the
      database, and it would be tedious to enter them all by hand. Instead,
      you tell your service about the registry (you will have entered its
      location when you edited <i>astrogrid.properties</i>) and let it transfer
      the information for you.
    </p>
    <p>
      Before registering, please check that your service passes its self-tests.
      Please also <em>check carefully the entries in <i>astrogrid.properties</i>
      that set the location of the publishing registry and the name under which
      the service will be registered</em> (these are not checked in the self-tests).
    </p>
    <p>
      To register, follow the "manage registrations" link in the side-bar of
      the web-application pages. This takes you to a page of controls. Now follow
      the link in the table under the heading "register DSA". This makes
      a new registration for the service and gives you a form to edit the
      "core metadata" describing the service to human users. After this operation,
      the service is visible in the publishing registry but does not yet have the
      technical metadata that make it easy to use from tools like VODesktop.
    </p>
    <p>
      Now go back to the "manage registration" page. Follow the link in the
      table under the heading "update service metadata". There is no form to
      complete here; the registry and DSA service interact to load the
      machine-readable metadata. Your registration is now complete.
    </p>
    <p>
      There will now be some delay, typically about an hour, before the new
      registration is harvested from the publishing registry into the main
      registries. Once this is done, your service is visible to all users of
      the virtual observatory.
    </p>
  </section>

</body>

</document>