<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

<properties>
  <title>Release notes for DSA/Catalogue 2009.1</title>
</properties>

<body>
<section name="Release notes for DSA/Catalogue 2009.1">

<subsection name="Functionality Supported">
<ul>
<li>Input queries in ADQL 0.7.4 and ADQL 1.0 (excluding Region searches and XMATCH).</li>
<li>Standard AstroGrid CEC web service interface, supporting multiple interfaces (currently ADQL querying, asynchronous "conesearch" and simple "multicone" crossmatch)</li>
<li>Standard optional IVOA conesearch interface, now with optional access-control.</li>
<li>Standardised, tested JDBC access to at least the RDBMSs listed
<a href="docs/configure_step3.jsp">on this page</a>.
</li>
<li>Log views</li>
<li>Registry metadata views</li>
<li>Server status views</li>
<li>Pluggable architecture for back-end data access</li>
</ul>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Functionality Not Currently Supported">
<ul>
<li>ADQL Region queries, advanced joins etc.</li>
<li>Other service interfaces such as SkyNode.</li>
</ul>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Installation">
  <p>
    The installation procedure is unchanged from the previous version,
    <em>except</em> in respect of secured cone-searches for which extra
    configuration is needed in the web server.
  </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Upgrading from previous versions">
<p>
  To upgrade from DSA versions 2008.2 and 2008.2.xx, you will have to edit
  <i>astrogrid.properties</i> and add the following properties.
</p>
<ul>
 <li>datacentre.url.secure</li>
 <li>cone.search.secure</li>
 <li>cone.search.access.policy</li>
</ul>
<p>
  These all relate to the ability to secure your cone-search services using
  HTTPS, but you must set them even if you do not need to secure your services.
  Please see the comments in <i>default.properties</i> for advice on
  the appropriate values.
</p>

<p>
  The "metadoc" files (the metadata describing the database) have the same
  format as in the 2008.2 series and need not be changed.
</p>

<p>
  You can re-use the context file from the old installation.
</p>

<p>
If you are upgrading a very old installation,
we suggest creating a new <i>astrogrid.properties</i> starting from the
<i>default.properties</i> file supplied with the
DSA/catalog service (by copying in relevant properties from your old
configuration), rather than attempting to update your old
configuration file.
</p>

<p>
Additionally, we advise keeping a backup of your original DSA/catalog
installation and any configuration files associated with it, in case you
should encounter any problems running a newer DSA/catalog service against
your RDBMS and/or data.
</p>

<p>
Please contact
<a href="mailto:astrogrid_dsa@star.le.ac.uk">astrogrid_dsa@star.le.ac.uk</a>
for advice if you find that you cannot upgrade an old installation to
the newest DSA/catalog service.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection name="Bug reporting">

<p>
If you have found a suspected bug, check the bugzilla pages at
<a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla">http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla<a/>
for known bugs. You can submit new bugs to the bugzilla entry page.
Before filing a bug, we suggest you run the self-tests to verify that
your system is correctly configured.
Please include any error output or logs in the bug report, along with the
server URL and version of the DSA/catalogue server you have installed.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>
</body>

</document>
