<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Securing DSA/Catalogue</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Securing DSA/Catalogue">
      <p>
        The DSA/Catalogue web-application supports access control on several
        interfaces.
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>the CEC interface (using digital signatures on SOAP messages);</li>
        <li>the cone-search interfaces (using HTTPS with client certificates);</li>
        <li>the TAP interface (using HTTPS with client certificates);</li>
        <li>the administration interface (using local passwords).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        When installing DSA/Catalogue, you need to secure at least the
        administration interfaces, even if you do not wish to control access
        to the science interfaces. You also need to explicitly turn <em>off</em>
        the access control on interfaces where it is not needed.
      </p>
      <p>
        This page summarizes the configuration of access control. Instructions
        for setting up security are repeated in other pages describing
        configuration.
      </p>

      <subsection name="The administration password">
        <p>
          The password protection for the administration pages is administered
          by the <a href="tomcat.html">servlet container</a>. I.e., the
          accounts and passwords are defined the configuration of the container
          and are not part of the IVOA single-sign-on system. The DSA/Catalogue
          web-application instructs the container to allow administration
          access only for user-accounts with the role <i>dsaadmin</i>.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="HTTPS">
        <p>
          The HTTPS protocol is operated by the servlet container,
          <a href="tomcat.html">servlet container</a>. There are two
          configurations.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>If you want to protect (by encryption) the administration
          passwords but do not need to secure the cone-search or TAP
          interfaces</em> use HTTPS with client authentication <em>off</em>.</li>
          <li><em>If you want to secure the cone-search and/or TAP
          interfaces</em> use HTTPS with client authentication <em>on</em>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          In each case, the CEC interface must remain accessible through plain
          HTTP. Do not configure your servlet container for HTTPS alone.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Access policy">
        <p>
          An access policy determines authorization for an authenticated user
          to proceed with their requested access. In DSA/Catalogue, a policy
          is represented by a Java class chosen by configuration settings.
        </p>
        <p>
          These are the configuration settings for access policy:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt>cea.access.policy</dt>
          <dd>applies to the CEC interface;</dd>
          <dt>cone.search.access.policy</dt>
          <dd>applies to the cone-search interfaces, including multicone;</dd>
          <dt>tap.access.policy</dt>
          <dd>applies to the TAP interface.</dd>
        </dl>
        <p>
          These properties are set in
          <a href="astrogrid-properties.html"><i>astrogrid.properties</i></a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          You should normally set the same policy for these three properties. In
          each case, the value of the property is the fully-qualified name of
          the policy class.
        </p>
        <p>
          Three basic policy-classes are supplied with DSA/Catalogue:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt>org.astrogrid.security.authorization.OpenAccessPolicy</dt>
          <dd>allows all access;</dd>
          <dt>org.astrogrid.security.authorization.AuthenticatedAccessPolicy</dt>
          <dd>denies access to anonymous requests and requests that fail authentication;</dd>
          <dt>org.astrogrid.security.authorization.NoAccessPolicy</dt>
          <dd>denies all access, turning off a group of interfaces.</dd>
        </dl>
        <p>
          The default is <i>NoAccessPolicy</i>, so you must configure the policies
          explicitly to open your science interfaces.
        </p>
        <p>
          To allow access to selected users, you need to write your own policy
          class. Your policy could refer to a simple list of names, perhaps
          read from a file, or it could send out to an external security system
          on your site for a decision. For details, please see the programming
          notes for the AstroGrid security-library.
        </p>
        <p>
          If there is sufficient demand, some extra policy classes could be
          included in later releases of DSA/Catalogue. E.g., authorized
          users could be read from a configuration file installed with the
          web application, or from a database table.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="HTTP access to secured interfaces">
        <p>
          When you use HTTPS, the interfaces are still reachable via plain HTTP.
          The system's response to a plain-HTTP request to a secured interface
          depends on the type of interface.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>CEC: HTTP access is normal; security does not use HTTPS.</li>
          <li>Cone search and TAP: the web application receives the request
              but the access policy rejects it because it is anonymous.</li>
          <li>Administration: the request is accepted, the password
              authentication operates and the controls "work"; but the
              password is sent in clear text and could be copied by an attacker.</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Registration">
        <p>
          When the cone-search and/or TAP interfaces are secured with HTTPS,
          the registered URIs for these interfaces must be the HTTPS versions
          and not the normal, plain-HTTP URIs. This choice is controlled by
          the property <i>cone.seach.secure</i> which can be set either
          <i>true</i> to use HTTPS or <i>false</i> to use HTTP. The actual
          URIs are derived from the properties <i>datacenter.url</i> for the
          plain-HTTP URIs and <i>datacenter.url.secure</i> for the HTTPS URIs.
          These properties are set in
          <a href="astrogrid-properties.html"><i>astrogrid.properties</i></a>.
        </p>
      </subsection>

    </section>
  </body>

</document>