<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="astro.maven.docs@codon.demon.co.uk">Dave Morris</author>
		<title>Installation</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Installation">
			<subsection name="J2EE Container">
				<p>
					In theory, the FileManager WebApplication (war) can be installed in any <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/index.jsp">J2EE servlet</a> container.
				</p>
				<p>
					In practice, AstroGrid use <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-5.0-doc/index.html">Apache Tomcat</a> server in all of our testing and deployments.
					<br/>
					The following instructions have been tested with <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/downloads/downloads_tomcat-5.cgi">tomcat-5.0.28</a>.
					<br/>
					If anyone has experience of installing FileManager in a different J2EE container, please let us know.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Manual install">
				<p>
					The FileManager WebApplication (war) can be deployed manually, by placing the war file in the Tomcat <code>webapps</code> directory.
					<br/>
					Please refer to the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-5.0-doc/deployer-howto.html">Tomcat deployment</a> documentation for details.
				</p>
				<p>
					Or, the FileManager WebApplication (war) can be deployed using the Tomcat Manager tools.
					<br/>
					Please refer to the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-5.0-doc/manager-howto.html">Tomcat Manager</a> documentation for details.
				</p>
				<p>
					Once deployed, you will need to set the JNDI <a href="configure.html">configuration properties</a> for the FileManager service.
					<br/>
					The configuration properties can be set by adding <code>&lt;Environment&gt;</code> entries to the WebApplication context file.
					Alternatively, you can use the Tomcat Admin tools to configure the properties on-line.
					<br/>
					Please refer to the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-5.0-doc/config/context.html#Environment%20Entries">Tomcat</a> documentation for details.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Command-line install">
				<p>
					Please refer to <a href="../../installdocs/generic-admin.html">General info for AG installer</a>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="GUI install">
				<p>
					At the moment, I don't know how to drive the installer toolkit for the FileManager.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
