<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Release notes: version 2009.1</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Release notes">
      <p>
        These notes cover 2009.1 and all sub-versions, including pre-release
        versions. Changes are relative to the last version of the 2008.2
        series.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Integration with VOSpace">
      <p><em>Since v2009.1.a01.</em></p>
      <p>
        This release can use a VOSpace-1.1 web-service to create home-spaces;
        previous versions could only create home-spaces in a MySpace service.
      </p>
      <p>
        To use this feature, set the configuration property
        <i>org.astrogrid.community.default.vospace</i> to the folder
        in your VOSpace that is to contain homespaces. E.g.:
        <i>vos://org.astrogrid.test!cambridge-test-vospace/home</i>.
        If the value of this property is a VOSpace locator
        (beginning <i>vos://</i>), then the community will use the VOSpace
        interface. If you enter instead an IVORN (a URI beginning
        <i>ivo://</i>), then the community will assume that it points to
        a MySpace service.
      </p>
      <p>
        An AstroGrid VOSpace deployment
        offers both MySpace and VOSpace interfaces on the same file-tree.
        Therefore, it is possible to switch a user-account from MySpace
        to VOSpace access by changing the URI of the home-space. However,
        the structure of the URIs differs so you can't just change the
        scheme prefix. Consult your VOSpace operator for possible
        translations.
      </p>
      <p>
        You can have some accounts with MySpace home-spaces and some
        with VOSpace home-spaces. Therefore, you can convert your
        user-accounts progressively.
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="MySpace deprecated">
      <p><em>Since v2009.1.a01</em></p>
      <p>
        The MySpace interface to the storage is now deprecated and will
        be discontinued soon. All new account should use the VOSpace
        interface. and old accounts should be converted as soon as
        possible.
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Changes to administration controls">
      <p><em>Since v2009.1.a01.</em></p>
      <p>
        When a basic account is created, no home-space is now
        allocated. You have to allocate the home-space as a
        separate operation.
      </p>
      <p>
        In order to allocate a home-space via the VOSpace interface,
        the user must first be issued with credentials. The home-space
        is then formally owned by the identity in those credentials.
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Uploading credentials">
      <p><em>Since v2009.1.a01</em></p>
      <p>
        Users with credentials from external certificate-authorities
        may now upload them to the community. The controls for this
        are on the community web-browser interface; they are public,
        protected by the account password. The credentials must be
        presented in a PKCS#12 key-store file.
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Web-browser interface">
      <p><em>Since v2009.1.a01</em></p>
      <p>
        The web-browser interface to the community, for administration,
        changing passwords and uploading credentials, is now registered
        in the IVOA registry.
      </p>
      <p><em>Since v2009.1.a07</em></p>
      <p>
        The documents linked from the web-browser interface are no longer
        embedded in the community web-application. The "document index" and
        "release notes" links now lead to an external site. The live pages in
        the community web-application have a different, yellow background to
        distinguish them.
      </p>
      </subsection>
      
    </section>
    </body>
</document>