<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Release notes: 2008.2</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Release notes for community web-appplication 2008.2">
      
      <p>
        These notes describe changes between v2008.1.02 and v2008.2.
      </p>
      
      <subsection name="Feature: version 3 of accounts protocol">
        <p>
          This release supports version 3 of the accounts protocol. With this
          upgrade, it is possible for a client to change a user's password.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Feature: backing up the community">
        <p>
          This release introduces a back-up function for the user credentials
          and community database.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Compatibility warning: retirement of SOAPy 'security service'">
        <p>
          The community service called "security service" has been removed from
          the web application. This (SOAP) web service was the only sign-on mechanism
          in the 2007 releases and was deprecated after the introduction of the
          accounts protocol with the 2008.0 release. Since then all usable
          copies of VODesktop and the Astro Runtime have adopted the accounts
          protocol and the older service is obsolete.
        </p>
        <p>
          However, it was recently discovered that the file-manager-delegate
          library still has one call to the obsolete service, and this call was
          actually being used in VODesktop, causing 
          <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=2815">bug 2815</a>.
          This is now fixed, but versions of VODesktop before 2008.1.1 will not
          work with community 2008.2.
        </p>
        <p>
          Tests show that Topcat is not affected by this issue. Code inspection
          shows that the MySpace clients embedded in DSA and CEA services
          can't be affected since they don't have user-name and password to
          send to a community service.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Compatibility warning: revision to configuration of community database">
        <p>
          This version of the community web-application uses Castor v1.2, 
          an upgrade from v0.9.5 using in Community 2008.1. The upgrade entrains
          a small change to the XML configuration of the community database.
        </p>
        <p>
          Two changes are needed to existing configurations:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Wrap the <i>database</i> element in a <i>jdo-conf</i> element;</li>
          <li>add a <i>transaction-demarcation</i> element with 
          attribute <i>mode="local"</i> as a child of the <i>jdo-conf</i>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The sample configuration in the web application has already been altered
          to suit.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Bug fix: encoding of passwords">
        <p>
          V2008.1.01 and earlier had a serious problem in the handling of
          passwords: see 
          <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=2809">bugzilla</a>
          for details. That problem now fixed.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Bug fix: suprious failures of permissions self-test">
        <p>
          <a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=2628">Bug 2628</a>,
          concerning failed tests of the CA credentials, is fixed.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      
    </section>
    </body>
</document>