<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Release notes: version 2008.0</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Release notes">
      
      <p>
        These are differences between version 2008.0 and the last release
        of 2007.
      </p>
      
        <subsection name="Accounts service">
          <p>
            The new "accounts" service is a RESTful web-service that is gradually
            taking over from the SOAP services. In the current version, the
            accounts service replaces MyProxy and the Security service as the
            means for users to sign on and receive certificates.
          </p>
          <p>
            A client for the accounts service is built into the community
            resolver library, starting at version 2008.0a7. Clients using this
            library will automatically use the accounts service if they find it
            registered. In practice, this means that versions of VODesktop from
            2008.1 onward will typically log in using the accounts service.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="MyProxy">
        <p>
          You are no longer recommended to run a MyProxy service for new
          communities. The accounts service takes over MyProxy's function and
          does so on a less-troublesome port.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sites that have already installed MyProxy may go on using it.
          MyProxy support will be retained in the AR and versions of the AR
          from 2008.1 will use MyProxy as a second choice if they cannot
          find an accounts service. To use MyProxy, you would need to hand-edit
          the community's registration, adding a MyProxy capability and
          possibly removing the capability for the accounts service. MyProxy
          and the accounts service can run in parallel, working from the
          same user-credentials.
        </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Certificate authority">
          <p>
            The certificate authority is now a required part of the community
            rather than an experimental option.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="HTTPS">
          <p>
            The community requires a copy of Tomcat with HTTPS enabled in order
            that passwords may be exchanged safely.
          </p>
          <p>
            Initially, only the accounts web-service uses HTTPS, in order to
            protect the users' personal passwords. The adminstration interface
            uses plain HTTP, but this will be changed in a later version.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Registry compatibility">
          <p>
            This release has been revised to work with registries providing
            registry interface v1.0 and containing documents based on
            VOResource v1.0. A registry of this kind is required in order to
            publish the community service. A further registry of this kind is
            required at run-time in order that the community amy look up external
            services. This version of community cannot work with the older
            registries (registry interface v0.1 and VOResource v0.10).
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="VOSpace compatibility">
        <p>
          This community software is intended to work with the first
          release of AstroGrid's VOSpace product. It does so using the
          legacy "file manager" interface in the latter software.
        </p>
        <p>
          Therefore, the current release is expected to work with old
          installations of AstroGrid MySpace. However, this combination
          is not officially supported.
        </p>
        <p>
          This community release does <em>not</em> work with IVOA's VOSpace
          interface. That interface will be introduced in a later release.
        </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Root ownership">
          <p>
            The standard installation now requires that Tomcat be run from
            the root account. This allows Tomcat to use ports 80 and 443, which
            are preferred to port 8080 and 8443 due to firewall problems. Running
            as root also gives better protection to the stored credentials.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Revised installation procedure">
          <p>
            A new installation-procedure has been documented. This standard
            procedure is designed to avoid the worst weaknesses and instability
            of Apache Tomcat while also giving the simplest installation.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Reuse of files from old installations">
          <p>
            The new software should work with the community database from
            any previous version.
          </p>
          <p>
            Certificate-authority files (CA key, certificate and serial-number
            record) that were used with the 2007.x community-software work
            with the current release. If you follow the new, standard layout of 
            files, then you will have to put the CA files (or copies of them) in
            a new location.
          </p>
          <p>
            User-credential files from all old versions may be reused with the
            current release. If you want to use the standard layout of files
            then you will have to move or copy your credential files. If you
            have a working community with symbiotic MyProxy service then you
            should <em>not</em> move the user credentials to the new location.
            Instead, change the community configuration to find the credentials
            where they are currently kept.
          </p>
          <p>
            The context file from old installations is <em>not</em>
            fully compatible with the new software. Using your old context
            file as a reference, you should make a new one starting from the
            supplied template; see the standard installation-sequence. Note that
            the new release doesn't use a JNDI <i>DataSource</i> object to
            locate its database; the associated configuration is dropped from
            the context file.
          </p>
          <p>
            The current release uses a database-configuration file and
            requires you to edit it to locate the community database. This
            file is not apparent in earlier versions (it's in there, but not
            as something that you can change).
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Self-tests">
          <p>
            Some self-tests have been added to the administration interface.
            These are only a partial test of the installation, but they
            may help to find some configuration problems.
          </p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
    </body>
</document>