<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community: standard directory structure</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Standard directory structure">
      <p>
        The community has files for configuration, for the database of
        users, for its certificate authority and for user credentals.
        All these files are kept outside the Tomcat directory tree in
        order that they survive reinstallations of Tomcat and the community
        web-application.
      </p>
      <p>
        You should create these directories:
      </p>
      <pre>
  /astrogrid/community/
  /astrogrid/community/db/
  /astrogrid/community/pem/
  /astrogrid/community/ca/
      </pre>
      <p>
        They should all be owned by root.
      </p>
      <p>
        The <i>db</i> sub-directory is where the community keeps its database
        files, both the configuration files which you will install and the
        actual data files.
      </p>
      <p>
        The <i>pem</i> directory is where the community keeps user-credentials
        generated by its certificate authority (PEM stands for Privacy Enhanced
        Mail and is the type of credential file to be stored here).
      </p>
      <p>
        The <i>ca</i> directory is where the community keeps the root
        credentials of its certificate authority (CA). You will later install these
        credentials. There will be three files: the CA's private key, the CA's
        root certificate and the a file recording the last serial-number used in
        a certificate.
      </p>
      <p>
        All the information in these directories is important for operation
        of the community. You should make sure that they are all backed up.
      </p>
    </section>
   </body>
</document>