<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community: standard configuration of the database</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Database installation">
      <p>
        The community web-application includes the HypersonicSQL RDBMS. The
        Java code connects to the RDBMS through the Castor JDO library.
        The latter needs to be told where to find the data files and how to
        map database records to Java objects. You do this by installing two
        XML configuration-files.
      </p>
      <p>
        Download the sample copy of the main configuration file ("DB configuration"
        on the templates manu of this page). If you are
        using the <a href="standard-directories.html">standard directory-layout</a>
        then this sample is correct for your community. If you are using a
        variant set of directories then you must edit the file to tell the
        database where to find its data files. The sample file contains
        comments telling you what to change. Install the configuration file at
        <i>/astrogrid/community/db/astrogrid-community-database.xml</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you are upgrading the software for an existing comunity, and if the
        previous version was 2008.1.02 or older, then you must change the
        structure of your database-configuration file to suit the current
        software (this change is forced on us by changes in 3rd-party software).
        Please see the
        <a href="release-notes-2008.2.a01.html">release notes for Community v2008.2.a01</a>
        for instructions, and the example configuration as a guide.
        If you have successfuly run a community with any version of the web
        application from 2008.2.a01 onward, then your current
        database-configuration file is structurally correct.
      </p>
      <p>
        Download the mapping file ("DB mapping" in the templates menu of this page).
        This is the same for all installations of
        the community. Install the mapping file at
        <i>/astrogrid/community/db/astrogrid-community-mapping.xml</i> (it
        must always be in the same directory as the database configuration-file).
      </p>
      <p>
        If you are upgrading an existing community with a populated database, then
        you will need to copy the data files from the previous installation. (If
        you are using the
        <a href="standard-directories.html">standard directory-layout</a>
        then your database files stay in the same place during the upgrade and
        do not need to be copied.)
        There are two files to copy: <i>org.astrogrid.community.properties</i>
        and <i>org.astrogrid.community.script</i>. Put them both in
        <i>/astrogrid/community/db</i>. The actual contents of the database are
        in <i>org.astrogrid.community.script</i>.
      </p>
    </section>
   </body>
</document>