<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>AstroGrid community: variations on the standard directory-layout</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    <section name="Variations on the standard directory-layout">
      <p>
        If you do not wish to follow the standard directory-layout, you
        have considerable freedom in how you disperse the community files on
        disc. The following are variations that should work.
      </p>
      <p>
        You can choose a different root directory to <i>/astrogrid/community</i>,
        keeping the same structure below your chosen root.
      </p>
      <p>
        You can put each sub-directory under a different root directory, e.g.
      </p>
      <pre>
  /foo/community-db
  /bar/community-pem
  /baz/community-ca
      </pre>
      <p>
        You can put the three certificate-authority files in different
        directories. This variant may be useful if you already have CA
        files and have a strongly-enforced policy for where they live. The
        CA needs only read access to the key and certificate files, but
        read-write access to the serial-number file.
      </p>
      <p>
        You can put the configuration files for the community database in
        a different directory to the data files.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you run the community with an NCSA MyProxy server, then the directory
        <i>/astrogrid/community/pem</i> must be changed to the directory
        where the MyProxy server expects to find credentials (probably
        <i>/var/myproxy/share</i> but check the Myproxy manual). Alternatively,
        you can reconfigure MyProxy to read credentials from 
        <i>/astrogrid/community/pem</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
        One possible installation policy is to gather all the read-only
        files into a structure on a disc that is mounted read-only for
        operation. The files that the community both reads and writes
        are then on a separate disc.
      </p>
    </section>
   </body>
</document>