<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--+
    | Maven project description for the AstroGrid registry client components.
    +-->
<project xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
	xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="maven-project.xsd">
	<!--+
        | Extend the top level project descriptor.
        +-->
	<extend>./maven/project.xml</extend>
	<!--+
        | The short name of the project.
        | This is used when naming jars and distribution files.
        +-->
	<id>astrogrid-registry-master</id>
	<!--+
        | The full name of the project.
        | This is used when generating JavaDoc titles.
        +-->
	<name>AstroGrid registry</name>
	<description> <![CDATA[
	<p>
		<br />
		The IVOA Registry will allow an astronomer or service to be able to locate, get details of, and make use of, any resource located anywhere in the IVO space, ie in any Virtual Observatory. The IVOA will define the protocols and standards whereby different registry services are able to interoperate and thereby realise this goal. This page is information about the Astrogrid Registry service that conforms to those standards.
		<br />
There are a few specifications that the IVOA Registry has defined and you can find reference to that on the main IVOA Registry page: http://www.ivoa.net/twiki/bin/view/IVOA/IvoaResReg or at the main document repository at: http://www.ivoa.net/Documents.  There are mainly two areas:
<br />
    * Metadata - Which is a set of XML schemas describing 'Resources'.  Such as Services, Data Sets, Applications, and others.
<br />
    * Interface Specification - is a specification that details how the registry can be searched and how registries must interoperate with other registries.
<br />

There are two main types of Registries.  A 'Publishing' registry which must publish its data in accordance with the Interface specification, and a 'Full' Registry which must be able to hold all 'Resource' records comply with the search interface and be able to harvest other registries hence it must conform with the Interface Specification fully.  Though not as common there is also a 'Specialized' registry that is the same as a 'Full' registry just does not hold all Resource records.
<br />
The Astrogrid Registry conforms fully with the IVOA specification and can be setup as just a 'Publishing', 'Full' or 'Special' registry all installs have a Search interface for searching and a Harvest interface for publishing. 
	
		<br />
		<b>See the webapp section for documentation on how to install the registry and how it runs</b>		

	</p>
	<p>
		The registry gathers its information from either user input by file, url, or through the portal.  Or more commonly most metadata is
		obtainged through harvesting.  Which is a means of reading in a url or web service described in the metadata (usually of another Registry)
		and make a call to extract the metadata from one resource and place it in the current registry.
	</p>
	<section name="Registry known to Astrogrid">
	<p>
		Retgistry main objective is for the use of querying the registry to gain information about Resource or Resources to be
		obtained by other registries.  This information can then be used for these other components.  Here is a quick look at other
		components and the use they have for Registry.
		<ul>
			<li>Workflow - To Discover Services such as Applications to be used.</li>
			<li>Data Center (Actually Data Sets)- To upload metadata to the registry.</li>
			<li>Data Query - To obtain information about Data Sets for particular querying on a data center.</li>
			<li>Application Controller - To uplaod metadata to the registry.</li>
			<li>Community - To obtain a users Myspace/VOSpace location.</li>
			<li>Myspace - To obtain Myspace/VOSpace servers, and remote Myspace services usually via the Community.</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	</section>	
		]]> </description>
	<shortDescription>Astrogrid Registry</shortDescription>
	<build>
		<sourceDirectory/>
		<unitTestSourceDirectory/>
	</build>
</project>